<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Salus Britannica, or, The safety of the Protestant religion against all the present apprehensions of popery fully discust and proved wherein all the popular fears and imaginary dangers are wholly dissipated and confuted, against all objections whatever.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 214KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61216</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">9011766</idno>
  <idno type="VID">42213</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248508773</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing S511</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25540</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">09011766</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61216)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42213)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1293:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Salus Britannica, or, The safety of the Protestant religion against all the present apprehensions of popery fully discust and proved wherein all the popular fears and imaginary dangers are wholly dissipated and confuted, against all objections whatever.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Graves,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Anti-Catholicism --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42213:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42213:1"/>
            <p>Salus Britannica: OR, THE SAFETY OF THE Protestant Religion, Against all the present APPREHENSIONS OF POPERY Fully Discust and Proved.</p>
            <p>Wherein all the Popular Fears, and Imaginary Dangers, are wholly Dissipated and Confuted, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all Objections whatever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Graves.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42213:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:42213:2"/>
            <head>Salus Britannica: OR, THE SAFETY OF THE Protestant Religion, Against all the present Apprehensions of POPERY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>REAT and Terrible have been the pretended Dangers of <hi>Popery,</hi> espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for some late Years; and Indefatigable have been the <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sorceries</hi> of <hi>Faction</hi> and <hi>Villany</hi> to conjure up this Hideous <hi>Apparition,</hi> to fright the deluded Multitude, both out of their <hi>Wits</hi> and their <hi>Allegiance.</hi> But not to Insist much upon the <hi>Grosser Impostures</hi> of Fanatical <hi>Incendaries,</hi> such as the Old most <hi>Impudent</hi> Cheat of turning both the Best of PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TESANT-KINGS, and a <hi>Protestant</hi> CHURCH it self into <hi>Popish</hi> and <hi>Antichristian;</hi> hoping that the most <hi>Vulgar</hi> Eyes and <hi>Humblest</hi> Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities have fully seen through so Diabolical a <hi>Delusion:</hi> However, as there still remains upon some Weaker Understandings, and Unsatisfied Minds, a Terror yet unvanquish'd; The business of this Treatise is to Examine what <hi>National Operation</hi> or <hi>Influence</hi> a Real <hi>Popish</hi> Crown'd Head can have over the <hi>Lives, Liberties</hi> or <hi>Estatss</hi> of <hi>Englishmen,</hi> as <hi>now <hi>Enjoy'd,</hi>
               </hi> and the Religion of the Kingdom, as at present Establish'd; and by confuting even the most <hi>Substantial</hi> of their Imagin'd Dangers, dissipate those <hi>False Fears</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> which no Man possibly (I mean in my humble Station) has more unhappily rais'd than my self.</p>
            <p>The wonderful <hi>State-Convulsions</hi> that <hi>Popery</hi> (or rather the <hi>Sophistry</hi> of Scriblers upon that <hi>Theme) <hi>seems</hi>
               </hi> to threaten, are no where, I confess, more <hi>Spightfully,</hi> more <hi>Venemously,</hi> or indeed (consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>weakness</hi> of the <hi>Cause</hi>) more <hi>Artfully</hi> described than in that Libel, called, <hi>The Character of a Popish Successour.</hi> But not to answer particularly to a <hi>Rapsody</hi> of <hi>Rhetorical Flourishes,</hi> a Tautology of <hi>Gay Words</hi> and <hi>Big Sounds</hi> to little or no <hi>Signification;</hi> which indeed is almost the <hi>whole Jargon</hi> of that Pamphlet, being truly the <hi>Best <hi>Reason</hi>
               </hi> the <hi>Subject</hi> would bear; I shall chiefly Reply only to the <hi>Argumentative</hi> Part of it; or at least, that which was <hi>intended</hi> as such.</p>
            <p>Therefore as this following Discourse will naturally fall under these two Heads, <hi>viz.</hi> If <hi>Popery</hi> be ever <hi>Introduced,</hi> it can have only these Two Doors for its <hi>Admission, <hi>Persecution,</hi>
               </hi> or <hi>Perswasion,</hi> I shall accordingly Examine,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> What Progress towards a National <hi>Conversion,</hi> and the <hi>Establishment</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> the CRU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ELTY and TYRANNY of it under a Popish Successor is able to make, by an Assault on the <hi>Weak <hi>Side</hi>
               </hi> of Mankind their <hi>Cowardice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Secondly,</hi> What Advance towards the aforesaid <hi>Conversion,</hi> &amp;c. the SUBTILTY and ELOQUENCE of Popish <hi>Emissaries,</hi> and Jesuitical <hi>Seducers,</hi> under the <hi>Ʋmbrage</hi> and <hi>Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement</hi> of a <hi>Popish Successor</hi> are likely to work, by an Attaque on the <hi>Blind <hi>Side</hi>
               </hi> of Mankind their <hi>Ignorance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To begin then with the <hi>First</hi> of the two, as the more <hi>Horrible Horn</hi> of the <hi>Beast; <hi>Persecution.</hi>
               </hi>The Character is not a <hi>little</hi> prolix on that old Popular <hi>Arch-Devil <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi>
               </hi> whilst PO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PERY and SLAVERY, those always <hi>Twin</hi> Monsters, those <hi>Never Seperable</hi> Feinds are so Painted to the Life, with all their <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Brimstone</hi> round them, that it has little else from the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:42213:3"/> Beginning to the End, but the Ratling of <hi>Chains,</hi> the Crackling of <hi>Flames,</hi> the Blazing of <hi>Smithfield Piles;</hi> and in fine, the universal <hi>Groans of Destruction</hi> and <hi>Desolation</hi> through the whole Land.</p>
            <p>And for an <hi>unanswerable</hi> Demonstration of all those most <hi>certain</hi> Calamities from a <hi>Popish Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessor.</hi> The Character tells you, that in the first place, the <hi>Romish</hi> Principles are such, <hi>That they value neither their Word, Promise, Vows, Oaths, nor Sacraments, but all their strongest Engagements are lighter than the very Breath that utters them.</hi> Next, <hi>That they so little Consult either their Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Glory, that there is not the most</hi> Abject <hi>Thing, that even C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>own'd Heads themselves shall not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake, when</hi> Rome, <hi>or</hi> Romes Interest <hi>shall command.</hi> And <hi>Lastly,</hi> That the puting all this Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity into Execution, <hi>is so highly Meritorious in the Romish Church, that the Pope will undoubtedly assign him no Common Diadem in Paradice for this Ʋndertaking.</hi> But upon his Remissness or Tenderness in this Point, <hi>bethunder</hi> him with so many <hi>Curses</hi> and <hi>Anathema's,</hi> as, <hi>an Ʋndutiful, Ʋnactive Son of Holy Mother Church, a Scandal to her Glory, a Traytor to her Interest, a Deserter of her Cause; One while accusing the Lukewarmness of his Religion; another while, the Pusillanimity of his Nature,</hi> &amp;c. till in short, <hi>To spare a Faggot in</hi> Smithfield, <hi>he does little less than walk upon Burning Irons himself.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how is it likely, that <hi>Romes continual Bulls</hi> (as the <hi>Character</hi> fancies) <hi>shall Bellow so loud against a Popish Successor for sparing a Faggot in</hi> Smithfield, when under the <hi>Infamy</hi> and <hi>Execration</hi> of so <hi>Tyrannick a <hi>Murderer</hi>
               </hi> (for what in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days was the Sentence of <hi>Justice,</hi> and the <hi>Legal</hi> Execution of the <hi>Law,</hi> must now be the highest <hi>Subversion</hi> of <hi>Justice,</hi> and <hi>Abrogation</hi> of <hi>Law</hi>) he must expose himself to the whole World as a greater <hi>Monster</hi> than <hi>NERO;</hi> so much a greater than <hi>He,</hi> as <hi>Nero's</hi> Barbarities were committed under the <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Darkness</hi> of <hi>Infidelity</hi> and <hi>Paganism,</hi> and this Mans <hi>Murders</hi> and <hi>Butcheries</hi> under the Light of the <hi>Gospel:</hi> Nay, the terrible <hi>Burning, Broyling,</hi> and <hi>Roasting</hi> denounced in the <hi>Character,</hi> with the <hi>Heating of Popish fiery Furnaces like</hi> Nebuchadnezars <hi>seven times Hotter than ordinary,</hi> with all the rest of the <hi>Romantick</hi> Popish Throat-cutting, will be ten times worse from a <hi>Popish Successor</hi> than the whole <hi>Ten Primitive</hi> Christian <hi>Persecutions.</hi> For a <hi>Nero, Caligula, Domitian,</hi> and the rest of them, as they had the Law in their own <hi>Breath,</hi> and a <hi>Sic volo, sic jubeo,</hi> was as much <hi>Authentick</hi> in old Heathen <hi>Rome,</hi> as an <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> in little <hi>England;</hi> and consequently, how <hi>Barbarous</hi> soever the Christian <hi>Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> was, yet it had the Face of <hi>Law,</hi> as being the Edict of the <hi>Absolute Prince,</hi> and thereby the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of the very <hi>Government.</hi> But such a Scheme of <hi>Cruelty</hi> here, as being beyond the <hi>Reach</hi> of the <hi>Perogative,</hi> and notoriously contrary to the <hi>Establish'd Constitution</hi> of the Kingdom, would, <hi>Ipso facto,</hi> be <hi>Ten Times</hi> more dreadfully <hi>Flagitious,</hi> as 'tis the highest <hi>Violation</hi> of <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Dissolution</hi> of <hi>Government.</hi> And whatever Opinion the noysie Fools of Mankind may have Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibed of <hi>Jesuitisme, Papisme,</hi> and all the <hi>Chimerical Terrours</hi> from <hi>Rome,</hi> how can that very <hi>Rome</hi> (if it pretends but to <hi>Christianity</hi>) that has Canoniz'd so many of those Suffering Primitive <hi>Martyrs,</hi> at the same time likewise make <hi>Saints</hi> of really <hi>Worse <hi>Monsters</hi>
               </hi> amongst <hi>Themselves</hi> than the very <hi>Heathen Butchers</hi> of those very <hi>Martyrs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true <hi>Inquisition-Houses, Lollards-Towers,</hi> and the Cruelty of <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Faggot</hi> we know have been frequent: but all this while they were never Erected by <hi>Standing ARMIES, Arbitrary CƲT-THROATS,</hi> nor <hi>Military EXECƲTION,</hi> but Establish'd by the <hi>Legislative</hi> Power of the Respective Governments that used them, and consequently Introduced with the Solemn In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution of <hi>Law,</hi> as a necessary Support of the Community: Neither has it been a Practice <hi>singular only</hi> to the <hi>Papists,</hi> to secure the Establish'd Religion, and thereby the Peace of the Civil Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by Capital Punishments, when the <hi>Protestant</hi> Government has done the like.</p>
            <p>For Example, does not the <hi>Character</hi> instance two several Acts of Parliament; one of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> in which, <hi>not only the <hi>Popish Priests,</hi> that shall have taken Orders from</hi> Rome, <hi>and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Return to</hi> England, <hi>but likewise all Persons withdrawn by them from the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> Establish'd, to a</hi> Reconciliation <hi>to the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>are Equally Guilty of</hi> High-Treason, <hi>and to suffer as in Cases of</hi> Treason —And a Second <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> the VIII. In which the <hi>Refusal of the Oath of</hi> Henery's <hi>Supremacy in</hi> Renunciation <hi>of the</hi> Pope, <hi>was also made</hi> High-Treason.</p>
            <p>Now if every <hi>Papist</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> without lifting a <hi>Hand,</hi> uttering a <hi>Word,</hi> or imagining the least Disloyal <hi>Thought</hi> against his Lawful Soveraign, his Crown and Dignity, or against the Peace of the Nation where he's a Subject, yet nevertheless out of a point of <hi>Conscience</hi> and meer matter of <hi>Faith,</hi> cannot be induced to believe a <hi>Temporal</hi> Prince capable of being <hi>Head of a Church,</hi> but is Invincibly perswaded (how Erronious soever) that the <hi>Pope</hi> is <hi>Peters</hi> undoubted <hi>Successor,</hi> and Christs unquestioned <hi>Vicar</hi> upon Earth, and cannot, without hazard of his <hi>Soul,</hi> so much as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent to acknowledge otherwise; yet notwithstanding, by the <hi>Protestant</hi> Laws of the Land, this In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Perswasion, without any other Crime, is Interpreted <hi>High-Treason,</hi> and Punish'd as such. Now I say, in this case, what wonderous Difference is there between the Rigour of a <hi>Popish</hi> or a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant</hi> Constitution? This, that makes a Defection from <hi>Their <hi>Church Establish'd,</hi>
               </hi> TREASON; and the other from <hi>Theirs,</hi> HERESY: This that punnishes an <hi>Apostate</hi> with Hanging and Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering at <hi>Tyburn;</hi> and the other with Burning at <hi>Smithfield.</hi> 'Tis true, the Branch of Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> Statute that concerns the Popish <hi>Laymans High-Treason</hi> was never yet put in Execution; and I hope, for the Glory of the Reformation Establish'd by that Illustrious Princess, as so extreamly <hi>Sanguinary,</hi> was never intended to be, being severe enough to give our Popish Enemies a Matter of <hi>Recrimination,</hi> though Enacted but in <hi>Terrorem.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42213:3"/>
            <p>But here I beg the Reader to be assured, that I urge not this Comparison in Disparagement of our <hi>Protestant Laws,</hi> but only to satisfie the Mistaken Part of Mankind, that all such <hi>Judicial Severities</hi> under the Government of both Religions have been introduced by the most <hi>Awful</hi> and <hi>Sacred Authority</hi> of the rightful <hi>Law-Makers</hi> of the Nations, and consequently in the English Constituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, not only the King's, but the People's <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Decrees;</hi> and so to convince them of the <hi>unreaso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nableness</hi> of that senseless <hi>Surmise,</hi> that upon the Admission of a <hi>popish</hi> Successour, all the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned Cruel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies, though without any such Induction of Law (and consequently, with all the <hi>Injustice, Rapine,</hi> and Cold-blooded <hi>Murder,</hi> even to that formal Solemnity of <hi>Butchery,</hi> that humane Imagination would tremble at) <hi>must</hi> and <hi>shall</hi> be introduced. For alas! how ridiculously extravigant must those <hi>Fears</hi> be, that can addle Men's Senses into a Dread of that <hi>prodigious</hi> Stroke from <hi>Popery,</hi> that was never given to it since the Creation. What <hi>Magnifying Glasses</hi> therefore must the <hi>popular Fears</hi> see through, to behold such <hi>stupendious <hi>Visions</hi>
               </hi> of Popery, as that <hi>THAT shall be</hi> that <hi>NEVER</hi> was, whil'st a Popish Crown'd Head in <hi>England</hi> must be the first, nay, <hi>only</hi> Royal <hi>Savage</hi> of a Papist that ever Reign'd.</p>
            <p>However for once let us suppose the <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>Pope</hi> as familiar together as ever they were painted at a Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Night, and that this <hi>Gospel-propagation</hi> were really the <hi>Doctrine of</hi> his pretended <hi>Infallibility,</hi> and this <hi>Bloody Mandate</hi> to a popish Successour the special <hi>Edict</hi> of the whole <hi>CONSISTORY,</hi> what would the Execution of that <hi>Mandate</hi> make towards the <hi>Growth</hi> or <hi>Advancement</hi> of <hi>Popery?</hi> God knows, so far from <hi>promoting</hi> the Romish Religion, that possibly there wants but that one Attempt to <hi>shame</hi> it almost out of the World.</p>
            <p>For in the first place, 'tis so far from a way or means to <hi>Convert</hi> even one Soul in <hi>England,</hi> that 'tis the only Course to increase their <hi>Abhorrence</hi> and <hi>Execration</hi> of that Religion, and bring the very <hi>THOUGHT</hi> of Popery even below <hi>Damnation.</hi> 'Twould no more make <hi>Converts</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> than the old Heathen <hi>Caldrons</hi> and <hi>Gridirons</hi> to <hi>Paganisme:</hi> For as the greatest <hi>prejudice</hi> of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishmen against Popery lyes in their <hi>Horrour</hi> of the <hi>Cruelties</hi> of it: so consequently nothing can contribute to the <hi>Advancement</hi> of it but the <hi>Clemency</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> of its Professours to reconcile us even into meer <hi>Charity</hi> with them: whil'st the Exercising of the forementioned <hi>unexampled</hi> Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s would make us fall from our present <hi>Ill Opinion</hi> of Popery as a <hi>Corrupted <hi>Church,</hi>
               </hi> to believe it <hi>no Church</hi> at all, but rather an <hi>Association</hi> of <hi>Monsters,</hi> and a Den of <hi>Cannibals</hi> and <hi>Tygers:</hi> and the greatest Operation such <hi>unprecedented</hi> Cruelty could meet, were at best but to fright the <hi>fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> People into a <hi>superficial, counterfit</hi> Complyance, and make them <hi>Temporize</hi> a little, only to <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound</hi> for their <hi>Lives;</hi> yet that <hi>Temporizing</hi> under so <hi>Villanous</hi> a Persecution, would be so far from a <hi>True Conversion,</hi> or any thing like it, that they'd only play the <hi>Highest</hi> of <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> come perhaps to <hi>Mass</hi> to mutter <hi>Curses</hi> instead of <hi>Ave-Mary's;</hi> or be hunted into the Popish <hi>Fold,</hi> only to pray for a favourable <hi>Opportunity</hi> of having a pull at the <hi>Throats</hi> of the <hi>Wolves</hi> that <hi>drive</hi> them thither.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Secondly,</hi> Besides the <hi>Impotent Effects,</hi> 'tis certain to find towards the <hi>Heretick Conversion:</hi> the Pope's Command, nay indeed, <hi>Connivance</hi> at any such Arbitrary, Tyrannick <hi>Stake-burning,</hi> or <hi>Throat-cutting</hi> from a Popish Successour, instead of <hi>advancing</hi> of Popery by so <hi>excentrick</hi> a Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, will be enough to <hi>stagger</hi> half the popish Hearts in <hi>Christendom;</hi> for as <hi>Implicit</hi> as the <hi>Faith</hi> of the <hi>Romish Zealots</hi> is, and as intirely devoted as they are to their <hi>Peter's Chair,</hi> and <hi>Mother-Church,</hi> undoubtedly there are <hi>Thousands</hi> of them, that notwithstanding they can disgest a <hi>Wafer</hi> for a GOD, can never be wrought to believe the <hi>Transubstantiation</hi> of such visible <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery</hi> into <hi>Righteousness</hi> and <hi>Christianity,</hi> how Zealous soever they may be for the <hi>Conversion</hi> of so Heretical a Nation as <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that this would be the Infallible Consequence of all such Barbarous Popish Measures: they that will but look back to the Annals of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> will find Historians telling us, That nothing so much advanced the <hi>Reformation</hi> as the Mistaken Conduct of Queen <hi>Mary</hi> and her bloody <hi>Counsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> in that point. And Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> expresly assures us, <hi>That the whole Body of the Nation</hi> grew <hi>to dislike the Cruelty of Rome</hi> [Abridg. Book the 3d. Pag. 275.] <hi>to that degree, that the popish Bishops for their Apology threw it off from</hi> Themselves, <hi>and openly laid it on the King's and Queen's Commands; insomuch that King</hi> Phillip, <hi>for his Excuse, made his</hi> Confessour <hi>preach a Sermon at Court against the taking of people's Lives for their Opinions in Religion, and inveighed against the</hi> Bishops <hi>for doing it. By which means a stop was put to it for some time. But nevertheless, as the same Severi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty soon after return'd again,</hi> he tells us all along, <hi>That the Nations dislike of it was <hi>Vniversal,</hi> and the repeated <hi>Acclamations,</hi> and</hi> Universal <hi>Transports <hi>of</hi> Joy <hi>at the proclaiming of</hi>
               </hi> Queen Elizabeth <hi>proceeded from the people's hopes of better Days under</hi> Her <hi>Scepter than her</hi> Sister's. <hi>By which it appeared how</hi> weary <hi>the Nation was of the <hi>Cruel</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>weak Administration of Affairs under the former</hi> Reign. <hi>And the <hi>Joy</hi> in this Change</hi> (he says) <hi>was so <hi>Great</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Vniversal, <hi>that but a</hi> Sad Look <hi>was thought</hi> Criminal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that to ballance Cases, if the Severity of <hi>Burning</hi> of two hundred and sixty <hi>Protestants</hi> in Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> Five Years Reign under the <hi>Legal</hi> Sentence of the <hi>then <hi>Law of the Land,</hi>
               </hi> and in that Respect by the Hand of <hi>Justice,</hi> begat such a <hi>Hatred</hi> of Popery, and made so many <hi>Converts</hi> to the <hi>Reformation,</hi> that possibly 'twas one of the <hi>Greatest Lifts</hi> to the <hi>Downfall</hi> of the Romish Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion in <hi>England;</hi> insomuch that 'tis the Opinion of all wise Men, that a <hi>Bonner</hi> and a <hi>Gardiner</hi> did more towards the Propagation of the <hi>protestant</hi> Religion than a <hi>Cranmer</hi> and a <hi>Ridley.</hi> How much <hi>infinitely</hi> more therefore must the Exercise of such <hi>popish Cruelties</hi> from the Hand of the most <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Tyranny under the visible <hi>Monstrous</hi> Face of the most notorious <hi>Illegality,</hi> and the blackest <hi>Injustice,</hi> increase our <hi>Irreconcileable Detestation</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and by making more <hi>Apostates than
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42213:4"/> Proselytes</hi> to their <hi>Cause,</hi> heap up but fuel for the <hi>Popish,</hi> not <hi>Protestant</hi> Confusion: and so at best, this <hi>Arbitrary Bloody Tyranny</hi> can have no higher prospect than of committing Murders for meer <hi>Murders</hi> sake.</p>
            <p>But to silence all Dangers of such <hi>stupendious</hi> papal <hi>Excursions.</hi> This barbarous Model of Gospel Propag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tion is at this present <hi>Age</hi> of the World wholly unpractised in all the Popish Nations in <hi>Europe,</hi> and excepting the <hi>Spanish Inquisition</hi> (and that too, seldom rigorous against any but the <hi>Open Seducers</hi> of the People from their Religion, to prevent the <hi>Disturbance</hi> of the settled Peace of the Kingdom under so <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eneral</hi> and <hi>unanimous</hi> a Conformity of the Roman Religion in <hi>Spain</hi>) There is now <hi>no</hi> Popish Government whatever, that proceeds against <hi>Heresy</hi> with <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Fag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got,</hi> or any other <hi>Sanguinary</hi> Punishment; whil'st on the contrary, the <hi>Reformers</hi> are more or less <hi>Indulged</hi> or <hi>Tolerated</hi> through almost all the Popish Kingdoms in the World; though 'tis true, that <hi>Indulgence</hi> or <hi>Toleration</hi> in the publick Exercise of their Religion is sometimes more <hi>enlarged,</hi> and other times more <hi>curtil d,</hi> according to the more or less generous <hi>Temper</hi> of the Respective Kings that grant them; which though magnifyed at a prodigious rate by the present Dreaders of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, such as the <hi>Tender-hearted Condolers</hi> of the true Protestant <hi>Dissenter</hi> Count <hi>Tekely,</hi> &amp;c. is no more tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t is dayly done even by Protestant Princes in the same Nature, whil'st the <hi>Immunities</hi> and <hi>Priv ledges</hi> of all <hi>Dissenting Perswasions</hi> against the Establish't Religion of the Land, as being but the <hi>Donation</hi> of the Governments <hi>Discretion</hi> and <hi>Curtesy,</hi> are <hi>increased</hi> or <hi>diminished,</hi> as the Favour of the Sov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raign shall extend, or the <hi>Policy</hi> of the Nation shall require.</p>
            <p>However, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all <hi>Sanguinary Persecutions</hi> of <hi>Heresy</hi> are now so universally l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ft off, and that too, considering the Popes Influence over the Royal Sons of his own Church, <hi>undoubte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly</hi> with his own <hi>Privity</hi> and <hi>Consent:</hi> 'tis certain, that both He and his Crown'd Heads are by Experience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the <hi>Fataility</hi> of such <hi>Rigorous</hi> Ecclesiastick <hi>Extremities,</hi> as wholly <hi>ineffectual</hi> to the Great Work <hi>Designed,</hi> the Intended Propagation of Religion. And consequently, the Pope must be strangely out of his <hi>Right Senses,</hi> to put a Popish Successour, and that in <hi>England,</hi> of all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys of the Universe, upon a <hi>Projection</hi> so <hi>long</hi> out of F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>shion in all the World beside; nay, and to a more <hi>Monstrous</hi> height of <hi>Extravagance</hi> (as being positively against any Law or Right what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever) than wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ever practised in the World before.</p>
            <p>Neverthel ss, laying <hi>Policy, Prudence,</hi> nay, <hi>Common Reason</hi> aside; for once, we'll dispense with all manner of <hi>Incoherencies</hi> and <hi>Absurdities</hi> whatever, and put the Supposition, That the Pope should <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at strange <hi>Tarantuia,</hi> as to begin this <hi>Frantick <hi>Dance,</hi>
               </hi> and a Popish Successour, that <hi>Madman,</hi> to follow him. The next Question that arises will be, <hi>How</hi> he shall set this Arbitrary Machine <hi>ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing?</hi> And which way he shall find <hi>Hands, Tools,</hi> and <hi>Materials</hi> to build this Terrible COLOSSUS, called <hi>Arbitrary Power.</hi> 'Tis true inde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, the <hi>Character</hi> tells us the way of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, as follows: <hi>Let us but rightly consider how far the Foundations of</hi> Popery <hi>(Viz. <hi>Arbitrary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ower</hi>) may be layed in England. First then, if a</hi> Papist <hi>Reign, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e very well understand that the</hi> Ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, Sheriffs▪ Justices of the Peace, <hi>and all the</hi> Judiciary Officers <hi>are of the King's Creation. And a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> such, how far may the Influ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce of</hi> Preferment <hi>on Baser Const<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tutions culled out for his purpose, dreva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> even to deprave the very Throne of <hi>Iustice</hi> her self, and make our</hi> Judges <hi>use even our <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Laws</hi> themselves to open the First Gate to <hi>Slavery.</hi> Alas! the Laws in corrupted</hi> Judges <hi>Hands, have been too often used as barbarously as the Guests of</hi> Procrustes, <hi>who had a Bed for all Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers, but then he either cut them shorter, or stretcht them longer to sit them to it.</hi> And after all this, the Character proceeds, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lls you, that <hi>to crown the Work, and make the</hi> Pope <hi>Absolute, <hi>this</hi>
               </hi> Popish <hi>Succ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssour wants a</hi> STANDING-ARMY, <hi>and he shall have it,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This <hi>True Ble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>Protest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt</hi>
               </hi> Schem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of In roduction for <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> by the way of distorting of our very <hi>Protestant Laws</hi> to bring it in, the <hi>History</hi> of the Popish Plot only excepted, is one of the most <hi>Comical Whim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> that was ever invented. I confess indeed some intricate Cases in <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> may occur, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re the most Impartial Judges may be divided in their Opinions, even in <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Law,</hi> and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iversity of various, and almost absolete <hi>Records</hi> and <hi>Statutes</hi> in several lesser <hi>Law-Matters</hi> may som times admit of Disputes &amp; diverse Interpretations, and a corrupt <hi>Judge</hi> under such a <hi>Latitude,</hi> may le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n or turn as Inclination shall guide. But that part of our <hi>Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sh</hi> Law that concerns our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> the long and labour'd Work of so many <hi>Successive</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; nay, and after the very <hi>Lopping</hi> of the <hi>Prerogative</hi> to secure the Subject by the Abolition of <hi>Oaths ex Offici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Star-Chamber Courts, Court of Wards,</hi> and by the Benefit of <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> Acts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the continued Care and Industry of our <hi>Law-makers</hi> for a hundred years together, stands so <hi>strongly</hi> fortifyed against all <hi>Romish</hi> or <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Invasions, that there's not the least <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> in the Law left open for the Admission of the <hi>One</hi> or the <hi>Other.</hi> However, this part of the Char<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cter was very well timed for the Season 'twas writ in. For when the very Protestant <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> and <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>shops</hi> of the Land, the whole <hi>Court,</hi> nay and the KING himself <hi>not excepted,</hi> were all <hi>helter skelter,</hi> just upon being turn'd into downright Papists in <hi>Masquerade,</hi> 'twas not at all unsea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable to improve upon the <hi>Fiction,</hi> and bring in the <hi>Protestant Laws</hi> too in the Crowd for <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Masqueraders</hi> among <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir Fellows.</p>
            <p>However, notwithstanding this Pretended <hi>Dangerous Inlet</hi> to <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> the <hi>Character,</hi> by a certain <hi>Fault</hi> which I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave read in a <hi>Treat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se,</hi> called <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>Baxter,</hi> (a Figure of Speech <hi>much used</hi> by that Eloqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt Divine, and truly <hi>much borrow'd</hi> in the <hi>Character,</hi> being little else throughout) makes bold in another place point Blank to <hi>contradict</hi> this Passage, and positively af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, <hi>That to set up <hi>Popery</hi> or <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> by Law, under the Laws we have already against them, is wholly impossible, and that our Laws will be but the Hedge to keep in the <hi>Cuckow.</hi> For</hi> Papists
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42213:4"/>
               <hi>and Slaves we must and shall be made, as the inseperable Concomitants of a Popish Successour.</hi> And to prove all this Breaking of all Laws whatever, it says <hi>in haec verba;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How can the Force of Laws, made by a</hi> Protestant <hi>Predecessour, and a</hi> Protestant <hi>Parliament, in any sort bind a</hi> Popish <hi>Successour? When the very first Advance of the</hi> Pope's <hi>Supremacy</hi> [a very nimble leap] <hi>introduces that higher <hi>Power,</hi> those Canonical <hi>Ecclesiastick Laws,</hi> which no Secular, or any other Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Court <hi>can</hi> or <hi>may</hi> Controul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Laws that shall declare, not only the</hi> Statutes <hi>and</hi> Acts of Parliament <hi>made against the Dignity of Mother-Church,</hi> voyd <hi>and</hi> Null, <hi>but the very</hi> Law-makers <hi>themselves, as</hi> Hereticks, <hi>wholly uncapable of ever having</hi> any Right <hi>of making any such <hi>Laws.</hi> No doubt then, but that Fire that burns those</hi> Heretick Law-makers, <hi>shall give their Laws the same</hi> Martyrdom.</p>
            <p>Here indeed the Affairs are alter'd, and truly, the Matter much mended. This I confess, says the <hi>Character,</hi> and this, at least three parts of the <hi>Fools</hi> of <hi>English</hi> Mankind believe for <hi>Oracles.</hi> And though all our <hi>Records, Histories, Chronicles,</hi> and the whole <hi>Series</hi> of all Ages since the Conquest to this day, do notoriously prove the <hi>Contrary;</hi> yet this <hi>Popular maxime,</hi> That the <hi>Romanists</hi> by their Ecclesiastick Laws, pretend to <hi>anull</hi> and <hi>make void</hi> all <hi>Secular</hi> Laws against their <hi>Church,</hi> and to incapacitate the very Prerogative and Authority of that Majesty, und those <hi>Law-makers</hi> that made them, though one of the most <hi>Impudent Falshoods</hi> in nature, is nevertheless one of the most received <hi>Vulgar <hi>Traditions</hi>
               </hi> that ever startled Ideots.</p>
            <p>For Example, to begin with their very <hi>Heretici Comburendi:</hi> The very <hi>Ax</hi> and <hi>Fasces</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> was it not an Act of the <hi>Secular Power?</hi> In the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry high<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st Reign of <hi>Porpery, did,</hi> or <hi>could</hi> the Pope punish an <hi>Heretick Apostate</hi> by Imprisonment, Fire or Faggot, any further than by <hi>Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Permission,</hi> and excepting that the Clergy were made Judges of <hi>Heresy,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d that too, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession of the <hi>Secular Authority.</hi> Was not the Execution of that Law kept in <hi>Temporal Hands?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, though 'tis true, the <hi>papal</hi> Power made many <hi>Ʋsurp'd</hi> Encroachments <hi>here,</hi> through the <hi>Bigotry</hi> of the Governm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt; yet, upon <hi>too hard,</hi> Pressures from <hi>Rome,</hi> did not several of our Kings many <hi>hundred years</hi> before the <hi>Reformation,</hi> resume their own <hi>Original</hi> Right; and expresly in the St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tute against PROVISOES <hi>under Penalty of Forfeiture of Goods, and Imprisoment for Life,</hi> forbid the admitting of the Popes <hi>Legantine Power</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> or making <hi>Appeals</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> or tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Inductions</hi> to Episcopal Sees from the Pope.</p>
            <p>And for Queen <hi>Mary</hi> her self, was there one <hi>Syllable</hi> of the Laws Enacted by the Father <hi>Henry,</hi> or her Brother <hi>Edward</hi> in favour of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> that she ever pretended to <hi>Over-rule</hi> by any Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastick <hi>Law</hi> or Pretence whatever? Nay, and did not the Pope's <hi>Supremacy</hi> it <hi>felf,</hi> and that not till many a hard tug, and two years after she came to the Crown, come in by <hi>Act of <hi>Parliament,</hi>
               </hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der several <hi>Limitations</hi> of his Power, with the Confirmation of the antient Statute against <hi>Provisoes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> and several other <hi>Boundaries;</hi> as much as to say, <hi>Move thus far, and <hi>no Further.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas! what's all this to the Author of a Popish <hi>Character? Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Power in spight of Fate, <hi>shall</hi> and <hi>must</hi> be set up. And therefore what Laws <hi>sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll,</hi> or <hi>shall not</hi> get uppermost, is ene as Mr. <hi>Scribler</hi> pleases. For truly <hi>Malice</hi> put pen to paper, and <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Reason</hi> were never <hi>minded:</hi> and indeed, there was no <hi>need</hi> of <hi>either</hi> of them; for as that Pamphlet had the honour in the Title-Page, of being <hi>humbly offered to the Consideration of the <hi>then</hi> HOƲSES</hi> of Parliament, both <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Reason</hi> were <hi>Immaterial</hi> to <hi>itb</hi> Recommendation▪ For where an <hi>Otes</hi> his <hi>Narrative</hi> past for <hi>Gospel,</hi> the Devil's in't, if a <hi>Popish Character</hi> could <hi>miscarry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, to confute that sensless Fear, that a Popish Successour will subvert the whole Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Government,</hi> and erect his own Arbitrary <hi>Edict,</hi> for the Supreme <hi>Standard</hi> of <hi>JƲSTICE,</hi> and that he shall find those Popish <hi>Judges, Sheriffs,</hi> or any other <hi>Officers</hi> or <hi>Ministers,</hi> that under the Protection of a <hi>Standing Army,</hi> shall make our <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> wholly dependant upon the <hi>Caprichio</hi> and <hi>Pleasure</hi> of the Prince, and persuant thereto, shall furnish him with <hi>Jayls, Gibbets,</hi> and <hi>Smithfield</hi> Piles, or any other Arbitrary, though <hi>less</hi> Sanguinary Persecution to convert us to Popery.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> let us examine the <hi>Courage</hi> of all these Arbitrary <hi>Judges, Officers,</hi> and <hi>State-Ministers</hi> that embarque in this Arbitrary Undertaking. They must be all those <hi>hardy</hi> popish Tools, whether cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by <hi>Zeal</hi> or <hi>Interest,</hi> that they must not value all their own <hi>Lives▪</hi> for notwithstanding what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Protection or Impunity they may receive during the Life of their Royal Popish Driver; no sooner shall the next Protestant <hi>Heir</hi> succeed him, but <hi>every Mothers S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> of them shall be answera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with their <hi>Necks</hi> for the <hi>least drop</hi> of Protestant <hi>BLOOD</hi> they have shed, or Protestant <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> they have invaded. The Protestant Laws of the Land will not be so tamely overthrown, without a <hi>certain</hi> Vengeance attending it; insomuch that those bold <hi>Babel Builders,</hi> these <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Raisers</hi> must either be so generous to their <hi>King</hi> as the <hi>Indian Wives</hi> to their <hi>Husbands,</hi> and make one glorious <hi>Funeral</hi> Pile upon his <hi>Grave;</hi> or else, resolve to live to offer up their <hi>Throats</hi> to the very <hi>Sword</hi> of <hi>Iustice</hi> in the Hand of a <hi>Lawful Authority,</hi> which themselves before have so <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully <hi>abused</hi>
               </hi> in their own.</p>
            <p>And that the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Subject</hi> is so tender in the Eye of the English Government, the very <hi>misusing</hi> and <hi>torturing</hi> of <hi>Hereticks</hi> in Prison, though under that <hi>Attainder,</hi> Ivable to the most ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious of <hi>Deaths;</hi> and though done in a Popish predecessours Reign, was sufficient to have taken the great Statesman <hi>Bonner's <hi>Head</hi>
               </hi> off, but only that Queen <hi>Elizabeth's <hi>Mercy</hi>
               </hi> interposed, as <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to stain the beginning of her Reign with Blood.</hi> [Reform. Abridg. <hi>B.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 357.] And if his Illegal Compliance with his Prince was so <hi>Capital</hi> an Offence, what must the more violent Irruptions of <hi>Arbitrary Rapines</hi> against the <hi>untainted</hi> Liberty of the Protestant <hi>Subjects</hi> now pull down upon the bold <hi>Invaders</hi> Heads.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:42213:5"/>
            <p>'Tis no difficult matter to possess the <hi>overcredulous</hi> World, the <hi>easy <hi>swallowing</hi>
               </hi> Multitude, with what wondrous Atchievements the <hi>Zealots</hi> of Popery shall undertake, and what indefatigable <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</hi> and <hi>Hazards</hi> they will go through for the Re-building of their <hi>Faln <hi>Temples,</hi>
               </hi> when animat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and influenced by a Popish Soveraign.</p>
            <p>I acknowledge ('tis true) there is no Courage more <hi>daring</hi> than that which <hi>Zeal</hi> inspires; and no <hi>Zeal</hi> possibly more <hi>violent</hi> than that of the Papists, and undoubtedly for <hi>Rome's</hi> Restoration, there would be many venturous and bold Champions amongst them in so <hi>Meritorious</hi> a Cause.</p>
            <p>But alas! every <hi>Heroe</hi> is not a <hi>Sampson.</hi> There are, no doubt, those of them that would spare neither <hi>pains</hi> nor <hi>study</hi> to propagate their own Religion, though never so indirectly; those possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly that would have it in their Power (if they could come handsomely by it) to use their Heretick <hi>Adversaries</hi> with as little <hi>Mercy</hi> as HE did his <hi>Philistian Enemies;</hi> but alas, not with his <hi>Hardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> too, as like <hi>Him,</hi> to pull down that Roof upon their Heads to their own inevitable Destructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on only to have the pleasure of crushing some of <hi>ƲS</hi> with them.</p>
            <p>We read, I confess, that <hi>pro Aris &amp; Focis</hi> men will venture far. Yes truly, for their <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Estates <hi>together</hi>
               </hi> they will do so. But in the Popish Case, where the <hi>Founding</hi> of the <hi>One</hi> will be the <hi>Destruction</hi> of the <hi>Other;</hi> where the <hi>Setting up</hi> of their <hi>Religion,</hi> will be the Forfeiting not only their <hi>Estates,</hi> but <hi>Heads</hi> too; 'tis more than a hundred to one, betwixt these two so directly <hi>opposite</hi> Interests, but that the keeping of their <hi>Skin</hi> and <hi>Bones</hi> warm on the <hi>one</hi> side, may make their <hi>Zeal</hi> a little the cooler on the other. For let me tell you, where the Erecting of the <hi>Altar</hi> will at long run make the <hi>Builders</hi> the <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> in all humane probability that Popish <hi>Temple</hi> will go but slowly up, whose Stones are to be dug out of so fatal a <hi>Quarry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis very remarkable in Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> Reign, when by the Majority of her Parliament, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion then but in its <hi>Minority</hi> was abolish't, and the Romish Government and Papal <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy</hi> Re-establish't; and indeed the Grandure of <hi>Rome</hi> even to <hi>Haeretici comburendi</hi> maintain'd. Yet that <hi>Parliament</hi> that had it absolutely in their power to gratifie the Pope's <hi>utmost</hi> Wishes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused the <hi>returning</hi> his <hi>Church-Lands again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, the Parliament were so averse to the thought of such a Restitution, that they had never been wrought up to the restoring of the very <hi>Supremacy</hi> it self, and of making of all those favourable Acts towards the re-installing of <hi>Popery</hi> again, but by much pains used (as <hi>Burnet</hi> in his <hi>Abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> pag. 268 says) by the policy of Bishop <hi>Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>din<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> to ensure the Kingdom from the Fear of coming under such Tyranny from <hi>Rome</hi> as their <hi>Ancestors</hi> had groaned under, and likewise from the Loss of the <hi>Abbey-Lands.</hi> Insomuch that <hi>Gardiner</hi> promised them for Removal of all such Jealousie, that all the old Laws against <hi>Provisions</hi> should continue in Force, and to shew them that <hi>Legates</hi> should exercise no dangerous Authority in <hi>England,</hi> he made <hi>Pool</hi> take out a License under the <hi>Great Seal</hi> for his <hi>Legantine</hi> Power; and for the other, <hi>Viz.</hi> the <hi>Abbey-Lands,</hi> he promised both an <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> and <hi>Convocation</hi> confirming them, and undertook that the Pope himself should ratifie the Alienation of the <hi>Church-Lands;</hi> which, History tells us, was accordingly done.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, as this Papal <hi>Dispensation</hi> came very unwillingly from <hi>Rome,</hi> being only a Forced <hi>Compliance</hi> and <hi>Temporizing</hi> with the English <hi>Obstinacy</hi> in that point. The Queen her self restored all the <hi>Church-Lands</hi> in her Possession, and proceeded so far as to the Re-building of several Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Houses, declaring, to her <hi>Treasurer,</hi> and some of her other <hi>Officers,</hi> that she thought her self bound in Conscience to restore all the <hi>Church-Lands,</hi> as being unlawfully acquired, and not to be held with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Sin: (as <hi>Baker</hi> in his Chronicle tells us) Nay, the <hi>Pope</hi> himself set out a <hi>Bull,</hi> excommunicat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that kept any Lands belonging to <hi>Abbeys</hi> or <hi>Churches;</hi> which▪ gave such an Alarm to the Nation, that <hi>Gardiner</hi> was forced to pacifie them, by telling them, that <hi>Bull</hi> was intended only to the <hi>people</hi> of <hi>Germany,</hi> and not <hi>England.</hi> However, the <hi>Pope</hi> continued his high Resentments against the Undutifulness of <hi>England,</hi> that he could not forbear telling the Queen's <hi>Ambassadours. (Abridg. pag.</hi> 221.) That it was beyond his <hi>power</hi> to confirm <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> and all were obliged, under the pain of Damnation to restore to the last Farthing every thing that belong'd to the <hi>Church;</hi> he said like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, that he would send over a Collectour to gather the <hi>Peter-pence;</hi> for they could not expect that St. <hi>Peter</hi> would open Heaven to them, so long as they denied him his Rights upon Earth.</p>
            <p>Yet all this made so little Impression on the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> that whatever Conscience might dictate, their Priests insinuate, their <hi>Popish <hi>Successour</hi> Solicite,</hi> or their <hi>Pope</hi> himself end<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>avour, so <hi>powerful</hi> was <hi>Interest</hi> above <hi>Conscience,</hi> and all other Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ives whatever, that several of the <hi>Commons</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> lay'd their hands on their Swords, and declared that they would not part with their Estates, but defend them. And every Motion that way, was always carryed in the <hi>Negative. (Abridg. of the Reform.</hi> B. 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 309)</p>
            <p>Now, pray, for once, let us compare Cases. If the <hi>Papists</hi> in her Reign, with the highest <hi>Papal Dominion</hi> and <hi>Sov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raignty</hi> in their own Hands, under an Establish't <hi>Roman Church,</hi> against both their Priests and their Prince; nay, a Prince too, with her <hi>Hereticks</hi> under her Feet, and her Religion in the very <hi>Saddle,</hi> could refuse both their <hi>Pope,</hi> and their <hi>popish Successour</hi> so <hi>Iust</hi> and so <hi>Sacred</hi> a Right, and so important to his Church's <hi>Interest,</hi> and that too, when with all Safety round them, they might have confirm'd their Oblation even by the strongest Bonds of <hi>Law;</hi> so on the other side, how shall it be suppos'd that the more <hi>prodigal <hi>Papists</hi>
               </hi> in our <hi>Age,</hi> in the quite contrary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream, shall gratifie the unjust Demands of a more <hi>Impotent</hi> popish <hi>Successour,</hi> under the lowest <hi>Ebb</hi> of Popery against all <hi>Law</hi> or <hi>Pretence</hi> of <hi>Law</hi> whatever, by launching out into the most notorious
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42213:5"/> Violation of all the highest sanctions of <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Justice,</hi> and the most <hi>openfaced <hi>Tyranny</hi>
               </hi> and most impudent <hi>Barbarity</hi> in the world, and all (forsooth) for the <hi>Establishing</hi> of <hi>Popery;</hi> and all, God wot, too <hi>little</hi> for the Work; and this too, to the running themselves into unavoidable <hi>Iayls</hi> and <hi>Halters;</hi> and not only to the ruining of their <hi>Estates,</hi> but to the cutting off of the <hi>Lives</hi> of <hi>Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves,</hi> and even the very <hi>RACE</hi> of <hi>Papists</hi> under the next immediate <hi>Crown'd-Head</hi> that succeeds.</p>
            <p>Besides, as boldly as the <hi>Roman Zealots</hi> stand up for the <hi>Interest</hi> and <hi>Dignity</hi> of <hi>Mother-Church,</hi> and the <hi>Grandure</hi> and <hi>Dominion</hi> of their <hi>Peter's</hi> Successour, not only the <hi>Papists,</hi> but the very <hi>Priests</hi> themselves are not so <hi>overcouragious</hi> in this Cause as the <hi>World</hi> suspects them. For Instance, in <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the <hi>Eighth's</hi> Reign, the whole Clergy of <hi>England,</hi> by a <hi>State-surprize</hi> upon them, were found guilty of a <hi>Premunire,</hi> by submitting to Cardinal <hi>Woolsy's <hi>Legantine-power,</hi>
               </hi> as derived only from the Pope's <hi>Authority,</hi> and thereby expresly against the <hi>Statute</hi> of <hi>PROVISOES,</hi> an old dormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Law,</hi> made several King's Reigns before, though rarely, or never put in Force, by reason of the <hi>Remissness</hi> of the Government, and the <hi>Supiness</hi> of the Nation and Kings <hi>Submission</hi> to <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore unwarily transgrest by the Clergy <hi>now.</hi> By vertue however of which they had forfeited <hi>their Goods and Chattels to the King, and their persons to be imprisoned.</hi> Upon the King's <hi>Menace</hi> of executing which Law (<hi>Reformat. Book the</hi> 2d. pag. 112.) the Convocation of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> in tenderness to their <hi>Skins</hi> and <hi>Estates,</hi> brought a Petition to his Majesty, acknowledging him in the Title, <hi>Protectour, and Supream Head of the Church and Clergy of England.</hi> Which was agreed to by nine Bishops, 82 Abbots, and the majority of the Convocation in the Province of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to accept of 100000 <hi>l.</hi> in leiu of the Punishments incurred. And the Province of <hi>York</hi> soon afterwards consented to the fame <hi>Submission,</hi> with the Offer of 18840 <hi>l.</hi> for obtaining the same pardon.</p>
            <p>Insomuch that we find the very popish <hi>Clergy</hi> themselves so servilely compounding for their <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and their <hi>Carcases</hi> (not so much in the Voluntary Tribute of their Purses) as with the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciation</hi> of the Pope's <hi>Ecclesiastical Supremacy,</hi> the very <hi>brightest <hi>Iewel</hi>
               </hi> in the <hi>Tripple <hi>Diadem,</hi>
               </hi> and consequently by this sordid Compliance, even the <hi>Priesthood</hi> it self by their own <hi>Leading Act,</hi> gave the fatal <hi>Original <hi>precedent</hi>
               </hi> to the succeeding <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> to confirm that <hi>Supremacy</hi> in the <hi>Crown,</hi> and so struck the first main <hi>Blow</hi> towards the <hi>shaking</hi> of the <hi>Romish Prerogative</hi> in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and thereupon <hi>Conspired</hi> to the gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>st part of the ensuing <hi>Fatalities</hi> to their <hi>Religion it self.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore, if the <hi>Ecclesiastical</hi> Sons of <hi>Rome</hi> could ward themselves from the <hi>Stroke</hi> of <hi>Law</hi> due to that <hi>less <hi>Capital</hi>
               </hi> Transgression <hi>THEN,</hi> by denying their very <hi>Pope:</hi> Why must the Sons of <hi>Rome</hi> be so prodigiously Fool-hardy <hi>NOW,</hi> as to run themselves into a more <hi>Dangerous</hi> and more <hi>Mortal <hi>Noose</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>Law</hi> for his <hi>Vindication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis very easie preaching to <hi>Fools</hi> and <hi>Madmen</hi> (as the popish <hi>Character</hi> has very <hi>Rhetorically</hi> done) what miraculous Fire and Faggot Feats, or other Arbitrary Extravagancies the wonderful Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists under a popish Successour shall do. But as great a <hi>Deity</hi> as the <hi>Romanists</hi> make of their Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Keys of Heaven, as the Devil (speaking of <hi>Job</hi>) makes answer to <hi>God Almighty, put forth thine hand, and touch him in all that he hath, and he will curse thee to thy Face.</hi> So let his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness put these <hi>Zealots</hi> upon that <hi>Hard Task,</hi> where their <hi>Necks</hi> are sure to stretch in the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> will be so little a part of the Sacrifice they'l make his <hi>Divinityship</hi> in such a Command, that all his <hi>Bell, Book,</hi> and <hi>Candle</hi> will be too little to <hi>conjure</hi> up <hi>half</hi> hands <hi>enough</hi> for so <hi>ungrateful</hi> and so <hi>cursed</hi> an Employment. Whatever pleasure they may take in bringing <hi>Vs</hi> to <hi>Stakes</hi> and <hi>Gibbets,</hi> they are not overfond of <hi>Martyrdom</hi> themselves. And though <hi>Great</hi> is their <hi>DIANA</hi> of <hi>Ephesus,</hi> whil'st <hi>Profit</hi> and <hi>Safety</hi> go along with her, and upon <hi>Reasonable</hi> Terms, much might be done to exalt her; yet ther's that <hi>Vniversal</hi> Charm in that thing call'd <hi>OƲR ALL,</hi> and that strange <hi>superseding</hi> Quality in those <hi>potent <hi>Operators,</hi> Self,</hi> and <hi>Self-preservation,</hi> that it over-rules the highest Excursions even of the most daring <hi>Zeal,</hi> and the very <hi>biggest</hi> Devils of <hi>Outrage</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> are laid by no other <hi>Spell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But perhaps it may be objected, That to incourage the bold Labourers in this <hi>Harvest,</hi> this <hi>popish</hi> King, to prevent the Ruine both of his <hi>Cause</hi> and his <hi>Party,</hi> will take Care, in case of a <hi>protestant</hi> Heir, to divert the <hi>Succession,</hi> and continue the Crown upon some <hi>other <hi>popish Head;</hi>
               </hi> and so by a <hi>longer</hi> Usurpation of this Arbitrary <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and a more <hi>lasting</hi> Persecution of the <hi>Protestants,</hi> provide as much as in him lyes, that the <hi>propagation</hi> of the <hi>Romish Faith</hi> may be compleated in suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding <hi>Ages,</hi> upon so good a Foundation lay'd in his <hi>Own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This foolish <hi>Supposition</hi> is so lewdly <hi>ridiculous,</hi> that ther's scarce a <hi>shadow</hi> for such a <hi>Fear:</hi> For (alas) there will be so little Hopes of a <hi>popish Vsurper's</hi> mounting the Throne, after so notorious a <hi>Tyranny</hi> under a <hi>Lawful popish King</hi> before him, as nothing can scarcely be more impossible. 'Tis possible indeed, the Duty of our <hi>Christianity,</hi> and the Bond of <hi>Passive Obedience,</hi> as having the Lawful Power of no other Weapons but our <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Tears</hi> against the Tyranny of our <hi>Lawful</hi> Prince, may <hi>tye up</hi> our hands, and keep us in the Bounds of Peace and <hi>Resignation</hi> during <hi>his <hi>Reign.</hi>
               </hi> But the setting up of a <hi>popish Vsurper</hi> after him, in wrong to the <hi>Imperial <hi>protestant Right</hi> Heir,</hi> will undoubtedly ingage all the Protestant <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Hearts</hi> against so impudent an <hi>Invader;</hi> (and if Occasion require, his <hi>Protestant</hi> Royal Neighbours in such a Cause) whil'st the taking
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42213:6"/> up Arms in such a Quarrel, which had been <hi>Rebellion</hi> against his Predecessour <hi>before,</hi> would be the work of their highest <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Allegiance <hi>now.</hi>
               </hi> And as the Remembrance of their <hi>past Yoke</hi> to all true English Spi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>its, would certainly <hi>double Edge</hi> their very <hi>Swords;</hi> so, in so just a Cause, 'twould infallibly spur them to so <hi>perfect,</hi> and so <hi>unanimous</hi> a <hi>Revenge,</hi> as to cut off their <hi>popish <hi>Enemies,</hi>
               </hi> even to the <hi>last Man.</hi> Now what <hi>popish <hi>Ʋsurper</hi>
               </hi> shall venture to pass such an <hi>Ordeal</hi> to a <hi>Throne?</hi> Or what hopes a <hi>popish</hi> King can have of such a <hi>Successour,</hi> or of accomplishing his own <hi>popish <hi>Designs</hi>
               </hi> on such a <hi>Basis,</hi> let common Reason judge.</p>
            <p>And therefore the Pope must have a very little <hi>Paternal Care,</hi> of his Royal <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of all his <hi>Catholick</hi> Sons in <hi>England,</hi> as to imbark them in a Cause so <hi>apparently, Derstuctive,</hi> whil'st by misleading them into such sanguinary, illegal Cruelties against the <hi>Protestants,</hi> and all for an <hi>impossible Conversion</hi> of a Nation, he runs his own darling people, <hi>Root</hi> and <hi>Branch</hi> into an ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitable <hi>Fate</hi> under the next <hi>Protestant Successor,</hi> exposed not only to the highest popular <hi>Swords</hi> and <hi>Fury,</hi> but even to <hi>Cords</hi> and <hi>Axes,</hi> and the severest Stroke and Vengeance of <hi>Law</hi> it self. But possibly their Fate shall not wait so <hi>long</hi> as the next King's Coronation, but overtake them in the first <hi>Onset</hi> of their <hi>popish Barbarity.</hi> For let ut but look back to the <hi>Gun-powder</hi> Treason, a Plot where <hi>Faux's Powder-Barrels</hi> were neither like <hi>Otes</hi> his <hi>Teuxbury Mustard-Balls,</hi> nor his <hi>Black Bills, <hi>Invisible.</hi>
               </hi> A <hi>Plot</hi> too, where the <hi>Conspirators</hi> dyed not <hi>Tongue-tyed,</hi> but confessed their <hi>Guilt,</hi> without that <hi>wonder-working Dispensation</hi> of asserting a <hi>Counterfeit Innocence,</hi> to the stretch o their <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> and Renuntiation of their God, on the very Brink of <hi>Eternity.</hi> Let us look back, I say, to the Discovery of that <hi>Plot:</hi> and History informs us, that 'twas as much as the <hi>King, Court</hi> and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> could possibly do to restrain the peopl's Rage from <hi>Butchering</hi> all the Papists in <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Guilty</hi> and <hi>Innocent</hi> together in the Revenge of so barbarous a Machination, though <hi>uneffected;</hi> tho by Providence <hi>detected</hi> and <hi>frustrated.</hi> And if the <hi>Genius</hi> of England was so highly exasperated, and so furiously transported in <hi>Zeal</hi> for their <hi>Prince's</hi> and their <hi>Representativ's</hi> Danger, though <hi>past</hi> and <hi>escaped.</hi> What Security shall the <hi>Pope,</hi> or his <hi>popish Successour</hi> promise themselves, that the people's <hi>Zeal</hi> for their <hi>own</hi> Dangers <hi>Approaching,</hi> will not be as much <hi>transported</hi> too. And that the Eruption of <hi>Smithfield Fires,</hi> with the dragging of their <hi>Fathers,</hi> their <hi>Wives,</hi> their <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> or their <hi>Kindred</hi> (and possibly their <hi>own <hi>Turn</hi>
               </hi> next) to a <hi>popish Stake,</hi> will not <hi>equally,</hi> if not more <hi>violently</hi> inflame them into as <hi>great,</hi> or <hi>greater</hi> Outrages than the <hi>Gun-powder</hi> Plot could do.</p>
            <p>But whether this certain Ruine should persue these Arbitrary <hi>popish</hi> Instruments either <hi>sooner</hi> or <hi>later,</hi> and that it were really possible these, or any other Illegal popish Measures might give us some <hi>Trouble</hi> and <hi>Disturbance</hi> during this <hi>popish Monarch's</hi> Reign. How wretched a piece of Work must the Wisdom of the Pope and the whole Conclave undertake, to make <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Power under a <hi>popish Successour,</hi> those <hi>Feeble Serpents</hi> that shall but just <hi>bite our Heels</hi> to provoke our succeeding Vengeance to crush their <hi>Heads.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the second year of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> after the Repeal of King <hi>Edward's</hi> Laws, but before the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storation</hi> of the Pope's <hi>Supremacy,</hi> we are told in the History of the Reformation: (<hi>Abridg.</hi> B. 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 253.) of a <hi>project</hi> proposed <hi>by the Spanish Ambassadour to the Queen, of assuming the <hi>power</hi> of a Conquerour, and ruling at pleasure; by which she might restore both the Religion and the Abbey-Lands, and be under no Restraint. This she communicated to her Chancellour</hi> Gardiner, <hi>and charged him to give her his Opinion of it sincerely, as he would answer to God for it at the last day. He read it carefully, and told her it was a most <hi>pernicious</hi> Contrivance, and begg'd her not to listen to such</hi> Platforms <hi>which might be brought her by base Sycophants. Ʋpon that she burnt the</hi> Paper, <hi>and charged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassadour to bring her no more such <hi>projects.</hi> This gave</hi> Gardiner <hi>great Apprehensions of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs <hi>that Spanish Councils might bring upon the Nation: and so he procured the Act to be made; by which the Queen was bound by the <hi>Law,</hi> as much as her</hi> Ancestors <hi>were.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if that <hi>Bloody <hi>popish</hi> Zealot</hi> Gardiner was so violently <hi>averse</hi> to the Thought of bringing <hi>Arbitrary-<hi>power</hi>
               </hi> into <hi>England,</hi> for what Service soever to the Romish Cause, as in his Opinion so most <hi>pernicious;</hi> when at the same time the <hi>Majority,</hi> or <hi>Half</hi> of the Nation at least were of that <hi>perswasion.</hi> And if <hi>popish <hi>Standing Armies</hi>
               </hi> could have done the Feat, they were ten times easier to be rais'd for any Arbitrary <hi>popish purpose <hi>then;</hi>
               </hi> especially too, when the Queen lay in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some of that <hi>potent <hi>Spanish Husband</hi>
               </hi> (witness his <hi>Invincible Armada</hi> soon after against Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>) that could have lent her a very considerable <hi>Helping <hi>Hand</hi>
               </hi> from <hi>Forreign Assistance</hi> to push on the <hi>project,</hi> had her <hi>English Strength</hi> been <hi>Insufficient.</hi> Now I say, if nevertheless the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign was deem'd so <hi>pernicious <hi>then,</hi>
               </hi> what <hi>popish <hi>State Councellours</hi>
               </hi> at this time of day will run their <hi>own</hi> and their <hi>Prince's</hi> Fingers so far in the Fire, as to advise him to any such <hi>Arbitrary Projection <hi>now,</hi>
               </hi> under so <hi>low</hi> a <hi>Wane</hi> of Popery, that scarce the 200th. part of the Nation are of that Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and therefore infinitely <hi>more <hi>pernicious</hi>
               </hi> than in Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> Case, and consequently, which nothing but the most abandon'd <hi>Lunacy</hi> can ever pretend to <hi>advise,</hi> or <hi>attempt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true indeed, the <hi>popish <hi>Character</hi>
               </hi> lays down a most <hi>Expeditious</hi> Method of raising this <hi>dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Standing Army,</hi> that are to accomplish the mighty Feat of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery</hi> under a Romish Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessour; which for the Reader's Diversion take as follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To make the Pope</hi> Absolute, <hi>there wants a</hi> Standing-Army; <hi>and he shall have it. For who shall hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him? Nay, all his Commanders shall be qualify'd even by our present Protestant</hi> Test <hi>for the Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. He shall have enough Men of the Blade out of one half of the Gaming Houses in Town, to Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer twice as many Forces as he shall want. 'Tis true, they shall be Men of no Estates nor Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42213:6"/> But they shall fight as well as those that have</hi> Both. <hi>For people are ever as Valiant that have their Fortunes to</hi> raise, <hi>as those that have them to</hi> defend: <hi>Nay, of the two they shall be the more Faithful. For they have no</hi> Property <hi>to be concern'd for, and will more zealously serve him, by Reason their whole Interest and Estates lye in Him. And that this Army may be more</hi> quietly <hi>raysed, how many</hi> honourable Pretences may be found? <hi>Perhaps the greatest and most important</hi> Preservation <hi>of his Kingdom shall call for it: and then upon second Thoughts, instead of defeating some Forreign Enemy, they are opportunely ready to cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our Throats at <hi>Home,</hi>
               </hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This Projection I confess is the only passage through the whole <hi>Character,</hi> that endeavours to make out the <hi>possibility</hi> of any part of the numerous <hi>popish <hi>Mischiefs</hi>
               </hi> denounced through the whole <hi>Pamphlet.</hi> For all along it absolutely supposes the <hi>power</hi> of a <hi>popish</hi> Successour's doing whatever he pleases; and after so fallacious a <hi>Petitio principii,</hi> it leaps over all <hi>Mountains</hi> in the way, and only labours to prove the <hi>Depravity</hi> of a <hi>popish Successour</hi>'s Tyrannical <hi>Inclinations,</hi> and give him the <hi>Will</hi> of putting that <hi>power</hi> into Execution.</p>
            <p>But to examine the Depth of this Projection, granting such a Set of <hi>Atheistick Officers</hi> could be found; what then must their Army be? Here's a <hi>Forreign Invasion,</hi> or some other <hi>Honourable Cause</hi> proposed, and an Army raysed for that <hi>seeming</hi> Intent and Purpose: an Army of <hi>papists</hi> they cannot be, for there is not 10000 <hi>Men, Women,</hi> and <hi>Children</hi> of that <hi>perswasion</hi> in the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and consequently, far short of 10000 Fighting Men amongst them all; and possibly, not one half of <hi>them</hi> neither, such <hi>Foolhardy <hi>Desperadoes,</hi>
               </hi> as to hazard their <hi>Lives</hi> so <hi>madly</hi> and so <hi>extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly</hi> in so <hi>unpromising</hi> a Cause, so <hi>unaccomplishable</hi> a Design as Subjecting of <hi>England</hi> by the <hi>Hands</hi> of the <hi>papists.</hi> So that an Army of <hi>Papists</hi> can be no part of a <hi>popish <hi>Successour's</hi>
               </hi> Thoughts.</p>
            <p>And that the number of the <hi>papists</hi> in <hi>England</hi> is really no <hi>Greater.</hi> The King's <hi>Indulgence</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly to those of that Religon, in gratitude for their Loyal Endeavours at <hi>Worcester;</hi> and indeed through all his Fathers Distresses; has been so far from putting them to the Shifts of <hi>Disguises</hi> or <hi>Concealment</hi> of their <hi>Perswasions,</hi> that before the late wakening of the Laws against them, the <hi>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists</hi> were every where as <hi>visible,</hi> and generally as <hi>distinguishable</hi> from the rest of Mankind as <hi>one Sex</hi> is from <hi>another;</hi> insomuch that (unless their Numbers have Increased by <hi>Converts</hi> made since the <hi>popish <hi>Discovery,</hi>
               </hi> and the Execution of the <hi>Statutes</hi> against them) there's scarce <hi>one <hi>papist</hi>
               </hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that all his Neighbours round him cannot particularly <hi>point at.</hi> And how <hi>thin sown</hi> those <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists</hi> are, is notoriously manifest, when in many and many a ten Parishes together in <hi>England</hi> there is not three <hi>Papists,</hi> and the whole number computed through the Nation, scarce the 200th. Man of that <hi>Perswasion.</hi> Notwithstanding there have been many <hi>Fanatical Pretensions</hi> of wonderful <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Dispensations;</hi> by vertue of which, there are at least thirty or fourty thousand <hi>Church-papists</hi> as some old <hi>Oliverian</hi> Rebels shall tell you, tolerated by the Pope to an <hi>Absolute Protestant Ʋnifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity,</hi> and ready upon occasion, to show themselves in their <hi>proper</hi> Colours. The Villany of which <hi>Damnable <hi>Falshood</hi>
               </hi> is sufficiently apparent, from the forementiond <hi>Indulgence.</hi> For why such a Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensation? Why a playing the basest of <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> and <hi>Bantring with <hi>Religion, Sacraments,</hi>
               </hi> nay, <hi>GOD</hi> himself; (as such a <hi>Dispensation</hi> is no less) when under so universal an <hi>Impunity,</hi> there was not the <hi>least</hi> Occasion for it? There's a natural <hi>Pride</hi> in all <hi>Religions</hi> to <hi>avow</hi> their own Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; and no Man, like St. <hi>Peter,</hi> denyes his <hi>Master,</hi> unless, like <hi>him too,</hi> under some <hi>Apprehension</hi> of <hi>Danger</hi> in <hi>Owning</hi> him. And therefore these <hi>papal <hi>Dispensations</hi>
               </hi> must be the <hi>Second Part</hi> of <hi>Otes</hi> his <hi>Commissions,</hi> and nothing but the Restless Malice of <hi>Schisme,</hi> and the Diabolical Spirit of <hi>Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion</hi> can raise so false an Alarum of <hi>popery,</hi> and bugbear the Ignorant <hi>Rabble</hi> by so vile and so curs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an <hi>Imposture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return to our <hi>Standing Army.</hi> An Army of <hi>Papists</hi> is not to be had; and an Army of <hi>Atheists</hi> is as unfeizible as the other. For whatever dissolute <hi>Debauchees</hi> might possibly be culled out (as the <hi>Character</hi> tells you) of no <hi>Religion</hi> nor <hi>Principles,</hi> for a few particular <hi>Officers;</hi> the whole Gross of an Army of the same Stamp is not <hi>in rerum Naturâ:</hi> For if a <hi>popish Successour</hi> will have an Army of <hi>English-men,</hi> he must take them as he finds them, the loose and poorer sort of <hi>Rabble,</hi> the <hi>Bore</hi> and <hi>Peasant,</hi> the <hi>Refuse</hi> of the <hi>Shop</hi> and the <hi>Plough,</hi> which are ever the <hi>Composition</hi> of <hi>Armyes</hi> in a Kingdom not so extraordinary <hi>peopled</hi> as <hi>England,</hi> and these must be the Hands that this <hi>popish Successour</hi> must raise for his <hi>Standing Armyes.</hi> And if so, how far the Genius of the <hi>Commonalty</hi> of <hi>England</hi> lyes towards such a <hi>popish <hi>Ʋndertaking,</hi>
               </hi> and this <hi>No-popish</hi> Army shall push on to these <hi>All-popish</hi> Designs, is worthy our Consideration.</p>
            <p>Here's an Army expresly rais'd for a <hi>Forreign Invasion,</hi> or the like; and on the quite contrary, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to cut our own Throats at home; rays'd for the Kingdom's <hi>preservation,</hi> &amp; used for its <hi>down-right <hi>Destruction;</hi>
               </hi> and all this, forsooth, because their <hi>Arbitrary <hi>popishly</hi> Affected Officers</hi> shall pull off the <hi>Vizor,</hi> and <hi>wheel about,</hi> and at the word of <hi>Command,</hi> the whole Army after them. But the <hi>Quaery</hi> is, Whether they'll <hi>obey</hi> that <hi>Command,</hi> and be so tamely indifferent <hi>pro</hi> or <hi>con</hi> in thei <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> as to act the most <hi>opposite</hi> thing to what they were raysed for, and maintain perhaps the <hi>only Cause</hi> that they abhor.</p>
            <p>I confess, in the Quarrels of Princes and States, as to <hi>Forreign</hi> Engagements, the vindicating of a National Honour, or the enlarging of Dominion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Armyes are generally of their <hi>Leaders</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, and it boots little possibly to an <hi>English</hi> Army, whether ingaged against a <hi>Dutch</hi> or a <hi>French</hi> Enemy. But in <hi>Domestick</hi> and <hi>Intestine</hi> Jarrs, the Favour of the <hi>Cause</hi> ever animates the <hi>Arm</hi> that fights it. In all the <hi>popish <hi>Rebellions,</hi>
               </hi> or <hi>Massacres,</hi> whether in <hi>Ireland, Piedmont,</hi> or <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> whether <hi>for</hi> or <hi>against</hi> the Prince, or in all the several <hi>Hugenot</hi> Rebellions in <hi>Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:42213:7"/> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her Kingdoms of <hi>Europe;</hi> when <hi>Religion</hi> was the Quarrel, 'twas not the Command of the <hi>Leader</hi> but the <hi>Principle</hi> of the Party adhering to him, that was ever the <hi>First Mover</hi> on <hi>both</hi> sides. And a <hi>popish</hi> Cause in <hi>England</hi> can never move, but upon the same <hi>Axle.</hi> And nothing is more i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an to fancy such an Extravagance in any People or Religion in the World, as to swallow such <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite Obedience</hi> to Princes, as to do <hi>any Thing,</hi> or <hi>all Chings</hi> because <hi>Commanded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis not the first time that through prejudice to the Person or the Cause, disgusted Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers have shot through their <hi>Captains</hi> instead of their <hi>Enemies Heads,</hi> and the Fate of <hi>Kuniski</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the <hi>Cossacks,</hi> is no <hi>Original</hi> of the Kind; nor is it any such <hi>Rarity</hi> in History, to find whole <hi>Armies</hi> turn <hi>Deserters,</hi> and not only set up new <hi>Leaders,</hi> but new <hi>Soveraigns</hi> too. And truly upon engaging an <hi>English</hi> Army under so <hi>Bloody</hi> a <hi>popish <hi>Standard,</hi>
               </hi> what Assurance can this <hi>popish</hi> Successour propose to himself, not so much of going through with so <hi>crabbed</hi> a piece of Work, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ven of his own meer <hi>Safety</hi> under the Protection of <hi>such <hi>Hands</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Swords</hi> to uphold him? What Security shall he, or indeed can he in common reason expect from the <hi>Stubborn, obstinate</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Hands, a People too apt to fly in the very Face of Princes upon a less Provocation than so un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful a piece of Service: and that upon raising an Army for any such kind of purpose, he has not put the Sword into their very hands that may guide it to his <hi>own Throat,</hi> whil'st poss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bly they shall be opportunely raised for some more <hi>Darling-protestant</hi> Favourite to step into the Head of them, and dismount, not only their <hi>popish</hi> Officers, but <hi>popery</hi> too, and the very Royal <hi>popish <hi>Nimrod</hi> himself;</hi> nay, and perhaps use him with as little Remorse as the <hi>Turkish Janizaries</hi> have done several of their <hi>less hated</hi> Grand <hi>Seigniours</hi> under a much more <hi>Trivial</hi> Disgust.</p>
            <p>But to give an Example out of our English <hi>Chronicles,</hi> of the <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> of <hi>English Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes</hi> to a <hi>King <hi>they hate;</hi>
               </hi> I shall only refer the Reader to the Fate of King <hi>Richard</hi> the Third at <hi>Bosworth</hi> Field. <hi>Baker</hi> tells us, that <hi>Richard's Army</hi> was double the <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Number</hi> of his <hi>Adversarys,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Richmond's.</hi> Yet see the Infidelity of an <hi>English Army</hi> to a Prince under the <hi>popular <hi>Dissatisfaction</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Prejudice.</hi> A great part of his Army raised for his preservation, was actually ingaged in his <hi>Destruction.</hi> For the Lord <hi>Stanly</hi> by a Revolt with 2000 Horse, Sir <hi>William Stanly</hi> with a <hi>party</hi> of 3000 more; and with these Sir <hi>Walter Hungerford,</hi> Sir <hi>John Savage,</hi> Sir <hi>Brian Stanford,</hi> Sir <hi>Simon Digby,</hi> all Command<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, who withdrew likewise with their Respective <hi>Inferiour Souldiers,</hi> amounting between them, to the <hi>Majority</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Richard's</hi> whole <hi>Army,</hi> turned all to the Earl of <hi>Richmond,</hi> and carryed the whole Fortune of the day to the <hi>Victorious Enemies</hi> Side, to the Loss both of <hi>Richard's <hi>Crown</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Life</hi> together. Nay, he goes further, and expresly tells us, that in this Battle <hi>Henry,</hi> Earl of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> a Commander of <hi>Richard's</hi> Party, <hi>never strock Stroke;</hi> as likewise many other, who follow'd him moreout of <hi>Fear</hi> than <hi>Love:</hi> which <hi>Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> upon the same <hi>Revolt</hi> as the Lord <hi>Stanly,</hi> might undoubtedly have withdrawn their <hi>party</hi> to <hi>Richmond</hi> too. So that upon that dangerous and <hi>Fatal Rock,</hi> the <hi>people's Aversion,</hi> how easily are the <hi>Crowns</hi> and <hi>Lives</hi> of <hi>princes <hi>Shipwrack't?</hi>
               </hi> and what <hi>little Trust</hi> can <hi>Monarchs</hi> repose in the Strength and Swords of <hi>Armies</hi> whose <hi>Hearts</hi> are not <hi>Theirs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas! if <hi>Richard</hi> the <hi>Third</hi> found such <hi>Treachery</hi> from a <hi>Revolting Army;</hi> and an <hi>Antipathy</hi> so destructive to him; What <hi>Truth</hi> or <hi>Faith</hi> is a <hi>popish <hi>Tyrant</hi>
               </hi> like to find from Armies under a more <hi>universal</hi> and <hi>inveterate</hi> Detestation.</p>
            <p>For wherein was King <hi>Richard's</hi> Crime so great? (I mean, as to the <hi>people</hi>) 'Tis true, he <hi>Mounted</hi> the <hi>Throne</hi> by the most Inhumane of <hi>Murders.</hi> And from that only <hi>Grievance</hi> proceeded the <hi>Defection</hi> of his <hi>Souldiers,</hi> that cost him his <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Empire.</hi> But still, that was not half so great an Incentive to his <hi>Revolting Subjects,</hi> as the forementioned Barbarities of a <hi>popish <hi>Tyrant</hi>
               </hi> now. For though he was so deeply stain'd in <hi>Royal Blood,</hi> yet that was not so nearly felt by the <hi>people,</hi> as a Romish <hi>Tyrants</hi> cutting his <hi>Subjects</hi> Throats would be, by reason that <hi>Englishmen</hi> have ever a greater <hi>Tenderness</hi> of <hi>Themselves</hi> than their <hi>Princes.</hi> Besides, whatever Wrong he had done to the <hi>Royal Family,</hi> never had Prince more endeared himself (or endeavoured it, at least) than he to his <hi>people.</hi> For <hi>Baker</hi> gives this Account of him, <hi>That having gotten the Crown by pestilent Courses, he sought to Establish it by Wholesome Laws: for in no King's Reign were ever better Laws made, for the Ease and Solace of the people, or more Immunities granted to the Subject.</hi> Nor was there any thing of <hi>Religious Difference</hi> in his Case (<hi>Religion,</hi> that the <hi>Character</hi> tells you, <hi>sets all Nations in a Flame</hi>) For <hi>Richard</hi> and his <hi>Souldiers</hi> were of <hi>One Church;</hi> and so no part of the <hi>people's <hi>Hatred</hi>
               </hi> (as in the Case of <hi>popery</hi> now) nor any part of the <hi>Coals</hi> was blown up from that Wind. Yet, if under no Danger to <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> no <hi>Approach</hi> nor <hi>Apprehension</hi> of Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Slavery, nevertheless his <hi>parricides</hi> alone outweighed all other Merits, and their <hi>Hatred</hi> of <hi>Richard</hi> only on that Score, could turn his Subjects Swords against his own Breast; how much more violent an Aversion will the <hi>Hatred</hi> of a <hi>popish <hi>Tyrant,</hi>
               </hi> both for his <hi>Religion</hi> and his <hi>Cause</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether produce, being enough to exasperate the <hi>English Constitutions,</hi> not only into <hi>Rebels,</hi> but even into <hi>Savages</hi> too.</p>
            <p>But for a farther Instance of Revolting Armies, the History of <hi>Demetrius,</hi> Emperour of <hi>Russia,</hi> is a memorable Example. This <hi>Demetrius,</hi> the only Heir of the <hi>Empire,</hi> was in his Infancy stoln away to be rescued from the Danger of his Life from the Cruelty of the Usurper <hi>Boritz Fedoritz,</hi> then in possession of the Empire, and another Body very like him, was exposed <hi>Dead</hi> to the View of the <hi>people.</hi> This <hi>Demetrius</hi> being brought up in <hi>Poland</hi> with the <hi>Palatine <hi>Sandomir,</hi>
               </hi> after he had travelled into <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> for the space of twenty years, gave himself to be known for the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42213:7"/> So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Bazil,</hi> and Heir of <hi>Russia,</hi> and by the Assistance of the <hi>Palatine,</hi> the <hi>Jesuites,</hi> and the Favour o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>King</hi> himself, entred in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <hi>Muscovy,</hi> well accompanied with <hi>Germanes, Poles,</hi> and <hi>Cossacks▪</hi> Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inst wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m <hi>Boritz</hi> raised a <hi>puissant</hi> Army. Nevertheless the Infidelity of his People, who rose in Arms against him, together with several <hi>Losses</hi> sustained, deprived him both of <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rage</hi> and <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe,</hi> and thereupon he dyed, but left his Son to succeed him; who was received indeed by some of his <hi>Faction.</hi> But the City of <hi>Muscovy,</hi> together with all the Country, having joyn'd with <hi>Demetri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> throw <hi>Boritz</hi> Son into Prison, and Establish't <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>metrius</hi> upon the <hi>Throne;</hi> whose Corenation, (as 'tis la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gely described in the <hi>History of the Iron Age</hi>) was attended with such loud <hi>Transports</hi> of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ple,</hi> and such universal Acclamations of Joy, as could scarce be exceeded. Yet this very Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce had no sooner ascended the <hi>Throne,</hi> and was scarce yet <hi>warm</hi> in the Seat, but those very Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts whose <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Swords</hi> had so chearfully and vigorously asserted the Justice of his <hi>Cause</hi> and <hi>Birthri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ht,</hi> and advanced him to the <hi>Empire;</hi> nevertheless, understanding that he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mbraced the <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sh Faith,</hi> and acknowledge the <hi>Pope,</hi> and that he had introduced the <hi>Jesuites,</hi> as they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nded, to endeavour the <hi>Change</hi> of the <hi>Religion</hi> (which in <hi>Russia,</hi> is the <hi>Greek Church</hi>) fell so tot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly off from their <hi>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w Allegiance,</hi> and entred into so <hi>sudden</hi> and so <hi>perfidious</hi> a <hi>Conspiracy</hi> against him, that upon a General Uproar they fell upon the <hi>Poles,</hi> and others, as they were going to <hi>Court,</hi> insomuch that they overpower'd all the <hi>Forreign Assistance</hi> he had brought with him, and appreach't so near to his Palace, till the Emperour left his Queen, and got away, and upon persuit, leapt down f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om a <hi>Tower</hi> through a Window; at the Foot whereof (being found alive) he was forthwith dispatcht, and the Cruelty of the barbarous Multitude continued upon his dead Body, which they to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e in pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ces: And so swift was the Change of <hi>popular Affections,</hi> and so violent the <hi>Fury</hi> stirred up by the meer Alarum of <hi>altering the Religion,</hi> that all this prodigious <hi>Revolution</hi> was wrought in a <hi>Month's</hi> Time after his Acquisition of the <hi>Crown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if the <hi>Imaginary</hi> Introduction of <hi>Popery</hi> (as this was hitherto no more) could raise so ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid a <hi>Torrent,</hi> and so <hi>sudden</hi> a <hi>Turn</hi> of <hi>Tide</hi> from the Revolting <hi>Muscovites;</hi> what miraculous Fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty can a <hi>Romanist</hi> expect f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om <hi>Englishmen,</hi> under as great an Abhorrence of the Religion, and a more <hi>real</hi> Appearance of the aforenamed Tyrannous Eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts of it.</p>
            <p>But put the Case, the best and most plausible way, <hi>Viz</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t a <hi>popish Successour</hi> (as some peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will fancy) though really impossibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) could raise a whole Army of the same <hi>Stretching Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science</hi> as the <hi>Character</hi> has raised him <hi>Officers,</hi> a Crew of all <hi>Atheists,</hi> and neither <hi>Principles</hi> nor <hi>Religion</hi> were any <hi>part</hi> of their Consideration, and consequently plyable to any <hi>purpose</hi> whatever; as a Pack of such <hi>Reprobates</hi> as shall obey their Prince and his Officers in so unjustifyable a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> and so <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nnatural</hi> a <hi>piece</hi> of Service as cutting the <hi>Protestant</hi> Throats, or upholding those Arbitrary <hi>Judges</hi> that shall do it; what <hi>Faith</hi> shall he dare lodge in an Army so Qualified? For what shall hinder them, upon any <hi>Opportunity</hi> or <hi>Overture</hi> of greater advantage, from turning as great <hi>Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es <hi>against</hi>
               </hi> him as <hi>for</hi> him? and truly with as little Guilt, and as good Conscience on one side as 'tother. For an <hi>Actual Obedience,</hi> even to a Crown'd Head in the Execution of an <hi>Vnlawful <hi>Act,</hi>
               </hi> especially so notorious as the <hi>Massacring</hi> of his Subjects, and Destruction of the Government, is as much against our Duty, both as <hi>Christians</hi> and <hi>Subjects,</hi> as downright to rebell against him. And if this Army can stretch so far as to such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orrid <hi>popish</hi> Outrages, so much against the <hi>English</hi> Grain, 'tis very great Odds, but they'd much easier lean to their more <hi>Natural Byass</hi> on the o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her.</p>
            <p>I need not insist much farther upon the manifest Inability of <hi>Popery's</hi> Advancement by <hi>Armies</hi> or <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> when <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> of it self <hi>alone,</hi> without the other <hi>unweildy Clog</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> at the heels of it, has been ever adjudged so <hi>impracticable</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> that the very <hi>Conquer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, the <hi>Norman William</hi> thought not his Victory secure, but by ingaging to adhere to <hi>William</hi> the <hi>Confessours</hi> Laws, or at least, to introduce no <hi>Noveltyes,</hi> excepting such as <hi>Tryals</hi> by <hi>Juryes,</hi> or the like; and these to the <hi>Priviledge,</hi> not <hi>Infringement</hi> of the Peoples Liberties. And the <hi>long</hi> and <hi>Bloody <hi>Baron's</hi> Wars,</hi> upon a less Invasion of Liberty, are a sufficient Demonstration of the <hi>Ʋneasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> of Englishmen under any <hi>Yoke</hi> whatever. Insomuch that a <hi>popish Successour,</hi> under the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable Suspitions, and at best, but <hi>faint Affections</hi> of his People, is so far from a Capacity of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannizing</hi> either <hi>with <hi>Armyes,</hi>
               </hi> or <hi>without</hi> them, that he has no other Support both of <hi>Himself</hi> and his <hi>whole</hi> Party, but by following the forementiond Measures of <hi>Richard</hi> the Third, and either to <hi>indear</hi> himself by making of <hi>Wholesome Laws</hi> for the people's <hi>Freedom</hi> and <hi>Tranquility;</hi> or at least by keeping within the Bounds of those wholesome Ones they have already made for their Security.</p>
            <p>Now with all these <hi>Numerous</hi> and undeniable <hi>Blocks</hi> in his way, why must a <hi>popish Successour</hi> be <hi>Able,</hi> or indeed possest with so <hi>Enthusiastick</hi> a Presumption (for nothing less than <hi>Supernatural</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spirations will do it) as to <hi>Think</hi> himself <hi>able</hi> to accomplish that <hi>very Thing</hi> in <hi>England</hi> which was <hi>never done</hi> by Monarch <hi>before.</hi> Nay, to make the Presumption a little <hi>more prodigious,</hi> this very <hi>Successour,</hi> who of <hi>all</hi> the Kings since the Creation, has the <hi>worst Tools</hi> for such an <hi>Atchievement,</hi> must be the <hi>first</hi> and <hi>only</hi> person that is for undertaking it. For as a National Slavery is always the work of <hi>Time,</hi> and can get footing at best but by <hi>slow</hi> and <hi>subtle</hi> Encroachments; and likewise, if at all, is a thousand times more Feasible from a Prince that is the People's <hi>Darling,</hi> than one that is their <hi>Aversion.</hi> How unfit a Prince will a <hi>popish Successour</hi> be, for so hazardous an <hi>Attempt,</hi> when the <hi>continual</hi> and <hi>united</hi> Jealousies of his Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts will prevent the first part of the Danger, by <hi>fore-watching</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:42213:8"/> even the least Surprize or Arbitrary Encroachment upon them, and next will never furnish him with <hi>half hands enough</hi> to <hi>perfect</hi> the <hi>Ʋndertaking.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, but notwithstanding all this, there are a sort of People in the World that shall make An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer, that <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi> in a <hi>Papist</hi> is not a thing so <hi>new,</hi> nor so <hi>unpracticable,</hi> when the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>now <hi>French King</hi>
               </hi> is so manifest a Testimony to the <hi>Contrary.</hi> And truly there are but <hi>too many</hi> Incendiaries in this <hi>Age,</hi> that distract the <hi>Brain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ss</hi> part of Mankind with almost no other <hi>Gorgon,</hi> Viz. That the <hi>French</hi> King's <hi>Standing-Armyes</hi> are to be the <hi>Pattern</hi> of a <hi>popish Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessour</hi>'s Government, and the Persecution of <hi>his <hi>Hugonots,</hi>
               </hi> the very <hi>Fate</hi> of the Protestants in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whil'st under the <hi>Rose, Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery</hi> are to Copy from no other <hi>Original.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As this is one of the <hi>main</hi> Pretensions of the <hi>Whig-Fears,</hi> and indeed the <hi>Top-Demonstration</hi> of Popery and <hi>Arbitrary Power;</hi> so when truly examined, you'll find it just such an <hi>Apparition</hi> as <hi>Otes's</hi> bloody <hi>Pilgrims;</hi> the more <hi>terrible,</hi> the more <hi>ridiculous.</hi> For as 'tis the common Fate of all <hi>popular Arguments</hi> on that <hi>Subject;</hi> so much the more <hi>Formidable,</hi> still so much the more <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the <hi>Phantom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For first, not to i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sist much upon the General <hi>Mistake</hi> of Mankind, when possibly the <hi>French <hi>Arbitrary Power</hi>
               </hi> is infinitely magnifyed above what really it is; for excepting the <hi>French King's</hi> now and then fleecing an Over-rich <hi>Cheating</hi> Courtier a little <hi>Arbitrarily,</hi> and thereby, in truth, making but a <hi>Reprizal</hi> of his <hi>own,</hi> I could never yet learn by those that know the <hi>French</hi> Government, that any man's <hi>Meum</hi> or <hi>Tuum</hi> was <hi>Illegally</hi> taken away, or any Man's <hi>Life</hi> or <hi>Fortune</hi> stood or fell, but by the Judicial Process of the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land.</hi> 'Tis true indeed, his Wars have been <hi>Expensive,</hi> but then his <hi>Revenues</hi> have been <hi>large</hi> to support them; and not only that, but his Forreign <hi>Depredations</hi> have supplyed the greatest part of the Expence. Nevertheless whatever <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Taxes he may have raysed, to the Injury of any <hi>particular</hi> aggrieved Subject, or whatever <hi>Tyranny</hi> he may have exercised over the <hi>distrest</hi> and <hi>persecuted <hi>Hugonots,</hi>
               </hi> if either of the two can be <hi>properly <hi>Arbitrary</hi>
               </hi> or <hi>Tyrannick,</hi> when past into a <hi>Low,</hi> and made a <hi>Decrée</hi> enacted by <hi>parliament,</hi> as both the <hi>Taxes</hi> and the <hi>present Hugon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Persecution</hi> are; the <hi>French</hi> King's <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Incroachments in <hi>France,</hi> are no precedent for a <hi>popish <hi>Successour's</hi> Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and that because the State and Constitution of the Two Kingdoms are so extreamly <hi>different,</hi> that there is not the least Ground for such a Foundation <hi>here</hi> as <hi>there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For first as to the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Genius</hi> of the <hi>People:</hi> In <hi>France,</hi> the Peasants <hi>ab Origine</hi> have not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed <hi>half</hi> the <hi>Priviledges</hi> and <hi>Immunityes</hi> of the <hi>Freeborn</hi> people of <hi>England.</hi> And therefore under that <hi>sordid</hi> Education, as knowing <hi>no better,</hi> and being in a manner <hi>inured</hi> to <hi>Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very,</hi> 'tis no such great wonder to see the <hi>French Commonalty submitting</hi> to s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch Oppression, as indeed, why should they otherwise, when they submit but to <hi>Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if the <hi>French King</hi> has any <hi>greater Ascendance</hi> over <hi>his <hi>Parliaments</hi>
               </hi> than the Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> over <hi>Theirs,</hi> to <hi>perform</hi> all this; why should that be any Rarity, when in reality they are of so <hi>different</hi> a Constitution from those of <hi>England,</hi> that they are rather the <hi>settled <hi>Magistrrey</hi>
               </hi> of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion than any thing like <hi>Our</hi> Parliaments; and as <hi>Ours</hi> are of the <hi>peopl's</hi> Election, <hi>Theirs</hi> in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner only the <hi>King's,</hi> every Member of the <hi>French</hi> Parliaments holding his Office not only for <hi>Life</hi> but even to his <hi>Heirs,</hi> unless alienated by the Prince upon a <hi>Forfeiture,</hi> or any personal <hi>Dislike;</hi> that in short, as being the <hi>Creatures</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> they are truly more like a <hi>Turkish DIVAN</hi> than an <hi>English <hi>House</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in fine, to make a Parallel of our Dangers between the State of the two Nations, which in truth is bringing <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South</hi> together. <hi>BECAƲSE</hi> a <hi>popish French <hi>King,</hi>
               </hi> with the <hi>Majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of the Kingdom of his own Religion, the <hi>Religion</hi> Established by <hi>Law,</hi> and Flourishing in Glory; by help of such vaste <hi>Armies</hi> too, intirely of that Religion, and thereby <hi>principled</hi> for his own <hi>Service,</hi> can squeeze some particular of his Subjects Purses a little <hi>Arbitrarily,</hi> and <hi>oppress</hi> and <hi>persecute</hi> the poor forlorn <hi>Hugonots,</hi> a Party infinitely the <hi>Minority,</hi> disabled too from all <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> and at highest, but suffered by the Indulgence of the State, and that even with the most <hi>favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Aspect</hi> of the Government, under that <hi>pittance</hi> of Encouragment, that (for Example) to the <hi>whole Body</hi> of the Reformers inhabiting in that vaste and populous City of <hi>Paris,</hi> there is tolerat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but <hi>One</hi> Hugonot <hi>Church,</hi> and that standing like our <hi>Pancras,</hi> only more Miles out of Town, because I say, the <hi>French King</hi> under these Circumstances can do <hi>all this: THEREFORE</hi> (pray mark it) a <hi>popish English</hi> King with his <hi>Diminitive</hi> Romish Party, the most <hi>inconsiderable <hi>Handful</hi>
               </hi> of the Nation, under not only the Censure of the <hi>Law,</hi> but the utter <hi>Abhorrence</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> with the help of an <hi>Army</hi> (if he has any) of a quite <hi>contrary</hi> Religion, and thereby <hi>whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unprincipled</hi> for the Service intended, shall <hi>vanquish</hi> and <hi>subject</hi> the <hi>Protestant Establish't</hi> Religion in all its Lustre and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rength, upheld by all the Fortifications of <hi>Law,</hi> and by <hi>Numbers</hi> even to a more than <hi>hundredfold Majority;</hi> whil'st the English Protestants are not only to feel the <hi>French</hi> Hugonots Smart, but (if either the Fanatical <hi>Suggestions,</hi> or the <hi>popish Character</hi> speaks <hi>Truth</hi>) to groan under a hundred times <hi>(Oh! Monstrum Horrendum!) more dismal <hi>Persecution</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very:</hi> the present <hi>French</hi> Arbitrary Stretch being little more than a <hi>Fleabiting</hi> to <hi>our total <hi>Aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               </hi> of our <hi>Laws, Libertyes</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to make this <hi>French Goblin more monstrous still,</hi> there are some People that go a Bowes Shoot farther yet, and will tell you, that by the aforesaid <hi>almost <hi>Omnipotent</hi>
               </hi> Things called <hi>Standing-Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes, a <hi>popish Successour</hi>
               </hi> shall not only crush our Protestant <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> to pieces <hi>Himself,</hi> but likewise <hi>hectour</hi> our very <hi>parliaments</hi> to that degree, as to force them to the giving up <hi>our very
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42213:8"/> Birthrights</hi> to him, nay, to the very passing of at once both <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery <hi>into Law it self;</hi>
               </hi> and then Lord have Mercy upon poor <hi>lost England.</hi> For alas! the same Absolute uncontroulable Soveraignty that the <hi>French King</hi> has over his <hi>Parliaments,</hi> is (they'll tell you) the intended <hi>Scheme</hi> of a <hi>popish Dominion</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> And then <hi>where!</hi> Oh <hi>where!</hi> is our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> when that black Day once comes?</p>
            <p>Now in the Name of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> what Infernal Impudence reigns in the World, when such <hi>Rank,</hi> such <hi>Nonsensical Stuff</hi> as this can be asserted by <hi>Rogues,</hi> and credited by <hi>Fools.</hi> For besides the most infamous Calumny that this <hi>execrable Imputation</hi> throws upon the whole Body of the Nation, <hi>Viz.</hi> That <hi>Englishmen</hi> shall be such <hi>tame,</hi> such <hi>abject,</hi> such <hi>despicable Wretches</hi> and <hi>Cowards,</hi> as out of any personal Fear whatever, to yield up their <hi>Laws, Rights,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> to the Ruine of themselves and their Posterity, and thereby offer, as it were, even their own <hi>Throats</hi> to the <hi>Slaughter.</hi> What Relation has the present Management in <hi>France</hi> to that of Popery in <hi>England,</hi> or the <hi>French</hi> King's P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rliamentary Influence to that of a <hi>popish <hi>Successour's?</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>For whatever extraordinary Obedience or Subjection the <hi>French Parliaments</hi> may yield to their King in the grant of any <hi>Oppressive Impositions</hi> upon the Subject to advance their King's Exorbitant Power and Greatness; are the <hi>French King's</hi> Arbitrary Endeavours to root up the <hi>Foundations</hi> of his <hi>popish Laws</hi> and the <hi>Establish't Religion</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> which <hi>vice versa,</hi> is the Case in <hi>England;</hi> so that if a <hi>popish</hi> Successour can hector our English <hi>Parliaments</hi> to no <hi>farther</hi> a <hi>Complyance</hi> than the <hi>French</hi> King do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>His,</hi> the Devil an Inch of Ground will <hi>Popery</hi> get in <hi>England;</hi> for as I take it, the <hi>French</hi> Parliaments are all <hi>popish;</hi> and as such, are in so little danger of their <hi>Religion,</hi> that truly their Prince in the other Extream is in the <hi>highest Extravagance</hi> of Advanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.</p>
            <p>So that unless we state the Parrallel between the two Kings <hi>Thus,</hi> Viz. (Supposing the <hi>French</hi> King a <hi>Hugonot,</hi> which is but <hi>turning <hi>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ables</hi>) that then both his <hi>popish</hi> Armies and <hi>popish</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments would nevertheless be <hi>awed</hi> and <hi>bullyed</hi> into that <hi>intire Submission</hi> to him, as to abolish the <hi>Fundamental Laws</hi> of the Kingdom, and thereby subject <hi>themselves</hi> and all their Brethren <hi>Papists</hi> to the self same <hi>Persecution</hi> and <hi>Slavery</hi> under the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> that the <hi>Hugonots</hi> suffer under <hi>Them:</hi> without which Supposition his Tyranny is wholly <hi>alien</hi> to our <hi>popish</hi> Successour's; and nothing but the most Villanous <hi>Phanatical Sophistry</hi> dares cant at this wretched rate, to pretend to make the <hi>French</hi> Tyranny a <hi>Model</hi> for English <hi>Popery</hi> to work by. But put the Case there were a <hi>French Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonot</hi> King, and that had the forementioned purpose in Agitation, either by <hi>Armies</hi> or <hi>Parliaments</hi> (as <hi>plyable</hi> as the <hi>French Genius</hi> is supposed to be) his <hi>Ill Success</hi> in such an Exploit might be soon guest, by the <hi>Difficulties</hi> and <hi>Obstructions</hi> of their <hi>Hugonot <hi>Henry</hi>
               </hi> the 4th. in his way to the Throne under but a suspition of inclining that way. And consequently, what worse Success would attend the like popish Changes in <hi>England,</hi> under the manifest <hi>disproportion</hi> of the English <hi>Papists</hi> to the French <hi>Hugonots,</hi> is past dispute,</p>
            <p>However, if neither English Armies nor English Parliaments can do the <hi>popish</hi> Feat, there's one last Expedient yet to <hi>vanquish</hi> all <hi>Obstacles,</hi> and that I assure you, (if no small Authors may be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved) a most puissant one, <hi>Viz.</hi> If the <hi>popish</hi> Hands in <hi>England</hi> are too weak to enslave us, this <hi>popish</hi> Successour shall borrow the Assistance of <hi>popish <hi>Neighbours</hi>
               </hi> to help out, and so what cannot be done by <hi>Domestick Forces,</hi> shall be perform'd by a <hi>Forreign Army,</hi> call'd over on purpose. This Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient I confess, is so much the more <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>ble,</hi> as it has some little Affinity to <hi>Bedlow's</hi> St. <hi>Jago Expedition,</hi> and truly has sometimes had the Honour to be harangued upon even in a <hi>House of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> as no small <hi>Danger</hi> from <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But notwithstanding the Authority and Veracity this Projection may seem to arrogate from its Admission into an <hi>Honourable</hi> House of Parliament; upon due Examination, I am half afraid, 'twill prove but one of the <hi>Observator's</hi> downright <hi>Twangers.</hi> For if this <hi>popish Successour</hi> be for setting up <hi>Popery</hi> by <hi>pitch't Battles</hi> and plain <hi>Conquest,</hi> and that too, by <hi>Outlandish Ayde;</hi> in the first place he must have far more than <hi>tenfold</hi> as many <hi>Forreign popish Hands</hi> as he has of his <hi>own</hi> to pretend at least to a strength able to subdue <hi>England;</hi> nay, and in truth, here's one <hi>unlucky Circumstance</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, that is, if he can borrow <hi>popish</hi> Neighbours, 'tis odds but the <hi>protestants</hi> may borrow <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant</hi> Neighbours too upon occasion; for Princes have as often lent Armies to succour <hi>opprest Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> as to assist <hi>Oppressing Tyrants.</hi> But let that pass.</p>
            <p>But supposing the best face of the thing, that there were some <hi>Chance</hi> for him in this <hi>bold</hi> Cast, and that after his setting of <hi>Honour, Life, Empire</hi> all at a Throw upon the hazard of <hi>War,</hi> there were only an <hi>even Lay</hi> of <hi>Keeping</hi> or <hi>loosing</hi> them, a <hi>Caesar</hi> aut <hi>nullus,</hi> 'twere a little more pardonable Venture. But as the Devil would have it, there's not one syllable of this in the Matter. For if overthrown, he's so <hi>irrevocably lost,</hi> that possibly not only his <hi>own</hi> Ruine, but that of all his <hi>Royal Family,</hi> and of <hi>Monarchy</hi> it self goes together. But admitting he <hi>Conquers,</hi> the Question is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Caesarship</hi> on the other side be so <hi>secure</hi> or no?</p>
            <p>For truly, what if the aforesaid <hi>tenfold Majority</hi> of <hi>Forreign</hi> Conquerours should make bold to pass a <hi>Civ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l Complement</hi> upon this Successour <hi>Militant,</hi> and the rest of his <hi>popish <hi>Remnant,</hi>
               </hi> and fairly <hi>keep</hi> the Victory when they have got it. For I assure him little <hi>England</hi> is a pritty Parcel of <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra firma,</hi> and 'twere no <hi>small <hi>Temptation</hi>
               </hi> to <hi>popish</hi> or <hi>no popish</hi> Fingers to be a little tenacious with so fortunate a Prize. And when those <hi>Triumphant Forreigners</hi> have tasted the <hi>sweet Air</hi> of so <hi>delicate a Spot</hi> as <hi>England,</hi> 'tis fourty to one whether <hi>They,</hi> or at least the <hi>Crown'd Head</hi> that <hi>lends</hi> them, will be <hi>overhasty</hi> of resigning so <hi>inviting</hi> a <hi>Trophy</hi> as the <hi>English Diadem;</hi> and truly cosi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42213:9"/> the <hi>Blackness</hi> of the Cause they came over to ingage in, if any Forreign Prince can lend an Army for so <hi>Dishhonourable</hi> a Quarrel, which indeed all Nations and all <hi>Religions</hi> must cry <hi>Shame</hi> against, with much <hi>less <hi>Dishonour</hi>
               </hi> may he wear the <hi>Lawrel</hi> he <hi>wins,</hi> and assume that vanquish't King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to himself, when he <hi>robs</hi> but a <hi>Robber,</hi> and at most <hi>deposes</hi> a <hi>Cut-throat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore to make Instance in the Case, what <hi>popish</hi> Successour will venture to call over, sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose thirty or forty thousand <hi>French</hi> to enslave his people (and thereby at one dash loose his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's Hearts beyond all <hi>Thoughts</hi> of a <hi>Recovery</hi>) as thither indeed the <hi>Whig</hi> Fears <hi>seem</hi> to <hi>point</hi>) upon a Confidence that the <hi>now <hi>French</hi>
               </hi> King's <hi>Generosity,</hi> though possibly not the <hi>best Faith-keeper</hi> in Christendom, after the Accomplishment of the Conquest, will make so intire a <hi>Resignation</hi> of all Pretensions of <hi>Victory</hi> to <hi>Establish</hi> this <hi>Absolute Popish Sultan:</hi> especially considering the <hi>insatiate Ambition</hi> of that aspiring Prince to <hi>Vniversal Monarchy,</hi> and particularly to the <hi>Soveraignty</hi> of the <hi>Seas;</hi> which though with all his present great Ships under the <hi>Maritime Weakness</hi> of <hi>France</hi> he cannot atchieve, he might <hi>intirely</hi> possess by so <hi>opportune</hi> and so <hi>important</hi> an Addition to his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quests as <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now they must have a wonderful Stock of <hi>Faith,</hi> with no small mixture of <hi>Madness,</hi> that can <hi>really believe</hi> any popish Crown'd Head in the World will ever play so cursed a <hi>Loosing Game,</hi> and take that Path towards Popery, with two such amnable Precipices both on the <hi>Right</hi> Hand and the <hi>Left,</hi> that the very <hi>Masterpiece</hi> of the Projection is but in effect writing his <hi>own</hi> MENE TE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>KEL over his <hi>own Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that all the forementioned <hi>Impotence</hi> and <hi>Impossibilities</hi> of <hi>popish</hi> and <hi>arbitrary</hi> Tyrannys Introduction into <hi>England,</hi> being fully demonstrated; I have only this to add; There is no greater Mistake in the generality of Mankind, than an <hi>Imbibed Opinion,</hi> that the <hi>Papists</hi> think themselves <hi>obliged</hi> to endeavour the setting up of their Religion <hi>hap-hazard, right</hi> or <hi>wrong, hand</hi> over <hi>head,</hi> without Consideration or Regard to the <hi>Issue</hi> or <hi>Success</hi> of the Undertaking; and that in fine, a <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Successour</hi> will certainly muster all <hi>Forces</hi> and all <hi>Engines</hi> to attempt the <hi>Storming</hi> of the whole <hi>Protestant Liberty</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> though under a tenfold Odds of laying <hi>his very Bones</hi> at the <hi>Siege.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Grossness of this popular Errour will appear from the <hi>past Conduct</hi> of all the <hi>Papists</hi> in all <hi>Ages</hi> and all <hi>Countreys,</hi> when they never attempted a <hi>Rebellion, Massacre,</hi> or any such <hi>Monstrous Design,</hi> but where they had, not only <hi>proper <hi>popish Instruments</hi>
               </hi> for the Service, but also a <hi>popish Strength</hi> capable in all reasonable prospect of going <hi>Through-stitch</hi> with it. Besides a <hi>Bigot</hi> in <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> is nevertheless a <hi>Statesman</hi> in the <hi>Establishing</hi> of that Religion, and excepting such <hi>Bedla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite Enthusiasts</hi> as the old Fifth Monarchy <hi>Adventures,</hi> there's <hi>Policy</hi> as well as <hi>Faith</hi> in all Churches; and how far soever <hi>Faith</hi> may stretch, <hi>Policy</hi> moves in the Bounds of <hi>Reason,</hi> and he that can believe the greatest <hi>lying <hi>Miracle</hi>
               </hi> in a <hi>Romish Legend,</hi> will never trust to <hi>Miracles</hi> in a <hi>Romish Battalia.</hi> And were a <hi>popish</hi> Successour in his Nature ten times, if possible, a <hi>Bloodyer-minded</hi> Tyrant than the very <hi>Character</hi> has shaped him, if he wants <hi>Humane Strength</hi> to enslave us, let us not suspect his relying on <hi>Divine</hi> or <hi>Infernal</hi> Assistance, the <hi>Ayd</hi> of <hi>Angels</hi> or <hi>Devils</hi> to help him.</p>
            <p>And truly when a popish Successour shall seriously consider the Temper of the <hi>Head-strong</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, a people always <hi>impatient</hi> of Wrongs, to that degree of <hi>Ill-nature</hi> in the <hi>Resentment</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution</hi> of <hi>Ills</hi> above all Mankind beside, that whereas all other Nations cry <hi>[Run Rogue]</hi> 'tis observable the English Note is ever <hi>[Stop Thief]</hi> But above all, a People so <hi>nicely Jealous</hi> of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,</hi> that the very <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Oppression</hi> (especially from the <hi>Crown-side</hi>) without the <hi>Thing,</hi> is enough to make them slip the Bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t and run <hi>stark mad;</hi> insomuch that a King of <hi>England</hi> is but <hi>too justly</hi> call'd a <hi>King of Devils;</hi> when he considers all this, I say, a <hi>popish</hi> Successour, a thousand to one, will never venture the raising those <hi>mutinous</hi> English <hi>Devils,</hi> without a Charm <hi>full strong enough</hi> to <hi>lay</hi> them again. And whatever his Inclinations might be for the <hi>Heretick Slavery,</hi> yet as
<q>Vana est sine viribus Ira.</q>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis not the Thunder in a <hi>Popish Successour's <hi>Heart,</hi>
               </hi> but his <hi>Hand</hi> that can hurt us, and where the Arm's <hi>too weak,</hi> and the <hi>Bolt <hi>too unweildy,</hi>
               </hi> let us never trouble our Heads with fearing the <hi>Blow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that Point, <hi>Viz.</hi> A <hi>popish</hi> Successours <hi>POWER</hi> of <hi>Enslaving, Persecuting, Burning,</hi> &amp;c. being sufficiently discust, let us next examine the Veracity of the <hi>Character</hi> in another <hi>Point,</hi> that is, granting he either <hi>had,</hi> or fancy'd he had the <hi>Power</hi> of doing it; <hi>Quaery,</hi> whither it necessarily follows that he must have the <hi>Will</hi> to do it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Character,</hi> 'tis true (as I said before) makes him <hi>plunge headlong</hi> into the Breach of all <hi>Promises, Vows, Obligations, Oaths</hi> and <hi>Sacraments,</hi> all the Dictates even of <hi>Morality</hi> and <hi>Common Humanity,</hi> and what not; and renders it withall so <hi>inseperable</hi> an <hi>Impulse</hi> and <hi>Principle</hi> of a <hi>popish Conscience,</hi> that in a manner, that popish Prince that <hi>neglects</hi> so incumbent and meritorious a Duty, is little less in the popish <hi>Ballance</hi> than a <hi>Judas</hi> or a <hi>Julian,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Though I confess, for all this terrible <hi>Oathbreaking,</hi> the two Instances recited in the <hi>Character</hi> to prove this <hi>universal popish Infidelity</hi> are possibly the <hi>Idlest</hi> that a Man could wish to meet with. The First of them is Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> Breach of <hi>Promise</hi> of their Quiet Exercise of the <hi>Protestant <hi>Religion,</hi>
               </hi> made to the <hi>Norfolk</hi> and <hi>Suffolk</hi> Inhabitants that mounted her to her <hi>Throne,</hi> which I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge was both <hi>ungratefully,</hi> and in the highest degree <hi>dishonourably</hi> done; yet when truly weighed, is far from any thing of that damnable Law-breaking popish <hi>Perjury</hi> that the <hi>Character</hi> all along endeavours to blacken all <hi>Romish Princes</hi> with; that on the contrary, though 'tis true,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42213:9"/> she broke her <hi>Promise</hi> given to <hi>Capitulating Rebels;</hi> for the <hi>Norfolk</hi> and <hi>Suffolk</hi> Inhabitants were indeed <hi>little better;</hi> for as their utmost Endeavours of setting their <hi>Lawful Soveraign</hi> upon her <hi>Throne,</hi> was their absolute indispensible Duty, whatever her Requital might be, yet the <hi>Chronicle</hi> tells us they refus'd the Queen any Assistance whatever till they had first condition'd with her, and extorted that <hi>Promise</hi> from her. And if nevertheless she broke that <hi>Promise</hi> afterwards with them; here was no <hi>Tyrannick Cruelty</hi> exercised, nor any <hi>Coronation Oath</hi> Violated, when she only burnt them by <hi>Law;</hi> and as her <hi>Coronation Oath</hi> obliged her to rule by <hi>Law,</hi> 'twas only her <hi>Misfortune</hi> to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lieve the Equity of that <hi>Sanguinary Law,</hi> and accordingly, to <hi>act</hi> by it, and consequently, their <hi>Misery</hi> to feel the <hi>Scourge</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>The 2d. Instance of a <hi>Certain Gentleman</hi> on the <hi>Other side the Water,</hi> that once took the <hi>Sacrament</hi> never to invade <hi>Flanders;</hi> which since he hath so notoriously broken: and the Inference from thence, that a <hi>popish Successour</hi> will much more break all Oaths, for the <hi>meritorious</hi> Propagation of his <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> when a <hi>popish <hi>Prince</hi>
               </hi> has violated even <hi>Sacraments</hi> themselves for his <hi>irregular, unjustifyable <hi>Ambition;</hi>
               </hi> is so impertinently urg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, that nothing can be less to the <hi>Purpose.</hi> For that Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Breach of his <hi>Sacramentary Oath</hi> is no Sin of the <hi>papist,</hi> but the <hi>Man,</hi> not a Principle of his <hi>Religion,</hi> but the fault of his little or no <hi>Religion</hi> in so slight a Regard of so <hi>sacred</hi> an <hi>Obligation,</hi> wherein his <hi>Ambition</hi> overpowered his <hi>Christianity;</hi> and possibly under his Lust of Power, an <hi>Oath</hi> upon the <hi>Bible</hi> or the <hi>Alcoran</hi> might be much of a <hi>Strength.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to find a better Example of <hi>Popish Perfidy</hi> than the <hi>Character</hi> affords, I acknowledge the <hi>hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid</hi> and most <hi>barbarous <hi>Infidelity</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>Charles</hi> the 9th. of <hi>France</hi> and the Impious and Execrable <hi>Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacre</hi> of the <hi>French Protestants</hi> by that <hi>Inhumane</hi> and <hi>Treacherous</hi> Monarch's <hi>Machinations:</hi> which <hi>Davilah,</hi> an Historian of his own Church describes with <hi>Detestation,</hi> and which all <hi>Religions</hi> must re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member with <hi>Horrour:</hi> but at the same time, to do Justice likewise to the <hi>Hugonot</hi> Guilt, all good Men ought to reflect on the three <hi>Hugonot</hi> Rebellions in his <hi>Reign</hi> (though whatever their Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation were) as wholly <hi>unallowable</hi> by the Laws of <hi>God;</hi> and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir <hi>Daylight <hi>Bloodsbed</hi>
               </hi> such a Blot in a <hi>Christian Scutcheon,</hi> which nothing but the others <hi>Midnight <hi>Murders</hi>
               </hi> could exceed; and possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly those Rebellions no small <hi>Incentive</hi> to that <hi>Diabolical Assassination.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I confess likewise, that I have read in a more <hi>sacred</hi> Record, now the <hi>Jews</hi> upon <hi>Picques</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venges</hi> have cut off almost <hi>whole Tribes</hi> amongst them; but at the same time, as 'tis certain, those <hi>Throat-cuttings</hi> committed upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir Breth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en, were against their <hi>Religion</hi> and the Laws of <hi>God;</hi> and which nothing but Exemplary <hi>Penitence</hi> could <hi>Atone,</hi> so the <hi>Massacring</hi> Spirit of <hi>Charles</hi> the 9th. when rightly scan'd, will not be found so <hi>Canonizing</hi> a Qualification in a <hi>Romanist,</hi> as the World <hi>suspects</hi> it.</p>
            <p>For if it were really that <hi>Signally Meritorious</hi> Principle of <hi>Popery,</hi> how comes it about that there's so <hi>few <hi>Popish Champions</hi>
               </hi> in so <hi>Holy</hi> a <hi>Popish <hi>War?</hi>
               </hi> For to instance the Practices of the <hi>Romanists</hi> in all Kingdoms, and all <hi>Ages</hi> since the Reformation. In the first place, in <hi>France</hi> (as Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> in his Preface to his <hi>Rights of Princes</hi> assures us) the <hi>Hugonots</hi> enjoyed their <hi>Liberties,</hi> and the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick unmolested <hi>Toleration</hi> of their <hi>Worship</hi> for several King's Reigns together; nay, and what's <hi>particularly</hi> remarkable, the Edicts that confirm'd that <hi>Toleration</hi> were granted all by popish Kings and a <hi>Majority</hi> of <hi>Papists</hi> in Parliament, a Favour which was never granted to the <hi>Papists</hi> by any <hi>protestant <hi>Parliament</hi>
               </hi> whatever since the first Establishment of the Reformation in <hi>England.</hi> Nor is this <hi>popish</hi> Good Nature peculiar only to the <hi>French</hi> Climate, when so many of the Principalities of <hi>Germany,</hi> and of the <hi>Cantons</hi> in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> where <hi>Popery</hi> is the <hi>Church Establish't,</hi> have from <hi>Age</hi> to <hi>Age</hi> continued the same <hi>Toleration</hi> of the Reformers in the publick <hi>Impunity</hi> of their <hi>Persons</hi> and <hi>Estates,</hi> and the <hi>Exercise</hi> of their <hi>Devotion.</hi> Now if <hi>Persecuting</hi> and <hi>enslaving</hi> of Hereticks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were so highly meritorious in the <hi>popish <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urch,</hi>
               </hi> nay, the very <hi>Shibboleth</hi> of the <hi>popish Christianity,</hi> as the <hi>Malice</hi> of popish <hi>Characters,</hi> and the Prejudice and Fear of English <hi>Fools</hi> has represented them, and that the highest of <hi>papal Blessings</hi> and Seats in Heaven were the promis'd Reward of such <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scendent <hi>Merit;</hi>
               </hi> what unpardonable <hi>Apostacy</hi> lyes at the Doors of almost the whole Body of <hi>Papists</hi> through the World, and what <hi>Curses</hi> and <hi>Anathema's</hi> must such <hi>wilful,</hi> such <hi>undutiful,</hi> and such <hi>graceless</hi> Omission of a Duty so <hi>Obligatory,</hi> the Remissness and Lethargy of so many Kingdoms and Principalities from so many Generations to Generations, deserved.</p>
            <p>But alas! as the <hi>Tree is known by the Fruit;</hi> and the Test of all <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Inclinations</hi> (I mean, under no <hi>Restraint</hi>) are their <hi>Actions;</hi> and as all those popish Governments have the popish <hi>Majority</hi> and <hi>Strength</hi> on their side; and thereby are in a visible Capacity of <hi>Oppressing</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuting</hi> their <hi>weaker</hi> Here<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ick Subjects; therefore this general <hi>Indulgence</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> is an <hi>unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable</hi> Argument, that under the <hi>POWER</hi> of <hi>Tyranny</hi> and <hi>Cruelty,</hi> they manifestly want the WILL. And whil'st their <hi>Lenity</hi> and <hi>Clemency</hi> so much exceeds even that of their <hi>Boasting <hi>Accusers,</hi>
               </hi> and the Favourable <hi>Concession</hi> of Romanists to Hereticks, outdoes that of Hereticks to <hi>Them;</hi> the Injustice of so false an Attainder, and so infamous an <hi>Imputation</hi> is sufficiently confront<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from such a Cloud of numerous Examples to the Contrary; whil'st it does no more follow, that a <hi>popish</hi> Successour, by the Tenents of his Church, must hold himself <hi>obliged</hi> to be a second <hi>Charles</hi> the 9th. or any thing like him (had he the Ability of being so) than that every <hi>popish <hi>Priest</hi>
               </hi> must be a <hi>Mariana</hi> or a <hi>Clements,</hi> and every <hi>Papist</hi> a <hi>Raviliac.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that if it be true, as the <hi>Character</hi> affirms, That a <hi>popish</hi> Successour in England, that <hi>keeps Faith</hi> with Hereticks, and <hi>Rules by Law,</hi> will be <hi>the greatest Laughing-Stock of the whole World, whil'st all <hi>Roman Catholick</hi>
               </hi> Princes <hi>will deride the Feebleness of his Arm, and the Tameness of his</hi> Spirit <hi>for <hi>sparing</hi> a Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>got</hi> in <hi>Smithfield, &amp;c.</hi> 'Tis very strange that those very Princes should so loudly exclaim against <hi>Him</hi> for that very <hi>Fault</hi> in which <hi>Themselves</hi> are five hundred times more criminal
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42213:10"/> than <hi>He <hi>can</hi>
               </hi> be, by reason their greater Romish Transgression (if it be one) is so much more <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excusable,</hi> as <hi>THEY</hi> have popish <hi>Opportunity, Strength, Power</hi> and <hi>Dominion</hi> to capacitate them for such a Persecution, and the Devil an <hi>One</hi> of them has <hi>HE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And at the same time (if it be the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi>) the <hi>Pope</hi> himself too, in so extraordinary severe an <hi>Imposition</hi> upon an <hi>English Romanist,</hi> must be prodigiously <hi>partial,</hi> nay, a worse than <hi>Egyptian Taskmaster,</hi> to lay such Rigorous Injunctions upon so <hi>Impotent</hi> a <hi>popish</hi> Soveraignty here in England, and yet allow such <hi>profuse Dispensations,</hi> and such <hi>extravagant Latitude</hi> to the more <hi>powerful</hi> Papists through all the World beside.</p>
            <p>Now after this pretended Brittleness of either <hi>Promises Obligations</hi> or <hi>Oaths,</hi> let us come to the next dreadful <hi>Phaenomenon</hi> of <hi>Tyrant</hi> and <hi>Barbarian</hi> in a Popish Successour. And that is, that his <hi>Zeal</hi> for his Church will supersede all the Dictates of <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> whatever, and nothing so <hi>horrid</hi> or <hi>villanous</hi> that a Papist, though never so <hi>great,</hi> either <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>Potentate</hi> will stand out at, when for the Advancement of <hi>popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Intended Proof of this Assertion is the very <hi>Master-stroke</hi> of the whole <hi>Character,</hi> Viz. <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batim,</hi> as follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Glory of a</hi> Papist! <hi>A pretty ayry</hi> Notion! <hi>How shall we ever expect that</hi> Glory <hi>shall steer the Actions of a <hi>popish</hi> Successour, when there is not that</hi> Thing <hi>so Abject, that he shall refuse to do; or that Shape or Hypocrisy so scandalous he shall not assume, when</hi> Rome, <hi>or</hi> Rome's Interest <hi>shall command; nay, when his own petulant Stubborness shall but sway him: As for Example; For one fit he shall come to the <hi>protestant Church,</hi> and be a Member of their Communion, notwithstanding at the same time his Face belyes his Heart, and his Soul is a</hi> Romanist: <hi>Nay, he shall vary his</hi> Disguises <hi>as often as an</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine <hi>his Colours, and change his Flag to conceal the</hi> Pyrate. <hi>As for Instance; another fit, for whole years together, he shall come neither to one Church nor 'tother, and participate of neither</hi> Communion; <hi>till ignobly he plays the</hi> Unprincely, <hi>nay,</hi> Unmanly <hi>Hypocrite so long, that he shelters himself under the Face of an</hi> Atheist <hi>to shrowd a</hi> Papist. <hi>A</hi> Vizor <hi>more fit for a</hi> Banditto <hi>than a</hi> Prince. <hi>And this methinks is so wretched and so despicable a</hi> Disguise, <hi>that it looks like being ashamed of his GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to the Eternal Shame of the <hi>Contagious Air</hi> of 79, and the most Flagitious <hi>Depravity</hi> of that <hi>Infamous Season;</hi> as nothing but the most <hi>unpardonable <hi>Malice</hi>
               </hi> encouraged and animated by the <hi>Licentiousness</hi> of those <hi>Libertine</hi> Days could have produced so exquisi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e a <hi>Mass of Ranc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur;</hi> so the Reader is to observe that it was <hi>exactly</hi> Calculated for that very Age 'twas written in, an Age when <hi>all Venome</hi> and <hi>no Reason</hi> was in Mode. For first, next to the old <hi>High Court</hi> of <hi>Justice,</hi> here's the most Impudent <hi>Tribunal</hi> set up, and a Prince most audaciously <hi>Arraign'd,</hi> and <hi>Sentenced</hi> for a <hi>Downright papist in his He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt</hi> at the same hour he's a Member of the <hi>protestant Communion,</hi> an Accusation beyond the possibility of <hi>Humane power</hi> or <hi>Knowledge</hi> to make <hi>proof</hi> of, and of which only God, that knows the Secrets of Hearts could be Judge. I remember I read of a Tyrant that hang'd a Fellow for a <hi>Sower Look,</hi> as a certain Conviction of a <hi>False Heart.</hi> But the <hi>Character</hi> goes a Bows Shoot beyo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> him, and pretends to <hi>Impeach <hi>Thoughts,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Adjudge <hi>Souls.</hi>
               </hi> And though neither the highest Scrutiny of <hi>Law,</hi> or Inquest of <hi>Humane Reason</hi> can inspect any further than into <hi>Visible Conformity</hi> and <hi>Ocular Demonstration:</hi> No matter for that, the popish <hi>Character</hi> can Out-fadom all Laws, and out-see all Reason, to find the vilest of <hi>Dirt</hi> to throw in the Face of <hi>Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The second <hi>Inglorious</hi> and <hi>Monstrous Blot</hi> in the Princely Scutcheon, as the <hi>Character</hi> designs him, is the <hi>Being a</hi> Papist, <hi>and yet not daring to go to the popish Communion.</hi> Which by the way, is all <hi>Supposition</hi> still, and no <hi>Proof.</hi> However, granting the Supposition, that he is one, does not the Express Law of the Land say, That <hi>no papist,</hi> at least, no <hi>Native</hi> popish Subject of <hi>England,</hi> though never so Princely <hi>Born,</hi> shall go to the <hi>popish Communion.</hi> Yet nevertheless, here's a Prince most arrogantly asperst and vilyfyed in the most barbarous Terms of <hi>Ʋnprincely, Ʋnmanly <hi>Hypocrite, Pyrate, Banditto,</hi> &amp;c.</hi> and all this for obeying the very <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land, and consequently, for performing the <hi>Duty</hi> of a <hi>Subject</hi> and a <hi>Christian:</hi> Nay, and in the Character way of Demonstrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he does an Act that looks like no less than being <hi>ashamed of his God,</hi> in submitting to the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> and thereby obeying the very <hi>Ordinance of God.</hi> If <hi>This</hi> be not a <hi>Master-stroke,</hi> as I told you, I know not what is.</p>
            <p>But truly to be plain with this single Paragraph in the <hi>popish Character</hi> (no disparagement to the rest of that <hi>Libel</hi>) no Impartial Reader but would swear the <hi>Devil himself</hi> could not have crowd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more <hi>Spight</hi> and <hi>Virulence,</hi> and less <hi>Sence</hi> into fewer Words; and yet to shew the misery of the time 'twas writ in; I was so far from an <hi>Original</hi> in that almost universal Spirit of <hi>Bitterness</hi> that then <hi>Reigned,</hi> that the Reader can't forget (as indeed the whole Nation has but too much Cause to <hi>remember</hi>) that if he at that time walked but <hi>Westminster</hi> or <hi>Oxfordwards,</hi> he might have seen <hi>five hundred</hi> Men together, much my <hi>Betters,</hi> that <hi>talk't,</hi> and what's worse, <hi>acted</hi> as <hi>had</hi> as I <hi>writ,</hi> and truly with as <hi>much,</hi> or <hi>more <hi>Gall,</hi>
               </hi> and full as little <hi>Reason.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus fairly stated our Case, and proved the Imbecility of our Fears, and the Invalidity of the Arguments used for the Danger of <hi>Popery</hi> in <hi>England</hi> this <hi>Rougher</hi> way, through <hi>Perjury, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barity,</hi> &amp;c. I shall come to the second Head of my Discourse, and enquire what Danger there is of its Introduction by <hi>Perswasion</hi> and <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> and all the gentler Meanes of a <hi>National Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:42213:10"/>
            <p>Now I confess, the pardoning of an Offender lyes in the Prerogative of the Crown, and the <hi>pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing,</hi> or <hi>not <hi>punishing</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>popish Priests,</hi> or any other Romish Emissaries, is wholly in the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>east of the Prince. And upon the Admission of a <hi>popish</hi> Soveraign to the Throne, 'tis presumed, that the <hi>Numbers</hi> of popish <hi>Visi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ants</hi> from Forreign Seminaries, will not only <hi>Encrease,</hi> but likewise act les<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Clandestinely</hi> than formerly under the Confidence of <hi>Connivance</hi> at least, from a Prince of their own Perswasion, and a <hi>Relaxation</hi> of all the <hi>poenal Statutes</hi> against <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Eminent Danger of Popery from this <hi>Inlet,</hi> raises <hi>no little Dust</hi> in the Character; and as if the whole Defence of our <hi>Protestant</hi> Religion was secured by no other <hi>Barriere</hi> than by keeping out <hi>popish</hi> Emissaries at <hi>Swords point,</hi> and <hi>hanging</hi> and <hi>Quartering</hi> of Priests and Jesuits, and the <hi>seve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>est</hi> Execution of the Statutes of <hi>Recusancy;</hi> which by the old Figure <hi>Petitio principii <hi>taken for granted,</hi>
               </hi> the <hi>Character</hi> most furiously lays about, to prove the Moral Impossibility of such a barbarous <hi>unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> popish <hi>Successour</hi> that shall hang and quarter those very Men that from the bottom of his heart he believes, <hi>are the undoubted Disciples of Heaven, and Pillars of Christianity,</hi> &amp;c. And if he doth not do all this, the <hi>Protestant</hi> Religion is upon it last Leggs, and our whole <hi>Church</hi> under a manifest prospect of being <hi>undermined</hi> and <hi>blown up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though by the by, here's another piece of <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>Baxterisme</hi> in the Case: For if <hi>popery</hi> shall make its Entrance, and sweep all before it <hi>this way,</hi> and by meer dint of <hi>Logick</hi> or <hi>Sophistry</hi> shall pervert the <hi>Church of England,</hi> what need was there of all the aforesaid <hi>Broyling, Roasting</hi> and <hi>Cut-throating,</hi> &amp;c. to do the Job.</p>
            <p>However, as this very Indulgence and Remission of the penal Laws is no more than what has been granted by the Clemency of the Crown even for Ages together, and all without one <hi>popular Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur,</hi> or the least <hi>Blot</hi> in the <hi>Royal Arms;</hi> the next Question is, what necessity of <hi>Shackling</hi> the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, and tying up a <hi>popish</hi> Successour to <hi>harder Meat</hi> than all his <hi>protestant</hi> Predecessours; or what more <hi>mortal</hi> Crime is that Indulgence in a <hi>Papist</hi> than in all the <hi>protestant</hi> Crown'd Heads be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him.</p>
            <p>Oh yes, infinitely more they'l tell you: for the Case is different, the <hi>popish</hi> Hopes will be more <hi>Lively,</hi> their Courage more <hi>daring,</hi> and Themselves by their <hi>popish</hi> Prince, more publickly and more solemnly <hi>embraced</hi> and <hi>countenanced;</hi> so that the Inconveniences attending us from these more <hi>propitious <hi>Royal Smiles</hi>
               </hi> to the profest <hi>Enemies</hi> and <hi>Supplanters</hi> of our Religion, will, God knows, have those Victorious Effects, which all the feebler <hi>popish</hi> Efforts <hi>before</hi> could never obtain.</p>
            <p>Well, imagine all this extraordinary <hi>Benigne Aspect</hi> towards <hi>popery,</hi> and for once, let us put the Case the <hi>Worst</hi> that can be. Let us suppose all the Indulgence or Incouragement to <hi>Popery</hi> from a <hi>popish</hi> Successour, that the <hi>highest stret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h</hi> of the Prerogative can give it. Nay, let us suppose a <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish <hi>Chappel</hi>
               </hi> in every <hi>Hamlet</hi> and <hi>Mass</hi> sung in every <hi>Parish</hi> in England, and to officiate in this Work, the whole Tribe of St. <hi>Omers, Doway,</hi> and all the rest of the English <hi>Seminaries</hi> abroad, <hi>trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted</hi> hither, to perform the <hi>Mighty Operation.</hi> What would all this do to bring in Popery? Nay, let the whole <hi>Colledge of Cardinals</hi> come over with them too, they would be almost as inoffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive to the <hi>protestant</hi> Religion as the <hi>Jewish Synagogue,</hi> and altogether as unable to make a <hi>National Conversion</hi> to <hi>Papisme,</hi> as the other to <hi>Iudaisme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For Instance, who are they, that these numerous <hi>popish</hi> Missionaries shall convert? The <hi>Ʋnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing</hi> part of the Nation, Men of <hi>Reason</hi> and <hi>Learning?</hi> Not at all. For let the <hi>popish <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi>
               </hi> increase as they please, the <hi>popish Arguments</hi> are but the same, whether defended by <hi>ten,</hi> or <hi>ten hundred</hi> Romanists. And therefore they that have their Principles of Faith, and the Grounds of their Religion <hi>Rooted</hi> and <hi>Confirmed</hi> by sound and well pondered <hi>Iudgment</hi> and <hi>Mature Conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> will no more be shaken by all the <hi>popish <hi>Numbers</hi>
               </hi> they can send over, than all the <hi>popish Volumes</hi> they have written. Besides, what greater <hi>Affront</hi> can be put upon our Religion it self, than to imagine it so weakly <hi>supported,</hi> as to be so much as capable of being thus overthrown.</p>
            <p>Who then shall they Convert? the <hi>Ignorant Multitude.</hi> No, <hi>Them</hi> less than the other. For as the others have <hi>Sense</hi> to defend themselves, <hi>These</hi> have that which is <hi>as strong,</hi> or <hi>stronger,</hi> and more Invincible, <hi>Viz. <hi>Deafeness, Prejudice</hi> and <hi>Resolution.</hi>
               </hi> For let any man seriously consider the <hi>Genius</hi> of the People of England in that point, and but fancy a <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>suit,</hi> a <hi>Priest</hi> or any other <hi>popish <hi>Emis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary,</hi>
               </hi> tampering with the poorest high-shoo'd, thick skull'd Clown, to <hi>possess</hi> him with a Faith in <hi>Transsubstantiation, Purgatory, Saint-praying,</hi> the Pope's <hi>Infallibility,</hi> or any other of the Terrible Romish Principles, and instead of making him a <hi>Proselite,</hi> upon the least Breath of that sort of Ayr, he should be so far from <hi>hearkening</hi> or <hi>listening</hi> so much as to the <hi>Means</hi> of a <hi>popish Conversion,</hi> so far from attending even to the <hi>Eloquence of Angels</hi> upon that Subject, that he should sooner look downwards for the <hi>Cloven-foot</hi> of the <hi>Seducer</hi> that utters it. For certainly those very <hi>people</hi> that have always been so <hi>Mazed</hi> and <hi>Night-mared</hi> with <hi>popery,</hi> that they have scarce seen any thing else but <hi>popish <hi>Specters</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Goblins</hi> even at the very <hi>Shadow</hi> of it, will fancy nothing less than <hi>Belzebubs</hi> and <hi>Lucifers</hi> at the <hi>real Appearance</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Reduction</hi> indeed of England to the Romish Religion is a thing as easily SAY'D, either in an <hi>Amsterdam Coffee-House,</hi> a <hi>popish Courant,</hi> or an <hi>Oxford House of Commons,</hi> as a Tale out of the <hi>Seven Champions,</hi> and truly with as much <hi>Credibility:</hi> But alas! when it comes to the <hi>DO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ING</hi> once, the Papists will find that the <hi>whole Body</hi> of the people of <hi>England,</hi> even to a <hi>Nemine Contradicente</hi> (at least, not one in a hundred excepted) if without any other Defence of their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, are still those <hi>Opinators</hi> in Religion, that maugre the general <hi>Ignorance</hi> of the Multitude, or the great <hi>Learning</hi> or <hi>Rhetorick</hi> of the <hi>Jesuites,</hi> they'd be no sooner perswaded to quit their plain <hi>English Bibles,</hi> nay, not so much as poor <hi>Sternhold</hi> and <hi>Hopkins,</hi> to listen to an <hi>unintelligible Latine
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42213:11"/>
                  <hi>Mass,</hi>
               </hi> or joyn in an <hi>Ora pro nobi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> sancte Paule, sancte Petre, sancte Loyola,</hi> and the rest of the Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity of <hi>Major,</hi> or <hi>Minor Saints,</hi> then they'd kneel to the <hi>Talmude</hi> or the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e no more perswaded into the possibility of a <hi>Wafer's Transsubstantiation</hi> into a <hi>Deity,</hi> than of a <hi>Cartwheel</hi> into a <hi>Star:</hi> and without these and the rest of the Romish <hi>Fundamentals,</hi> where's the <hi>Restoration</hi> of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish Faith,</hi> or the Progress of a Popish <hi>Propagation</hi> in England.</p>
            <p>But to confirm this certain <hi>Truth</hi> from a more substantial <hi>Authority</hi> than my own. 'Tis the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Opinion of the Reverend Dr. <hi>Burnet <hi>himfelf,</hi>
               </hi> a <hi>person,</hi> let me tell you, under no small <hi>Pains-tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> for the <hi>protestant Religion,</hi> and as a Churchman, under no <hi>common</hi> Consternation from <hi>popish <hi>Dangers,</hi>
               </hi> and therefore not at all likely to <hi>lull</hi> us into a <hi>false Security</hi> of our Religion. The Instance of which Opinion I find in the 9th. <hi>page</hi> of his Preface to the <hi>Rights of Princes,</hi> as follows;</p>
            <p>
               <q>Tis the Maxime of the Popes, not to reform Abuses in their Church, for if some <hi>Corruptions</hi> were once acknowledged, and amended, that would give credit to the Complaints which the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks</hi> made, and be a publick <hi>Confession,</hi> that the Church had <hi>Erred,</hi> and would set on foot a hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of making <hi>Changes,</hi> which could not be easily <hi>limited</hi> or <hi>managed.</hi> These Politicks prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Rome,</hi> so that instead of removing Abuses, all were justifyed and maintained, and yet humane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly speaking, it is not to be imagin'd but that if some more palpable Abuses in the Worship, such as the scandalous Ufe of <hi>Images,</hi> the denying the <hi>Chalice,</hi> and saying the Office in an <hi>Ʋnknown Tongue,</hi> had been <hi>corrected,</hi> the Reformation could not have made so great a Progress as it did. Wise Men are unwilling to make great Changes, and the <hi>Rabble</hi> are wrought on, not so much by <hi>Speculations,</hi> and subtle and learned Arguments, as by <hi>prejudices</hi> to some <hi>publick Abuses,</hi> of which they are ALL sensible; and while these are continued, 'twill be easie to heighten their Dislike of them, and to lead them almost into <hi>any</hi> Opinions, to which the hatred they bear to the Abuses may any way dispose them. And the <hi>defending</hi> or <hi>maintaining</hi> of Abuses, which <hi>cannot</hi> be defended, endangers the <hi>whole Cause</hi> in the Opinion of those who judge of Parties in <hi>Gross,</hi> and not by the <hi>Retail</hi> of <hi>particular Arguments.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>So that to summe up the Matter: Here's the whole Cause of <hi>Rome</hi> in a manner wholly lost by the <hi>Gross Abuses</hi> in that <hi>Communion.</hi> And what between the <hi>Invincible Obstinacy</hi> of the Romanists on one side, never to recede from those <hi>Abuses;</hi> and the <hi>Rabble's unanimous Disgust</hi> against them on the other, as being apparent even to <hi>all <hi>Capacities;</hi>
               </hi> here's the greatest <hi>progress</hi> of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> slow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from almost no other <hi>Channel;</hi> and by consequence, if the <hi>Original Prejudice</hi> against those Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, could open so brord a Gate to the <hi>protestant Religion,</hi> the present more <hi>irreconciliable Antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> against <hi>Rome,</hi> heightned by so many <hi>successive</hi> popular <hi>Inflammations,</hi> will make the <hi>Resumption</hi> of that <hi>popish Vomit</hi> so more universally <hi>nauseous,</hi> that it will undoubtedly much more contribute to the <hi>Confirmation</hi> of the Protestant Religion, than ever it did to the <hi>Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>For let but any reasonable Man consider, that during so many Ages of Impunity to the Papists from the long Mercy of the late Kings of <hi>England,</hi> when <hi>Recusancy</hi> went <hi>unmolested</hi> and <hi>unregard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and neither <hi>Papist,</hi> nor <hi>popish priest,</hi> either <hi>punish't,</hi> or <hi>examined:</hi> excepting some few Families, that bred up their Children in their own Perswasion, what Conversions have the <hi>popish party,</hi> and all the <hi>Romish Missionaries</hi> made in <hi>England</hi> for half a hundred years last past? So far from any <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease,</hi> that on the contrary, they have from <hi>Generation</hi> to <hi>Generation <hi>apparently</hi>
               </hi> dwindled <hi>less and less</hi> till they are now scarce a <hi>handful</hi> in consideration of all England. And if <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Jesui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisme,</hi> with all their <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>Insinuations</hi> under such <hi>Royal Indulgence</hi> have made such <hi>feeble progress</hi> in the Conversion of <hi>England,</hi> that they have dayly <hi>lost</hi> ground, not <hi>gain'd</hi> it; shall the yet <hi>larger Indulgence</hi> of a <hi>popish</hi> Successour, with the permission of their <hi>popish Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ests barefaced,</hi> the multiplying of their <hi>Numbers,</hi> or the Influence of <hi>Regis ad Exemplum</hi> do the Work? The quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. For suppose the <hi>popish Priests</hi> a hundred times more numerous, and a hundred times bolder than now, yet as the <hi>popish Seducers</hi> are increased, so likewise under the dismal Apprehension of a visible <hi>popish Successour</hi> the popular <hi>Aversion</hi> will so much more increase too, and thereby become the more <hi>impregnable,</hi> whil'st the <hi>Ʋniversality</hi> of their <hi>Fear</hi> and <hi>Hate</hi> will make them so much the more <hi>Fortifyed</hi> against the <hi>utmost Assault.</hi> Besides, if the <hi>Jesuites</hi> have made so little Advances of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery formerly in <hi>England,</hi> that (granting it true that's said of them) they have been put to the poor shifts of herding with <hi>Fanaticks,</hi> and <hi>disguising</hi> into <hi>Conventicle Preachers;</hi> what Encouragements (Oh wonderful!) are they like to meet, when they throw off the <hi>Vizor,</hi> and walk by <hi>day,</hi> in the <hi>open</hi> Propagation of a Religion so <hi>universally loathed,</hi> that it wants the subtlest of <hi>Artifices</hi> and <hi>Disguises</hi> to obtrude even the least Tenet of it into the World; at least, <hi>our Part</hi> of the World.</p>
            <p>But surely nothing in nature can be a more ridiculous Supposition at this time of day, as that the <hi>Example</hi> or <hi>Favour</hi> of a King in Case of Popery, shall contribute towards the People's Embracing it, when undeniable Experience tells us, that the very <hi>Aspersion</hi> of but <hi>popishly affected,</hi> has lost our Kings so many Hearts, nay One of Them (with horrour be it spoken) his very <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Head.</hi> By consequence, how many more Hearts shall Popery in earnest loose a <hi>true</hi> Popish King? and what little hope of gaining <hi>Proselites</hi> or <hi>Friends</hi> to a <hi>real Romanist,</hi> when the meer <hi>Imagination</hi> has rays'd such contagious <hi>Desertions</hi> and <hi>Enmity</hi> even to the best of <hi>Protestant</hi> Crown'd Heads. And therefore how wretched a piece of <hi>Sophistry</hi> must that be that Imposes on the unreasoning World so impudent a piece of Falshood, <hi>Viz.</hi> That Popery and a Popish Successour will find such
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42213:11"/>
               <hi>favourable Stars</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> when on the contrary, the bare <hi>Notion</hi> of Popery and <hi>popish Councils</hi> have been attended with such <hi>Fatality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, to answer a little nearer yet to the Danger of Popery's coming in through the <hi>Remiss<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> and <hi>Neglect</hi> of executing the Laws against it, and the Indulgence and Incouragement of the Prince to promote it, I have only this Request to make to thee, thou poor <hi>frighted, half-witted Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> that fearest all this Danger (for nothing of sense can fear it) to lay thy hand upon thy Heart, and answer me this Question. Amongst those Proselites that the aforesaid <hi>Toleration</hi> and <hi>Encouragement</hi> of the <hi>popish</hi> Successour, and the Witchcraft of the Pope and Jesuits are like to make, Art thou thy self one of the number that is in that danger of <hi>turning Papist?</hi> Now to answer for thee in thy own Dialect, <hi>No!</hi> God forbid, thoul't say, what, shall I turn to a <hi>Religion</hi> that has nothing in it but <hi>Superstition</hi> and <hi>Idolatry!</hi> a Religion worse than <hi>Paganisme</hi> and <hi>Judaisme,</hi> a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion that consecrates <hi>Daggers,</hi> and canonizes <hi>Murderers,</hi> that makes nothing but <hi>stabbing of Kings,</hi> &amp; <hi>Massacring whole Nations</hi> the only meritorious Act of <hi>Christianity;</hi> and do you think that either the <hi>Insinuations</hi> of Priests, or the <hi>Flattery</hi> of Kings themselves, or any Earthly Reward shall make me turn such an <hi>Apostate</hi> from <hi>Truth,</hi> as to <hi>damne</hi> my Soul and <hi>renounce</hi> my <hi>God:</hi> no, I have more As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance in his good <hi>Grace</hi> than to imagine he'll abandon me to <hi>such a Thought:</hi> no, no, my Fear is not for my self. But alas! though <hi>I</hi> shall never turn <hi>Papist,</hi> too many <hi>others</hi> will; and when these <hi>Iesuites, Priests,</hi> and <hi>Villains</hi> have perverted the greatest part of the Nation to their <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and thereby come to be able to set up the <hi>Romish <hi>Religion,</hi>
               </hi> with all the old <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Faggots</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to it, then shall such <hi>honest Protestants</hi> as my self be burnt at a Stake, for not <hi>turning Devil</hi> too for <hi>Company</hi> with them. And what a miserable Condition will the poor <hi>Protestants</hi> be in in that dreadful day.</p>
            <p>Why thou fool, canst thou thus make this <hi>confident</hi> &amp; <hi>Resolute</hi> Answer for thy self, and art thou so secure for thy <hi>own part,</hi> and only <hi>suspectest</hi> the <hi>Danger</hi> of a <hi>popish Conversion</hi> from the <hi>weakness</hi> of thy <hi>Neighbour.</hi> If that be all, trouble not thy self; nor distract thy little Brains for nothing, but for thy Comfort, examine thy <hi>Neighbours Hearts</hi> as thou hast done thy <hi>own,</hi> and of ever <hi>hundred</hi> amongst them thou wilt find almost <hi>every where</hi> at least <hi>ninety nine</hi> of them that have the same dreadful Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Popery</hi> as thou hast, and as utter an <hi>Abomination</hi> of it as thy self, with the same <hi>Confident As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance</hi> of themselves too; nay, and that have only <hi>thy</hi> very <hi>Reasons</hi> of fearing it. How ridiculous therefore must thy Fear be, when if <hi>thou</hi> art secure, they are so too. And if so, where then are the <hi>Infinite Numbers</hi> of those <hi>Weak Brothers</hi> that the Pope's Emissaries shall subdue, and that <hi>Majori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> of a <hi>perverted Nation</hi> that shall Establish and set up this <hi>Nebuchadnezar's <hi>Image,</hi>
               </hi> and doom thee to <hi>Fiery Furnaces</hi> for not kneeling with them to Worship it.</p>
            <p>If the Dint of <hi>Perswasion</hi> and <hi>Indulgence</hi> then be all the Introduction of <hi>Popery,</hi> and this the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Flight of a <hi>popish Successour <hi>(as indeed it is)</hi>
               </hi> all our <hi>Dangers</hi> are quite <hi>vanisht,</hi> and the more the Nation <hi>abhors</hi> Popery, the less Cause it has to <hi>fear</hi> it, whil'st the Universality of the <hi>Detestation</hi> is the certain <hi>Security</hi> of keeping it out; and none but <hi>Fools</hi> or <hi>Madmen</hi> can be frighted by the <hi>Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hensions</hi> of it that way. For the <hi>Blacker</hi> the <hi>Feind,</hi> the less <hi>power</hi> he has over us, and they that are <hi>above Temptation</hi> need not fear the <hi>Devil himself.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But beyond all these various Pretences for Popery's coming in, there's one more general Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment almost in all <hi>Mouths,</hi> which we find dayly urged, and that bears no little sway in Vulgar Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why is it impossible that <hi>Popery</hi> should come in again, and that too, by <hi>Law Establish't?</hi> Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience plainly tells us, that <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eighth</hi> lay'd the <hi>Foundation</hi> of the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> nay, and by a <hi>popish Parliament</hi> too. For by a <hi>Romish Parliament</hi> was the <hi>Pope's Supremacy</hi> destroyed, by a <hi>Romish</hi> Parliament the <hi>Monastery's</hi> and <hi>Abbey-Lands</hi> confiscated, and that very Monarch, after the Continuation of Popery by a Reign of more than half a <hi>thousand</hi> years, in the very <hi>Infancy</hi> too of the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> when possibly the Protestants then in <hi>England,</hi> were a less handful than are the Papists in <hi>England <hi>now.</hi>
               </hi> This very King I say, with so small a Party of <hi>Protestants,</hi> could nevertheless lay the very <hi>Corner Stone,</hi> that the <hi>whole Reformation</hi> was afterwards <hi>built</hi> upon, and that too by <hi>Act of Parliament.</hi> And why on the other side, shall it be so impossible for a <hi>popish Prince,</hi> with <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight's <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Conduct</hi> withal, after not a <hi>hundred</hi> and <hi>fifty</hi> years Reign of the <hi>protestant Religion,</hi> to be likewise <hi>able</hi> to do the same Favour for <hi>Popery;</hi> and <hi>lay</hi> the very <hi>Basis</hi> of it even by <hi>Parliaments</hi> and <hi>Law.</hi> And a <hi>protestant Parliament <hi>now,</hi>
               </hi> as a <hi>popish one <hi>then</hi>
               </hi> be so <hi>managed</hi> or <hi>Influenced,</hi> as to give a main Lift to the <hi>Work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Besides, why should the <hi>Change</hi> of the Religion be so <hi>wondrous</hi> or <hi>difficult</hi> a <hi>Deed</hi> under <hi>a popish Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch <hi>now,</hi>
               </hi> when upon every <hi>Change</hi> of the Prince's <hi>Faith</hi> since the Conquest, the <hi>Establish't Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> of the Kingdom has been changed <hi>with it.</hi> For Instance, after <hi>Henry's</hi> good Stroke towards it, Did not an Infant Prince, <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, in poor <hi>seven years time</hi> Establish the <hi>protestant Religion</hi> by Law? And did not <hi>Mary</hi> his <hi>popish Successour subvert</hi> it again by <hi>Law,</hi> and by Law restore the very <hi>Pope's Supremacy?</hi> And lastly, Did not the <hi>protestant</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> after her, trample both <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Popery</hi> under Feet, and confirm that very Protestant Religion that Reigns at this Day. And why shall a Popish Successour now, with as much <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>Industry</hi> as his <hi>Predecessours</hi> miscarry in that very work in which not one of them fail'd before him.</p>
            <p>There is nothing that possibly passes for a more <hi>Authentick Confirmation</hi> of all our <hi>popish Dangers</hi> than this <hi>One Assertion</hi> so universally received for <hi>Currant Sterling,</hi> by being only taken <hi>at a Lump upon Trust unweighed</hi> and <hi>unexamined.</hi> But when considerately and throughly inspected, all rational
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42213:12"/> Men must blush to be deceived by so <hi>light</hi> and so <hi>drossy</hi> a Popular <hi>Tradition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For to begin with <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eighth.</hi> In the first place, here neither <hi>is,</hi> nor <hi>can</hi> be the least <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive</hi> for the present Protestant <hi>People,</hi> or their <hi>Representatives</hi> to make the <hi>least Change whatever</hi> in the present <hi>Church of England,</hi> in any kind <hi>answerable</hi> to the several <hi>Inducements</hi> that wrought those <hi>Changes</hi> in <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eighth's</hi> Time.</p>
            <p>For first, as no small <hi>Encouragement</hi> for the <hi>Reformation,</hi> the People had then contracted a <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> and <hi>just Odium</hi> of the <hi>whole Clergy,</hi> strangely occasion'd by the Murder of <hi>Hunn,</hi> a Merchant of <hi>London</hi> in Prison. This <hi>Hunn</hi> being sued in the <hi>Legates Court</hi> for Non-payment of a <hi>Mortuary</hi> to his Parish-Priest; in return, sued the Parish Priest in the <hi>Temporal Court</hi> for a <hi>Premunire,</hi> for bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King's <hi>Subjects</hi> before a <hi>Forreign</hi> and <hi>Illegal Court.</hi> This incensed the <hi>Clergy</hi> so much, that they threw him into Prison for <hi>Heresy;</hi> where having several Articles exhibited against him, upon Confession of part of them, and begging Mercy, he was only enjoyn'd <hi>Penance.</hi> But not being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd upon to <hi>let fall his Suite</hi> in the <hi>Temporal Court,</hi> the Bishop's <hi>Chancellour,</hi> a <hi>Doctor,</hi> and other of his <hi>Officers</hi> inhumanely <hi>Murdered</hi> him in Prison, by breaking his <hi>Neck</hi> with an <hi>Iron Chain,</hi> and other Wounds given him upon the Belly; and then hanged him up in his <hi>own Girdle</hi> to possess the World that he hanged himself. And what was yet worse, upon a full <hi>Detection</hi> of the <hi>Truth</hi> of this Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the Bishops of <hi>Durham</hi> and <hi>Lincoln,</hi> to <hi>palliate</hi> the Guilt, proceeded to charge him with new <hi>Heresies</hi> after Death, and having sound a <hi>Wickliffs Bible</hi> in his House, they condemn'd him as an <hi>Heretick,</hi> and burnt his Body. All which Proceedings being now looked upon as the <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>whole Clergy,</hi> they lost the Affections of the People to that degree that they could <hi>never recover</hi> them; and nothing more <hi>disposed</hi> the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ople to the embracing of the <hi>New Preachers</hi> than the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentment of so infamous a <hi>Murder, <hi>committed</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>patronized</hi> by the whole <hi>Clergy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>[Hist. of Ref. <hi>pag.</hi> 14, and 15.]</p>
            <p>And then for the Changes made in Parliament. The Suppression of <hi>Monasteries,</hi> one of their <hi>Acts,</hi> was no more than what was <hi>design'd,</hi> and <hi>begun</hi> in some Measure by Cardinal <hi>Woolsey,</hi> and the <hi>Pope himself,</hi> and that long before the Breach betwixt the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Him,</hi> who granted a <hi>Bull</hi> to destroy several of them, to convert into <hi>Bishopricks; [Ref. pag.</hi> 22.] the scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and lewd Lives of too many of the <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Fryars</hi> being obnoxious even to <hi>Rome</hi> it self. Though 'tis true, the King and Parliament proceeded to a <hi>total Suppression</hi> of them afterwards for the same Intent of erecting <hi>new Episcopal Sees;</hi> though indeed the <hi>vast profits</hi> arising from their <hi>Sale,</hi> through the <hi>Extravagant Profuseness</hi> of <hi>Henry the Eighth,</hi> were not wholly converted to that Use; notwithstanding, <hi>part</hi> of his Promise was performed, <hi>Viz.</hi> In his constituting six new <hi>Bishopricks,</hi> and making Allowance for fourteen <hi>Deanaryes</hi> and <hi>Prebendariships</hi> to fourteen Bishop's <hi>Sees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to gain the Parliament to the <hi>King's</hi> Party in the <hi>Destruction</hi> of <hi>Monasteries,</hi> there was that which <hi>Governs</hi> the World, <hi>Interest</hi> in the Case; which was no small <hi>Wheel</hi> in the <hi>Machine.</hi> For the King selling of the <hi>Lands</hi> at <hi>easie Rates</hi> to the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry;</hi> by this Policy the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Members,</hi> as <hi>Purchasers,</hi> by the Temptation of such <hi>good penny-worths,</hi> were ingaged to as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist the King in the <hi>Maintenance</hi> of the Changes made. [<hi>Ref. pag.</hi> 223.]</p>
            <p>And for another part of <hi>Henry</hi> the 8th's Reformation, <hi>Viz.</hi> The <hi>censuring</hi> and <hi>condemning</hi> of <hi>Bulls, Indulgenses, Shrines, Pilgrimages,</hi> and <hi>Relicks,</hi> with the <hi>pulling down</hi> of <hi>Images;</hi> the <hi>scandalous Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures</hi> of several of them by the <hi>fraud</hi> of the Priests, being publickly discovered, [<hi>Ref. p.</hi> 242.] created no little aversion in the People. But besides all that, here could never be a more <hi>pleasing Change</hi> to them than so <hi>beneficial</hi> a part of <hi>Reformation,</hi> Viz. The freeing them from all those <hi>Ecclesiastick Romish Dreins,</hi> that had so long swallow'd almost <hi>half</hi> the Wealth of the Kingdom, in which too many of them had been too great <hi>Sufferers,</hi> not only through their <hi>own,</hi> but also the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded <hi>Superstition</hi> of their Bigotted <hi>Ancestors,</hi> and by which no less than whole Families had been <hi>Impoverish't</hi> and <hi>Undone,</hi> through the <hi>pious Frauds</hi> and <hi>continual Suckings</hi> of those <hi>Church Horse-leeches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And lastly, for the Exclusion of the Papal <hi>Supremacy,</hi> the above cited penalty of Premunire incurred both by the whole <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Layty</hi> of <hi>England</hi> in submitting to the Pope's <hi>Legantine</hi> Power, contrary to <hi>Law,</hi> as against the Act of <hi>Provisoes,</hi> contributed no little matter both to the <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> Submission to the King in the point of that <hi>Supremacy.</hi> Besides, to facilitate the Assumption of it, it was plainly proved by that <hi>Provisoe Act,</hi> and other <hi>Substantial Records,</hi> that the Pope's <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments</hi> in <hi>England</hi> were but <hi>Vsurpation,</hi> and the <hi>Supremacy</hi> in reality <hi>ab origine &amp; de jure</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent in the <hi>Crown;</hi> and therefore the Resumption of it by the King, no more than a <hi>Challenge</hi> and <hi>Reprizal</hi> of his own <hi>Invaded Prerogative.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As these were <hi>all the Changes</hi> made by <hi>Henry the Eighth,</hi> the Popish Religion being so far from abolish't by him, that he rather strook at the <hi>Court</hi> than <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> witness the <hi>Act of the six Articles</hi> made by him, defending the <hi>greatest</hi> and <hi>principlest Tenets</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> by no less than <hi>Capital</hi> Punishments, and a Parlimentary <hi>Reinforcement</hi> of the old Statute <hi>de Hereticis comburendis; [Ref. pag.</hi> 147.] the <hi>Heretick Burning</hi> continuing through his whole Reign. As these I say, were all the <hi>Changes</hi> made by <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eighth,</hi> instrumental to the present Reformation, and that too, not without <hi>Obstructions,</hi> witness several <hi>Rebellions</hi> occasioned by this Change; the one of 20000 Strong in <hi>Lincolnshire;</hi> another more formidable one in <hi>Yorkshire,</hi> called by the Rebels, <hi>The Pilgrimage of Grace,</hi> attended with a general Insurrection in all the <hi>North.</hi> However, as I said before, here is no <hi>Motive</hi> or <hi>Inducement</hi> now for the like Parliamentary Compliance with a Popish Successour, to make any, the <hi>least Change</hi> Instrumental to the <hi>Romish Restoration.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:42213:12"/>
            <p>For first, supposing (how notoriously false soever) an equal <hi>Mutability</hi> or <hi>Disposition</hi> in the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple now, to return to <hi>Rome,</hi> as then to <hi>depart</hi> from it. Here's no stigmatizing <hi>Brand</hi> of <hi>Murder,</hi> or any other publick <hi>Perpetration</hi> or <hi>Avowing</hi> of any <hi>Villany</hi> whatever to taint the <hi>whole Protestant Clergy,</hi> and thereby <hi>withdraw</hi> the People's Hearts from them.</p>
            <p>Here's no <hi>Holy-Cheats</hi> and <hi>Superstitious <hi>priest-Impostures</hi>
               </hi> practised to <hi>drein</hi> the People's Purses to <hi>gratifie</hi> a <hi>scandalous, voracious Clergy.</hi> Or any detected <hi>Abuses</hi> and <hi>Corruptions</hi> to <hi>disgust</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asperate</hi> the People against them.</p>
            <p>Here's no least <hi>Dormient Statute</hi> or <hi>Title</hi> whatever, for a Popish Successour to <hi>lay hold of,</hi> in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Papacy's <hi>Return</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> as there was for its <hi>Expulsion.</hi> The Fence of our present Protestant <hi>Constitution</hi> being so strong against it, and all Pretensions of <hi>Rome</hi> so utterly <hi>extinct</hi> and <hi>abolish't.</hi> Neither is here any <hi>Premunire</hi> incurred by the <hi>whole Clergy</hi> and <hi>Nation</hi> to <hi>affright,</hi> or <hi>da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterdize</hi> them into any fordid <hi>Condescencion</hi> or <hi>Grants</hi> in Diskindness to our <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And lastly, here's no <hi>Fleecing</hi> of an <hi>Overgrown, Overrich Church</hi> in the Case. (The present <hi>Church Revenues</hi> under so many <hi>Impropriations,</hi> being no more than will but just support its <hi>Dignity</hi> and <hi>Pastors</hi> but with <hi>Subsistence</hi> and <hi>Decency.</hi>) No Ecclesiastick <hi>Booty</hi> nor <hi>Prize</hi> to bribe or allure an <hi>Avaricious</hi> Parliament to <hi>weaken</hi> or <hi>impoverish</hi> their Church for the temptation of sharing the <hi>Spoyl.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But above all other Obstacles against <hi>Rome,</hi> her's an <hi>Absolute Impossibility</hi> of a <hi>Temporizing <hi>Clergy</hi>
               </hi> to favour Popery. For supposing even the most barbarous Insinuation of their <hi>Fanatical Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, True;</hi> and that <hi>Mammon, Interest, Sycophantry,</hi> (how <hi>rascally</hi> soever that <hi>Infamous Suggesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>) were above <hi>Religion</hi> with them. Yet nevertheless the <hi>utmost Influence</hi> of a Romish Prince could never warp them to any such <hi>Execrable Apostacy;</hi> by reason the <hi>Indispensable <hi>Coelibacy</hi>
               </hi> of the Romish <hi>Clergy</hi> would totally <hi>exclude</hi> the present Members of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> as being <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed Men,</hi> from any <hi>Share</hi> or <hi>Hopes</hi> under a <hi>Romish</hi> Government, whil'st instead of <hi>Preferment</hi> or <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest,</hi> nothing but <hi>Degradation</hi> and <hi>Beggery</hi> could attend them.</p>
            <p>And for an <hi>unanswerable Disparity</hi> between <hi>Henry the Eighth's</hi> Influence towards the present <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion,</hi> and a Popish Successour's towards <hi>Popery.</hi> The <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> with an invit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Face</hi> was in a State of <hi>Innocence,</hi> untainted by any of its Corrupted Professours with any thing like <hi>Parisian Massacres, Irish Rebellions,</hi> or <hi>Gun-powder Treasons;</hi> enough of themselves alone to open that <hi>uncloseable Chasme,</hi> that <hi>never to be cemented Breach</hi> between <hi>Englishmen</hi> and <hi>Popery;</hi> that Popery could not now gain <hi>three</hi> Proselites to a <hi>hundred</hi> gain'd in <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eighth's</hi> Time to the Protest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here I cannot but take notice of one <hi>Gross Mistake,</hi> that's commonly receiv'd for <hi>Truth,</hi> Viz. <hi>That</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighth <hi>hectored</hi> his</hi> Parliaments <hi>to what he listed.</hi> Which is oftentimes made use of as an Argument, that a Popish Successour, with the <hi>same Courage</hi> may do the like with <hi>his;</hi> when on the contrary, they acted only by their <hi>own Inclinations;</hi> and when any thing was proposed by the King that went against the <hi>Grain;</hi> not all his <hi>Menaces</hi> could force them to a Submission. For Example, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en a Bill had past the <hi>House of Lords</hi> for regulating a common Practice then in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> of defrauding the King and several of the Lords of their <hi>Advantages</hi> made by <hi>Wards, Marriages,</hi> and <hi>Primier Seisin,</hi> by Men's making such Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tlements of their Estates by their last <hi>Wills,</hi> and other Deeds to that purpose. Yet notwithstanding the <hi>utmost pressure</hi> both of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> for redressing that Abuse, the <hi>Commons rejected the Bill</hi> [Ref. <hi>pag.</hi> 116.] And as to the <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> some part of it was of their own seeking. For Example, in his 22d. Year, the <hi>Commons</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to the King of the grievous and intolerable Severity of the <hi>Ecclesiasticks,</hi> for calling Men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them <hi>ex Officio,</hi> and laying Articles to their Charge without any <hi>Accuser,</hi> and then admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting no <hi>Purgation,</hi> but causing the Party accused either to <hi>abjure</hi> or <hi>burn.</hi> Reform. Pag. 116. And indeed in all the Reformation they rather drew with him, than were driven by him.</p>
            <p>And to shew the <hi>vast Difference</hi> betwixt the Operation of the Prince, either by <hi>Edward</hi> or <hi>Mary</hi> towards the <hi>Change</hi> of the Religion, and the working of a <hi>Change</hi> now.</p>
            <p>In the first place, besides the dayly <hi>Converts</hi> made to the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> in <hi>Edward's</hi> Reign, which added Strength and Vigour to the Reformation wrought by that Prince, as the State of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> then stood the <hi>Popish</hi> and <hi>Protestant</hi> Party were grown in a manner to be an <hi>Equal Division</hi> of the Nation, and 'tis not to be wondred, that where the <hi>Weight's even,</hi> the Soveraign Power added to the <hi>Ballanee,</hi> could <hi>turn the Scale;</hi> as both in his and his Sister's Reign. <hi>Either</hi> Party having an <hi>Easie Game</hi> to play, whilst the Respective <hi>Monarch</hi> might with small <hi>Difficulty</hi> turn up his <hi>own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion <hi>Trump,</hi>
               </hi> when he had <hi>half</hi> the Cards in his hands.</p>
            <p>Besides, the <hi>Law</hi> had then so weakly <hi>provided</hi> for the <hi>true Settlement</hi> of either <hi>Religion,</hi> that the greatest part of the <hi>Ecclesiastick Changes <hi>then,</hi>
               </hi> lay almost wholly in the pleasure of the Prince: For after the <hi>Parliament</hi> had <hi>fully invested</hi> Henry the <hi>Eighth</hi> with the <hi>Supremacy,</hi> they impowered him as <hi>Head of the Church,</hi> to dispose of all <hi>Episcopal Sees</hi> by <hi>Letters Patents <hi>during pleasure.</hi> (Abrid. Ref. Book</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 4.) and the Bishops by the <hi>same Authority</hi> had the like <hi>Jurisdiction</hi> over the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Clergy.</p>
            <p>This <hi>unbounded Latitude</hi> of the <hi>Supremacy</hi> continuing through both the <hi>next Reigns,</hi> a great part of the Changes was owing wholly to this <hi>Prerogative;</hi> whil'st King <hi>Edward</hi> made choice of a <hi>Clergy</hi> of his <hi>own Perswasion;</hi> and in like manner Queen <hi>Mary placed</hi> or <hi>displaced</hi> her Bishops, and remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all the <hi>Inferiour</hi> Clergy <hi>ad Libitum,</hi> turning out whom she pleas'd, without any <hi>Form of Process,</hi> or special <hi>Matter</hi> objected against them. All which (<hi>Abridg. P.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 249.) was done by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42213:13"/> of the Queens being <hi>Head of the Church;</hi> which though she condemned as a <hi>sinful</hi> and <hi>sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgious Power,</hi> yet she now employ'd it against those <hi>Bishops,</hi> whose <hi>Sees</hi> were <hi>quickly filled</hi> with <hi>Men</hi> for her <hi>Purpose.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that nothing could make a <hi>greater Turn</hi> of <hi>Church Affairs</hi> in the Kingdom in <hi>those <hi>Days,</hi>
               </hi> when under such a <hi>Total Alteration</hi> of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> and all ready <hi>at hand</hi> to step into their <hi>Seats,</hi> the whole <hi>Interest</hi> of the <hi>Adverse Religion</hi> through the forementioned <hi>Equality</hi> of Parties could not but be <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly shaken,</hi> and the Prevalence in <hi>Parliament</hi> be highly mov'd by no <hi>other Spring.</hi> Besides, the Act <hi>De Hereticis comburendis</hi> was then <hi>unabolish't,</hi> and as the Determination of <hi>Heresy</hi> lay in the <hi>Breast</hi> of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> here was an easie leap into <hi>all the foregoing Severities</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> even by the Law <hi>it self.</hi> Insomuch that either of the Religions could not <hi>properly</hi> be call'd by <hi>Law Establish't,</hi> whil'st our <hi>Pastors</hi> and our <hi>Fold</hi> were in a manner at the <hi>Will of the Soveraign,</hi> and there wanted but little more than the <hi>Royal Breath</hi> to drive us to the <hi>Right</hi> or the <hi>Left,</hi> the <hi>Sheep</hi> or the <hi>Goats.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But all this is so prodigiously remote from the <hi>present State of England,</hi> and the <hi>Religion now Esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blish't,</hi> that <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Darkness</hi> can be scarce more <hi>dissonant.</hi> For besides the infinite <hi>Disproporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the Popish Numbers in Queen <hi>Mary's Reign,</hi> to <hi>Ours,</hi> enough of it self to silence all <hi>Dispute;</hi> a <hi>popish Succesours</hi> Removal of the <hi>present Protestant Clergy,</hi> and the Introduction of <hi>Priests</hi> and <hi>Jesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its</hi> in their <hi>Room,</hi> as Head of the <hi>Church,</hi> is no more in his <hi>Prerogative</hi> than the Government of <hi>Transylvania:</hi> The <hi>present Bishops</hi> and <hi>Clergy</hi> holding <hi>for Life,</hi> and only to be <hi>displaced</hi> or <hi>silenced</hi> upon <hi>Crimes</hi> or <hi>Insufficiencies</hi> adjudged or condemned by the <hi>Protestant Censure</hi> and <hi>Sentence.</hi> And all the <hi>popish Clergy</hi> so <hi>incapable</hi> of their Places, that they are <hi>Aliens</hi> to the <hi>Nation,</hi> under an <hi>attaint</hi> of <hi>Treason</hi> upon the very Assumption of their <hi>Sacerdotal Orders;</hi> and so shut out from our <hi>Church-Ministry</hi> by <hi>Parliamentary Oaths, Tests,</hi> and <hi>Abjurations,</hi> that nothing but the most Diabolical Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal <hi>Dispensation,</hi> and a <hi>Conscience</hi> even <hi>Brimstone Proof</hi> could introduce them, were there really <hi>Room</hi> for their Admission.</p>
            <p>But alas! considering in what <hi>Equilibrium</hi> Religion then hung, whatever <hi>Concurrence</hi> the Prince could then obtain from his People in Parliament in favour of his <hi>own Perswasion:</hi> The <hi>Genius</hi> of <hi>England</hi> is now quite <hi>another thing. <hi>All</hi>
               </hi> our <hi>Parliaments</hi> for almost a hundred years last past, have been so far from granting even the <hi>least Concession</hi> to the Crown in favour of <hi>popery,</hi> that on the contrary, all their <hi>Study, Votings, Labours,</hi> and <hi>Endeavours</hi> even to a <hi>Nemine Contradicente,</hi> have been levell'd at the very <hi>Root</hi> of it; so far from countenancing of it, that the very <hi>sound</hi> of it has made them fly out into the most <hi>rapid Torrent</hi> of <hi>Contradiction</hi> even beyond the Duty of <hi>Subjects,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of Complimenting either <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Popery,</hi> they have tyed up their very Hands even from the best of <hi>Protestant Crown'd Heads,</hi> and in their <hi>highest Extremities</hi> denyed them their most <hi>reasonable Demands</hi> in the most pressing <hi>Necessities</hi> of the Crown, and all for the Apprehension of <hi>popish <hi>Designs,</hi>
               </hi> and for keeping the least String of their Purses from <hi>popish <hi>Fingers.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>I need not instance what Load of Miseries attended the late <hi>Royal Martyr</hi> from this <hi>Fatal Original.</hi> Neither do I urge this in Relation to those detestable <hi>Regicides,</hi> the corrupted Limbs of that <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable Senate,</hi> that under the Vizor of <hi>Religion,</hi> were plotting the most <hi>Infernal</hi> of <hi>Mischiefs;</hi> and so from the false Alarum of <hi>popery,</hi> denyed their Soveraign <hi>All Things</hi> only to make him <hi>Nothing.</hi> No, as <hi>All <hi>Men</hi>
               </hi> are not <hi>Monsters,</hi> and even in <hi>that <hi>Accursed Parliament</hi>
               </hi> there were <hi>some</hi> honest <hi>Men;</hi> yet those very honest Men, those that by the <hi>universal Delusion</hi> were <hi>inchanted</hi> into <hi>False Fears,</hi> and so design'd nothing but <hi>Truly</hi> the <hi>Prevention</hi> of <hi>popery,</hi> were yet under that Terrour, so <hi>Jealous</hi> of their Prince, so <hi>Deaf</hi> to his <hi>Interest,</hi> and so <hi>inexorable</hi> even to his most <hi>Crying Wants,</hi> and all for battring these fancy'd <hi>Ayry Castles,</hi> that in the vehemence of their <hi>Zeal</hi> they contributed to the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Designs</hi> of his <hi>Murderers;</hi> and how <hi>ignorantly</hi> soever, heap'd together the very <hi>Coals</hi> to the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal <hi>Conflagration;</hi> so far too, that they had only Time to detect the <hi>Infernal Imposture,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore the dire Effects of their miserable Mistake <hi>too late.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Besides, to come a little nearer home, What <hi>dismal Consequences</hi> were the late <hi>Malignant Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction</hi> of <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Iealousies</hi> in the same <hi>Fiery Trigon</hi> producing again? What <hi>Demi-Gods</hi> and <hi>Nation-Saviours</hi> did the whole <hi>Vox populi,</hi> nay, the very <hi>sensible</hi> Men of the Nation make of those very <hi>Varlets,</hi> which now their <hi>Opened Eyes</hi> and <hi>waken'd Senses</hi> (I appeal to their own Consciences) tell them are those <hi>flagitious, <hi>unparallel'd</hi> Villains,</hi> that would shame a <hi>Gibbet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet the very <hi>Loyallest</hi> of all our late Members of <hi>Parliament,</hi> for they were not all <hi>Shaftsburys</hi> nor all <hi>Sidneys;</hi> neither such that were for <hi>Associating</hi> to <hi>Kill-Kings,</hi> to <hi>keep out Popes,</hi> nor answer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Filmers</hi> out of <hi>Buchanan's</hi> and <hi>Miltons,</hi> nor seating the <hi>Good Old Cause</hi> at the <hi>Right Hand of GOD.</hi> Not those that made <hi>popery</hi> the <hi>pretence</hi> alone to manage their own <hi>Hellish Republick Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations.</hi> But only those that (alas, and well a day!) had been <hi>Beuk-Blawd</hi> a little out of their right Wits by the aforesaid <hi>Nation-Saviours,</hi> and so were for combating of <hi>Popery,</hi> possibly for the <hi>Real <hi>Preservation</hi>
               </hi> of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdom.</hi> Yet the very Loyallest of these Men, I say, were wrapt up to that <hi>height</hi> of <hi>perverseness,</hi> that to use the gentlest Terms I can find, they thought they could never do <hi>little enough</hi> even for <hi>that very King</hi> attested by their own <hi>unanimous reiterat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Acknowledgments to be the very <hi>Isthmus</hi> that kept POPERY from <hi>Surround<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Us; and on whose <hi>Only</hi> Thread of Life the whole <hi>FATE</hi> of the Protestant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion depended.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:42213:13"/>
            <p>I shall not trouble my self wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the Repeating the Diversity of <hi>Statutes</hi> recited in the <hi>Character</hi> to instance the various <hi>Bandying</hi> of the <hi>Succession</hi> of the Crown in <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Eighth's</hi> Reign, design<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there as an Argument of <hi>Justice</hi> for a <hi>Parliamentary <hi>Bill of Exclusion</hi>
               </hi> against a <hi>Popish Heir.</hi> For whatever different Settlements of the <hi>Descent</hi> of the Crown <hi>that</hi> King and his <hi>Parliaments</hi> were pleas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make, occasioned by the <hi>Intricacy</hi> of his <hi>Daughter's</hi> Titles, grounded upon that long contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted Point, the <hi>Divorce</hi> of Queen <hi>Katherine,</hi> the Mother of Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> and therefore not at all enacted as an <hi>Exclusion,</hi> but a <hi>Confirmation</hi> of the <hi>Right Heir.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, as far soever as a <hi>Parlimentary</hi> Power may pretend to extend in that Case, all these <hi>Statutes</hi> make nothing to the <hi>purpose</hi> for Justification of an <hi>Exclusion</hi> for matter of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For had those Parliamentary Proceedings been a <hi>Warrant</hi> or <hi>Precedent</hi> for any <hi>such Exclusion,</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was a more <hi>urgent Necessity</hi> than in Queen <hi>Mary's Reign,</hi> of laying hold of such a <hi>Pretension.</hi> For considering the State of <hi>Religion</hi> in her Time, when looking back to the two last King's <hi>Reigns;</hi> so formidable a Progress had the <hi>Protestant <hi>Perswasion</hi>
               </hi> made, and the Inclinations of the People lean'd so much towards the <hi>Reformation,</hi> that the very <hi>Change</hi> of the <hi>Prince</hi> was enough to turn the <hi>whole Ballance;</hi> and therefore as all her popish Measures were under a manifest <hi>prospect</hi> of being <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to pieces</hi> under a Protestant Successour, and that Successour was notoriously foreseen in her Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> so much that Bishop <hi>Gardiner</hi> (speaking of her) could say, <hi>That their burning of Heroticks was only vainly cutting off the Branches▪ whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st the <hi>Root</hi> was still alive.</hi> Yet nevertheless it was so far from entring the Breasts of a <hi>popish <hi>Soveraign</hi>
               </hi> and a <hi>popish <hi>Parliament</hi>
               </hi> to <hi>Exclude</hi> a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Heir,</hi> that Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> in his <hi>Abridgment</hi> of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> Book the 3d. <hi>page</hi> 325. says as follows. <hi>A Bill was brought into Parliament, confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ming the</hi> Letters Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ents <hi>which the Queen had granted, or might grant. This related to the Foundations of Religious Houses; but only</hi> Coxly <hi>opposed this, and insinuated, that perhaps the Queen intended to dispose of the Crown in prejudice of the Right Heir; at which the House express'd so great a Dislike, as shew'd they would not have it so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as imagined, that Lady</hi> Elizabeth <hi>could be <hi>excluded.</hi> He had a publick Reprimand given him for insinuat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Thing so much to the Queen's</hi> Dishonour.</p>
            <p>Now notwithstanding here was a Queen so <hi>Zealous</hi> for Popery, and a Parliament so officiously <hi>forward</hi> in Establishing of it, that they gave their Queen possibly one of the most <hi>Ample Royalties</hi> that ever Parliament lodged in the Prerogative, <hi>Viz.</hi> the confirming <hi>indefinitely</hi> all <hi>Letters Patents</hi> that the Soveraign either <hi>Had,</hi> or <hi>Might</hi> grant; yet still this very <hi>Parliament</hi> utterly abhorred even the <hi>Imagination</hi> of so <hi>infamous</hi> a <hi>Projection</hi> as an <hi>Exclusion Bill:</hi> nor did the Bigotted Queen her self ever debase her self so low as to make use of this Act of Parliament, or any part of her Prerogative for so <hi>Dishonourable a purpose</hi> as the Prejudice of her Sister's <hi>Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to compare Cases. If both a <hi>popish Prince</hi> and a <hi>popish Parliament</hi> detested the Exclusion of a <hi>protestant <hi>Successour,</hi>
               </hi> though in so <hi>threatning</hi> a Juncture, and so <hi>truly</hi> an <hi>Impending Danger</hi> to their Religion from that Succession, and that too, when her Parliaments had declared the <hi>Divorce</hi> of Queen <hi>Katherine,</hi> Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> Mother, <hi>unlawful;</hi> and consequently might have soreclosed the Right of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> under the most specious Pretext even of <hi>Illegitimacy</hi> it self. On the contrary, why should a <hi>protestant <hi>Monarch</hi>
               </hi> and a <hi>protestant <hi>Parliament</hi>
               </hi> now <hi>Strain Honour</hi> and <hi>Consciences</hi> beyond the very <hi>Papists themselves,</hi> and exclude a <hi>Royal Heir</hi> upon <hi>Presumption</hi> of being a <hi>papist,</hi> though with never so undoubted a <hi>Right,</hi> and above all <hi>pretensions</hi> of <hi>Scruple</hi> or <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute,</hi> and that under <hi>little,</hi> or indeed <hi>no</hi> Danger to our Religion at all, a Religion not only so in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincibly Fortifyed with so many strong <hi>Bulwarks of Law,</hi> but likewise by that most Impregnable of all <hi>Bulwarks,</hi>
               <q>Defendit Numerus junctaeque umbone Phalanges.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The almost <hi>Totality</hi> of the Nation (comparatively speaking) against so <hi>feeble</hi> and <hi>scattered</hi> a <hi>Remnant</hi> of Papists, and so universal an <hi>Odium</hi> of <hi>popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I shall not think it worth my while to make much <hi>Reply</hi> to that part of the <hi>Character</hi> that treats upon <hi>Passive Obedience,</hi> and so boldly justifies the taking up <hi>Arms</hi> againg an <hi>Oppressing Monarch.</hi> 'Tis enough that <hi>Great Point</hi> of our <hi>Christianity</hi> has been the Subject of Nobler Pens, and therefore the <hi>discussing</hi> it is a province above me. I shall only give the <hi>Reader</hi> this <hi>Quaery.</hi> If the <hi>Great Lord</hi> of our <hi>Salvation</hi> could enjoyn the <hi>turning of the other Cheek</hi> even to Injuries received from our <hi>Equals;</hi> I would fain know what part of <hi>Christianity</hi> can allow Resistance to <hi>God's Annointed?</hi> Let it suffice, that all that part of the <hi>Character</hi> was written by the Direction of the Right Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able the <hi>Earl of Shaftsbury,</hi> after an Amendment made in the <hi>Character</hi> by the Advise of that LOYAL <hi>Peer,</hi> bidding me <hi>speak more favourably of Rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have you heard, not only all that the <hi>popish <hi>Character,</hi>
               </hi> but likewise the <hi>popular Fears</hi> have urged for the <hi>pretended Danger</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary-power.</hi> And I doubt not but all <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing</hi> and <hi>unbyassed Readers</hi> will be fully satisfyed of the <hi>unreasonableness</hi> of that <hi>Epidemical Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lousie</hi> that has so long infected the Head and Brains of the <hi>Short-sighted populace</hi> through those <hi>Scare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crows.</hi> I shall only now give the <hi>Reader</hi> his last Farewell of the <hi>popish Character</hi> in the <hi>Concluding Paragraph</hi> of that Pamphlet.</p>
            <p>After that whole Libel by a <hi>Tautological sort</hi> of <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> a great many <hi>accumulated</hi> Words, but especially gay <hi>Allegories,</hi> has over and over again drawn a <hi>popish Successour</hi> only in so many
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42213:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:42213:14"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:42213:15"/> several Disguises; as one while making him a <hi>Nero with his Harp,</hi> and then his three Kingdoms are <hi>in one General Conflagration:</hi> another time an <hi>Alexander in his Cups,</hi> and then <hi>every honest protestant</hi> Clytus <hi>that doth but thwart his drunken Frenzy, is immediately his Frenzy's Sacrifice.</hi> Another while he's in the Prophet <hi>Elisha's Dream,</hi> and then the <hi>poor <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> ants</hi> are the very Birds and four legged Beasts that bob at his Mouth, with this Label over their Heads, <hi>Rise, Slay,</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Eat.</hi> In another place, instead of <hi>Pater patriae,</hi> he's nothing but a downright <hi>Lupus Agri,</hi> and then we are only <hi>Sheep</hi> and <hi>Lambs. Cum multis aliis,</hi> &amp;c. In short, having danced him through all the <hi>Elements,</hi> and transformed him into more several <hi>Bestial Shapes</hi> than ever <hi>Jupiter</hi> Whored in; after the <hi>Character</hi> has all the way brought us to <hi>universal</hi> and <hi>inevitable</hi> Destruction, and <hi>Enslaved</hi> both <hi>Vs</hi> and our <hi>posterity,</hi> till the Admission of a <hi>popish</hi> Successour at last is <hi>no less than a Plot of GOD himself to scourge a Nation, and make three Kingdoms miserable, a Design form'd by the Irresistable Decree of Heaven, either for our Sins, or what Cause, to its self best known, to lay a Groaning Country in Ruine,</hi> &amp;c. After all this, no sooner is this Ruinous Doom pronounced, but the <hi>Character</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately proceeds <hi>in haec verba.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>Upon the Supposition of a <hi>popish <hi>Heir</hi>
                  </hi> we must not conclude, that 'tis only the poor distressed <hi>Protestants</hi> that shall feel the Smart, and stand the Mark of <hi>Slavery</hi> and <hi>Martyrdom.</hi> A <hi>popish</hi> King has that pestilential Influence, that he <hi>blasts</hi> even the very party he <hi>smiles</hi> upon, and entayls a <hi>Curse</hi> upon his dearest Darling <hi>Favourites.</hi> As for Instance, if after this King's Reign, steps up a <hi>prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant</hi> Prince (for surely the whole Royal Blood must not all follow his <hi>Apostacy,</hi> and degenerate <hi>in secula seculorum</hi>) th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n what becomes of the popish Interest in the next Generation; and all that flourishing Party, whom either the Witchcrafts of <hi>Rome,</hi> or the Contagion of <hi>Regis ad Exemplum has <hi>nurst</hi>
                  </hi> up for <hi>Ruine.</hi> 'Tis the greatest Toyl of the next King's Reign, to make those <hi>severer Statutes</hi> for <hi>future</hi> Ages, to s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ppress the <hi>Insolencies</hi> and <hi>Follyes</hi> of the <hi>past;</hi> whil'st those very <hi>Idols</hi> that were <hi>Saints</hi> but yesterday, are now <hi>crush't</hi> and <hi>dash't</hi> to <hi>pieces.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now in the Name of <hi>Blunder Egregious,</hi> here's <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>Baxter</hi> to the highest of Perfection. For here's the whole foregoing <hi>Design</hi> of the <hi>Character</hi> quash't at this one last blow. For if really all the <hi>popish</hi> and Arbitrary Movements and Acquisitions of a Romish Prince (as the Character it <hi>self</hi> affirms, which indeed by Chance is the very Oracle of the Pamphlet) will be totally <hi>crusht and destroyed</hi> under the next protestant Soveraign: and all his <hi>popish <hi>Tools</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Partizans,</hi> nay, the whole <hi>Romish Cause</hi> it self given up to the protestant <hi>Justice</hi> and <hi>Revenge,</hi> that shall <hi>crush them to pieces;</hi> so that in perfect Contradiction, instead of <hi>inextricable <hi>Slavery,</hi> universal</hi> protestant <hi>Ruine,</hi> and a <hi>total <hi>Extirpation</hi>
               </hi> of <hi>Heresy,</hi> prognosticated all along in the <hi>Character;</hi> here's at most but a <hi>Temporary</hi> Flourishing of <hi>Popery,</hi> and so far from a real protestant <hi>Suppression,</hi> either by <hi>Persecution</hi> or <hi>Massacres,</hi> or the Devil knows what, that we shall be strong enough to rise up under the next protestant Heir, and to <hi>pluck up</hi> and demolish even <hi>Root</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> all the preceding <hi>Batteries</hi> and <hi>Machinations</hi> against our Religion and Liberties, whil'st the <hi>True <hi>Ruine</hi>
               </hi> lies in fine, not on the <hi>protestant,</hi> but <hi>popish</hi> Side. If so, I say, as the <hi>Character</hi> has unluckily started this undeniable <hi>Truth,</hi> certainly we lye under no danger of a popish Successours ever attempting that irregular <hi>po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish <hi>Atchievement,</hi>
               </hi> and setting up that <hi>Short-liv'd</hi> Arbitrary popish <hi>Dagon,</hi> which, as has been proved before, and is even <hi>confest</hi> here, will be of so Calamitous a Consequence to the <hi>Interest</hi> and <hi>Safety</hi> even of his whole Party and Religion.</p>
            <p>You see, Reader, what <hi>Incoherence, Absurdities, Contradictions,</hi> and indeed <hi>Impossibilities</hi> the popish Character is fraught with, and what notorious Stuff that is that <hi>Revenge</hi> and <hi>Malice</hi> obtrudes upon Mankind, where <hi>popery</hi> is the <hi>Theme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But truely 'tis to be consider'd, that that Pamphlet was written and publish't, not for the Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Seven Wise Men,</hi> but of the <hi>seven thousand Ill-natured Knaves,</hi> and the <hi>seventy <hi>thousand credulous, unreasoning Fools</hi>
               </hi> of that Age, (the REPRESENTATIVE <hi>Patrons,</hi> to whom that Libel was <hi>Dedicated,</hi> not excepted from the Number) that would have swallow'd <hi>every Syllable</hi> of it, had it been <hi>ten times</hi> more lewdly ridiculous than 'twas.</p>
            <p>Now, as not only the <hi>Character,</hi> but the unpondered and groundless Apprehensions of Men, have so dreadfully <hi>predicted</hi> such a terrible bloody <hi>Revolution</hi> under a popish Successour, without one <hi>Jota</hi> of proving or examining how that wondrous Change is possible to <hi>come to pass;</hi> that the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> may not be surprized at that <hi>weak sort</hi> of arguing in the one, and that headlong <hi>Credulity</hi> in the other, 'tis remarkable, that not <hi>one</hi> Pen that ever wrote upon Popery and Arbitrary-Power, ever scribbled otherwise. For as the HOW and WHICH WAY they can be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced into England, are not in <hi>posse,</hi> those Essential Circumstances are always <hi>stubber'd over,</hi> and nothing but a <hi>Huddle</hi> and <hi>Jingle</hi> of <hi>general Notions</hi> of <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Faggot Assassinations</hi> and <hi>Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacres, Popes</hi> and <hi>Devils,</hi> &amp;c. And a Declamatory Discant upon those <hi>Tragical Heads,</hi> are ever the whole Contents of the Chapter; and whil'st the peoples Fears are set a tingling by this sort of <hi>Din</hi> and <hi>Gibberish,</hi> they are babled out of their <hi>Senses,</hi> and transported into <hi>Frenzy</hi> it self without looking <hi>farther,</hi> or searching <hi>deeper</hi> for the <hi>Grounds</hi> of their <hi>Fears.</hi> For Example, let us trace up the first Alarum of Popery and Arbitrary-power even to the <hi>Fountain Head.</hi> In all the <hi>venemous Libels</hi> in the late blest <hi>Martyr's</hi> Reign (for there were <hi>popish <hi>Character Writers</hi>
               </hi> in those Days too, though in other Names) in all the <hi>Licentiousness</hi> of that Villanous Age, and the highest <hi>Encouragement</hi> of <hi>Rebellious Senates,</hi> there were neither those <hi>Pens</hi> nor <hi>Tongues <hi>within</hi>
               </hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:42213:15"/> the Parliament House, or <hi>without</hi> it, that could ever go further than to a bare <hi>general <hi>Allegation</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Outcry</hi> of Popery and Arbitrary Power; for in all the hideous Roarings against <hi>popish-Counsel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> (as 'tis not the <hi>Councellers,</hi> but the <hi>Councel</hi> put in <hi>Execution</hi> that can hurt us) was there any Man of them all that <hi>did,</hi> or indeed, <hi>pretended</hi> to <hi>particularize</hi> those popish Counsels, or form the <hi>least Draught</hi> of any Dangerous <hi>popish</hi> Machinations whatever under the least <hi>probability</hi> of shaking our <hi>Laws, Liberties,</hi> or <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, there were <hi>strange</hi> and <hi>wondrous <hi>popish Incendiaries</hi> represented</hi> at work, but about <hi>doing</hi> of <hi>what,</hi> The Devil a word they inform us. Not all the <hi>Republick Rhetorick,</hi> nor all the <hi>Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence</hi> even of <hi>counterfeit <hi>Fears</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Jealousies</hi> could lay down one <hi>tolerable Demonstration</hi> of the <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Compositions</hi> of those popish <hi>Fireballs</hi> those Incendiaries were to use, or the <hi>Conbustableness</hi> of what they were to set on Fire. Nay, those very <hi>Devils</hi> that had <hi>Impudence enough,</hi> not only to <hi>murder <hi>the best of Kings,</hi>
               </hi> but to bring him to a <hi>Scaffold,</hi> with a solemn <hi>Pageantry of Iustice,</hi> were nevertheless so far from the Confidence of pretending the popish <hi>Strength</hi> or <hi>Numbers</hi> in England to have the least <hi>Shadow of Ability</hi> to erect their <hi>Romish Altars,</hi> and subvert the <hi>Protestant Religion;</hi> that to carry on the popular Fears by that <hi>Forged Sham</hi> of Popery, and give <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Bulk</hi> to the <hi>Gorgon,</hi> they were forced to help out one <hi>damn'd Imposture</hi> by a <hi>Greater,</hi> and bring in the very <hi>Church of England</hi> for <hi>Popish</hi> and <hi>Antichristian</hi> to joyn in the Plot. Nor were our <hi>later</hi> true Protestant Rome-dreaders much short of the <hi>same Artifice,</hi> to <hi>crutch up the <hi>same Cripple.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, for want of any <hi>Substantial</hi> Pretext of the Introduction of any of the <hi>Real <hi>Fundamental Superstitions</hi>
               </hi> of Rome, they were put to the <hi>wretched Shift</hi> of making the harmless <hi>Book of Sports,</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>censed by Bishop <hi>Laud,</hi> and an after-Service Game at <hi>Coyts</hi> or <hi>Stool-Ball,</hi> no less than all over <hi>Rome and Antichrist;</hi> yes, and to push the <hi>Jest</hi> a little farther, the old Kings tolerating half a score of Priests (in Indulgence to his Queen) to wear the <hi>Habit of their Order,</hi> though in Reality an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject more for the <hi>Hooting</hi> of <hi>Boys,</hi> than the <hi>Converting</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> was screwed up to no less <hi>than a Plot upon the <hi>whole Reformation.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, as the Characterizing of such a Tyrannick popish Successour in England, is but Mounting that Chimerical <hi>Jehu</hi> in the Chariot where neither his <hi>Wheels</hi> can move him, nor the <hi>Ground</hi> will bear him; and all the Pretensions of Fears from Popery are only <hi>Suppositious</hi> and <hi>Delusive;</hi> nay, and considering that those most violent Asserters of Romish Dangers in that very Age, when they had this <hi>Advantage</hi> to help out, <hi>Viz.</hi> To alledge the Old King was a <hi>Papist in Disguise;</hi> by which <hi>Villanous Supposition</hi> they h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ten times a fairer Field for the pretended Introduction of <hi>Popery</hi> than can be under a <hi>Visible popish Prince;</hi> could nevertheless urge so little to the purpose, and so weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly support the Cause of such <hi>Fears:</hi> The <hi>Contradictions, Noyse, Rumble</hi> and <hi>Nonsense</hi> in the <hi>Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter</hi> on the worse side of the Hedge, are a little more Excusable.</p>
            <p>Having (I may with Confidence say) fully answered and confuted all <hi>Appearances</hi> or <hi>Suppositions</hi> of Danger from a <hi>Popish Successour;</hi> yet as the Minds of some People are so strangely possest and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatuated with those <hi>Brainsick Fancies,</hi> and <hi>Visionary Specters</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Slavery,</hi> that scarce the most apparent <hi>Truth,</hi> the most substancial <hi>Reason,</hi> not <hi>Oracles,</hi> nay, not <hi>Angels</hi> from <hi>Heaven</hi> could <hi>Cure</hi> or <hi>Dispel.</hi> I shall therefore go one step further, and to dissipate all <hi>Storms</hi> or <hi>Clouds</hi> whatever from <hi>Romewards</hi> impending, plainly and absolutely convince them, that whatever Scruples may yet remain unsatisfyed; at this present day there is not the least <hi>Prospect</hi> or <hi>Idea</hi> of any such <hi>Threatning Successour</hi> in the present Royal Line of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For though that Illustrious Prince, whom the Malice of <hi>Antimonarchal</hi> and <hi>Associating Traytors,</hi> and the Insolence of a Pack of Seditious and Confederate <hi>Commons,</hi> like the old Sons of Earth, have levell'd their <hi>spightful,</hi> though <hi>feeble</hi> Vengeance at; though that great <hi>Injur'd</hi> Prince, I say, through the <hi>false Mirrour</hi> of those <hi>Anarchical Boutefeus</hi> has been villaniously rendred almost the only <hi>Object</hi> of the greatest part of the popular Jealousies, as the intended <hi>Ʋnderminer</hi> of our <hi>Laws, Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberties;</hi> I shall unanswerably demonstrate the utter <hi>Impossibility</hi> of that glorious Prince's <hi>ever being that Man,</hi> or debasing himself so much, as to entertain the least Thought that way, be his Religion what ever it will.</p>
            <p>For supposing he were really a <hi>Convert</hi> to the Romish Perswasion, what <hi>Pillar</hi> is that Prince likely to make to the <hi>Romish Cause?</hi> For if he be that Convert, either the <hi>Pope</hi> believes a <hi>popish Heir</hi> of <hi>England <hi>Capable</hi>
               </hi> of setting up the Romish Religion, or <hi>not</hi> capable of doing it.</p>
            <p>If <hi>capable,</hi> as that's the present Point; Then undoubtedly (which is but a reasonable <hi>Conclusion</hi>) he has left no <hi>Pains</hi> nor <hi>Industry</hi> unmanaged to <hi>Advance</hi> or <hi>Advantage</hi> the Popish Interest by such a Convert as an Heir of the English Crown. And if so, the <hi>only Policy,</hi> or indeed the only <hi>possible Means</hi> of favouring the least <hi>Romish Hopes</hi> whatever, had been to have used the utmost <hi>Papal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority</hi> for enjoyning and perswading him, not only to have kept himself wholly undiscoverd, but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise wholly <hi>unsuspected</hi> to the Kingdom by any Abscenting from our <hi>Communion,</hi> or any other Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary Symtome of such a Conversion.</p>
            <p>For as all the greatest of <hi>Inconveniencies</hi> and <hi>Misfortunes</hi> have attended the whole popish Party up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>meer Supposition</hi> of such a Conversion; and that only founded on the foremention'd <hi>Occasion</hi> of <hi>Suspition.</hi> Witness the removing all Papists whatever from all <hi>Offices</hi> of <hi>Trust</hi> in the whole Kingdom, from all <hi>Seats,</hi> either in <hi>State Administration</hi> or <hi>Parliaments</hi> by the present <hi>Protestant TEST,</hi> wholly created upon that <hi>Suspition;</hi> by Force of which there is not the least Admission of a Papist into any Place of <hi>Power</hi> in the Government, except by taking of the <hi>Protestant Sacrament,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:42213:16"/> and entring into a Solemn Oath against the <hi>popish Religion,</hi> and subscribing to a <hi>Recorded Abjurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> even of the greatest and most <hi>Essential Articles</hi> of their Faith as <hi>Superstitious</hi> and <hi>Idolatrous;</hi> and so by the most impudent <hi>premeditated Perjury,</hi> and setting the notorious Brand upon themselves of that sordid and scandalous <hi>Renuntiation</hi> of their very Religion, which the poorest Soul'd <hi>Pagan</hi> that ever worship't but <hi>Garlick</hi> and <hi>Onions</hi> would blush at.</p>
            <p>Besides all this weeding out of the <hi>popish</hi> Party from all Authority and Power, being no <hi>small <hi>Blow</hi>
               </hi> to their Interest under so weak a Number of that Perswasion in England. There is not any <hi>one Calamity</hi> that for these seven last years has befall'n the <hi>who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e popish Party,</hi> that is not truly owing almost <hi>wholly</hi> to this <hi>Suspition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore as all the <hi>Ill Consequences</hi> (or <hi>worse</hi>) attending them, are really no more than the <hi>Pope</hi> and all his <hi>Counsellors</hi> could in common <hi>Reason</hi> expect from a Nation so <hi>extravagantly jealous</hi> of <hi>Popery;</hi> whil'st woful Experience might have remembranced him how <hi>dangerous</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive</hi> even a <hi>less Shadow</hi> of <hi>popish</hi> Inclinations had been; nothing was more indispensable (I mean for the <hi>popish Interest</hi>) in a <hi>popish Heir,</hi> than <hi>all means</hi> of <hi>avoiding</hi> such <hi>Suspition;</hi> nay, possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly even for his own secure <hi>Access</hi> to the <hi>Throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis true, some ridiculous People have foolishly objected, That the Deserting of our <hi>Communion</hi> was for the <hi>Advantage</hi> of their <hi>Cause;</hi> it being as it were setting up the <hi>Standard of Popery</hi> to call all Hearts and Hands together; whereas otherwise the <hi>Romanists</hi> had been kept in Ignorance of the <hi>Champion</hi> God had raised for their <hi>Deliverance;</hi> and thereby might have neglected the glorious <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity</hi> that offered it self.—Now in the Name of <hi>Dulness,</hi> it any such Deliverance were <hi>imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable,</hi> or any Succour to the <hi>Romish Cause</hi> whatever, either sooner or later could be expected from such a <hi>Convert;</hi> or lastly, if the <hi>Conscience</hi> or <hi>unfullyed Glory</hi> of that <hi>Heroick Prince</hi> were possible to be wrought upon to stoop to so ignoble a <hi>Design,</hi> as any <hi>unwarrantable</hi> popish Assistance; Why must the <hi>Papists</hi> be kept in Ignorance of his being one of them, <hi>if he were so;</hi> without some kind of publick Declaration: when 'tis notoriously known to all the sensible part of Mankind, what Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of <hi>Intelligence</hi> and <hi>Correspondence</hi> the Papists have above all Religions in the World, when their <hi>Jesuites</hi> are by the very Duty of their <hi>Order,</hi> the greatest <hi>Spyes upon Christendom,</hi> whil'st the privatest Affairs and Secrets of <hi>Families, Courts</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms</hi> through all <hi>Europe,</hi> from hand to hand, and from Superiour to Superiour of them, are convey'd to the <hi>Pope</hi> himself.</p>
            <p>So that take the whole Matter toge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her with this Advantage of <hi>Communication</hi> even under <hi>Confession</hi> it self on the one side, and the foremention'd Dangers from a <hi>National Jealousie</hi> on the other, as I said before; whatever Discovery might have been requisite to their <hi>own Party,</hi> the highest Policy of <hi>Rome</hi> had been to have concealed the very Suspition of it from the <hi>Protestants;</hi> more especially, if they had had any such Thing as a <hi>King-killing Plot</hi> in hand, or the least part of the <hi>Salamanca Conspiracy</hi> upon the Anvil. For then they might have made use of <hi>Ruffians,</hi> or <hi>Screw'd Gunners,</hi> and as <hi>Dugdale</hi> swears, have laid the King's Murder upon the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> or any other of the scatter'd <hi>Churches</hi> with ten times more ease; and have hastened the Mounting a <hi>popish Successour</hi> with more Facility into the Royal Seat.</p>
            <p>And therefore as nothing can be a <hi>plainer</hi> or <hi>greater Obstacle</hi> to all <hi>popish Designs</hi> whatever than this <hi>Conduct</hi> in the present Heir of <hi>England,</hi> if he be a <hi>Romanist,</hi> and they had an Expectation of any considerable <hi>Advantage</hi> to their Religion from his being one: undoubtedly there has been no <hi>Oratory</hi> wanting to induce him to so necessary and so <hi>Venial</hi> a Disguise, as being the most important Prop of their <hi>Cause.</hi> But maugre all the <hi>Necessity</hi> of such a Compliance, and all the <hi>Romish Interest</hi> depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereupon, notwithstanding the papal Power of a <hi>Dispensation</hi> in that Case, and all the <hi>Arts</hi> that may have been used to that <hi>purpose;</hi> nothing is more visible than his <hi>Indisposition</hi> and <hi>Aversion</hi> to so <hi>dishonourable a Condiscension</hi> as playing the <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> how dispensable soever in that <hi>Church,</hi> or how <hi>advantagious</hi> soever to his own Circumstances.</p>
            <p>Now I appeal to all <hi>Mankind</hi> what <hi>least Apparition</hi> of <hi>popish Danger,</hi> or what <hi>humane possibility</hi> of that very Princes ever being that so much dreaded <hi>Romish Instrument</hi> for <hi>Arbitrary popish Tyranny,</hi> through the most execrable <hi>Violation</hi> of the most sacred <hi>Royal Trust,</hi> the most flagitious of <hi>Perjury</hi> in the Breach of a solemn <hi>Coronation Oath,</hi> to trample our <hi>Laws, Religions,</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> to <hi>pieces;</hi> that has already <hi>proved</hi> himself so incapable of <hi>dispensing</hi> but with one poor piece of <hi>Hypocrisy,</hi> though against the highest <hi>Interest</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> though to the wakening of all the sleeping <hi>Statutes</hi> against <hi>Recusancy,</hi> tho to the raysing of <hi>Tests, Oaths,</hi> and <hi>Sacraments;</hi> and thereby not only <hi>excluding</hi> the Sons of <hi>Rome</hi> from all <hi>Honours, Trusts,</hi> and <hi>Employments,</hi> but likewise exposing them to the Dayly Severities and Perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the <hi>Laws,</hi> nay, and very near to the shaking of his own <hi>Hereditary Succession</hi> to an Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Crown.</p>
            <p>Now (I say) if this very Prince (upon Presumption of that Church) be nevertheless a Person of those <hi>rigid</hi> Principles of <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Conscience,</hi> that he durst not so much as digest so inconside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a <hi>piece</hi> of <hi>Dissimulation,</hi> though for the highest and most Important Service to himself and his <hi>whole Church;</hi> how much <hi>less</hi> shall he ever <hi>condiscend</hi> to the <hi>Ignominious</hi> and <hi>Indelible Brand</hi> of down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right <hi>Perjur'd,</hi> and launch into all the <hi>Barbarities</hi> and <hi>Outrages</hi> of <hi>Tyrant</hi> and <hi>Murderer,</hi> and all this too, as has been plainly proved before) with very <hi>little,</hi> or <hi>none;</hi> at least, no reasonable <hi>Hopes</hi> of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himself or his Church any Service at all.</p>
            <p>Besides, as tis utterly impossible either for <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Papists,</hi> even with the most <hi>Romantick <hi>Assurance</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Confidence</hi> of <hi>Success</hi> ever to hope for a National Conversion, or a Romish Establishment in <hi>One Age;</hi> insomuch that 'tis not a <hi>single <hi>Popish Successour,</hi>
               </hi> but a <hi>Line</hi> of <hi>Popish Successours</hi> that can be so
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:42213:16"/> much as suppos'd capable of going through with so difficult an <hi>Ʋndertaking;</hi> what least <hi>Shadow</hi> of any such <hi>Intention</hi> can we imagine from this Royal <hi>Heir,</hi> when he has not only bred up his next <hi>Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Heirs,</hi> his Children in the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> but likewise lodg'd them in the Bosomes of those very <hi>Protestant Princes,</hi> as far from the least <hi>Inclination</hi> towards <hi>Rome,</hi> or a <hi>Look</hi> that way, as the whole <hi>Choice</hi> of <hi>Christendom</hi> could have <hi>pickt out.</hi> So that upon the Issue of the whole Matter, how contrary to <hi>common sense</hi> is it, to think that very Prince either <hi>is,</hi> or <hi>can</hi> be so <hi>stupidly infatuated</hi> as ever to Embark in so <hi>hazardous an Atchievement,</hi> which (were he Crown'd to <hi>morrow</hi>) with his years upon his back, he begins but with the <hi>latter part</hi> of a Life, and which the length of a Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth's</hi> Reign could never finish. And all this so preposterously too, as to be for building that Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish Interest with <hi>one hand,</hi> which he has so palpably destroy'd with the <hi>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Considering then, (as has been fully proved before) that <hi>Popery</hi> in the present State of <hi>England,</hi> is something like the vulgar Tradition of the <hi>Basilisk,</hi> it must either look <hi>Vs</hi> safely <hi>Dead,</hi> or we shall look <hi>that</hi> so; For there's no <hi>Medium</hi> in the Case, between <hi>Conquering</hi> or <hi>Dying:</hi> who in his right wits can imagine this Prince will ever <hi>Begin</hi> what he himself before hand has taken Care shall never be <hi>Finish't.</hi> And if not <hi>finish't,</hi> will be but put into a ten times <hi>worse Condition</hi> than if <hi>never begun.</hi> And therefore not only his meer <hi>Pride</hi> will be our <hi>Security,</hi> it being impossible that any thing that has one <hi>spark</hi> of <hi>Glory</hi> will ever ingage in a Cause under such <hi>Certainty</hi> of a <hi>Defeat:</hi> but likewise supposing even the utmost Suggestions true; under such an <hi>Impossibility</hi> of <hi>Crowning the Work,</hi> the <hi>Greater</hi> the <hi>Zeal,</hi> the more <hi>Inoffensive</hi> the <hi>Zealot:</hi> since all <hi>Irregular</hi> exorbitant Ferments of <hi>Popery</hi> will but hatch <hi>Scorpions</hi> and warm <hi>Stings</hi> for its own Destruction: the greater the <hi>Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> for his own Party and Religion, the greater the <hi>Security</hi> of <hi>ours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover the <hi>Character <hi>positively</hi>
               </hi> lays down this <hi>Maxime.</hi> That the <hi>Papists</hi> doom all out of their own Church to <hi>certain Damnation:</hi> and on that <hi>Foundation</hi> all their Bloody <hi>Principles</hi> are built, as thinking no Cruelty <hi>too severe,</hi> nor any Tyranny <hi>too sanguinary;</hi> but on the contrary, the most <hi>bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous</hi> Gospel Propagation the greatest <hi>Obligation</hi> of their Religion. And therefore it tells you, <hi>A <hi>popish</hi> Successour will never believe he can do his Subjects an Injustice in that very Thing in which he doth God Service, or that he injures Ʋs when he does our Souls right.</hi> And that therefore all the threatned <hi>Miseries, Horrours</hi> and <hi>Desolations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> from the beginning to the end of the whole Character, flow from no other <hi>Source.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if this be truly the <hi>Tenet</hi> of a <hi>Romanist,</hi> and all our horrible dangers proceed from <hi>that Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net,</hi> either our present <hi>Royal Heir</hi> must be <hi>no Romanist</hi> at all; or if he be one, however he absolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>dissents</hi> from <hi>Rome</hi> in that particular <hi>Main Principle.</hi> For if such were his <hi>Faith,</hi> and such his <hi>Principles,</hi> why has he so <hi>wilfully</hi> and so <hi>egregiously</hi> contributed to his own Children's <hi>Damnation,</hi> not only in their severest <hi>Protestant Education,</hi> but likewise in that <hi>additional</hi> Strengthening that Damnable Perswasion by such <hi>Fatal Marriages,</hi> whereby he has not only endanger'd their <hi>living</hi> and <hi>dying</hi> in that Erronious <hi>Faith,</hi> but likewise secured the <hi>Interest</hi> and <hi>Establishment</hi> of that <hi>prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Religion</hi> in likelihood by <hi>Them and their Heirs</hi> to the <hi>End of the World;</hi> and consequently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to the Damnation of succeeding <hi>Heretical Generations</hi> in <hi>Secula seculorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have only one thing more to add for the <hi>Safety</hi> of our <hi>Religion.</hi> There is not in the World that Prince in his Nature more <hi>grateful</hi> for Services and Obligations received, or a <hi>firmer</hi> and more <hi>unalterable Friend</hi> than himself. And as the <hi>Church,</hi> and only the <hi>Church of England</hi> has truly and vigorously asserted the <hi>Iustice</hi> and <hi>Duty</hi> of maintaining his <hi>unforfeitable Succession</hi> and <hi>Inviolable Birthright,</hi> and has stood <hi>ALONE <hi>in the Gap</hi>
               </hi> against all the whole <hi>Crowd</hi> of his <hi>Enemys;</hi> we may confidently assure our selves, that if ever 'tis Heaven's pleasure he should be our Soveraign, that all such <hi>kind</hi> and <hi>signally good Offices</hi> will never be ungratefully requited by the most <hi>Generous</hi> of <hi>Mankind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I shall only conclude; under this <hi>manifest Security</hi> of our Religion and Government on all hands, They that shall have Impudence enough (no <hi>Person</hi> nor <hi>Quality,</hi> in any <hi>Station whatever</hi> excepted) to persecute that Prince under the Pretence of <hi>Fear,</hi> are undoubtedly planting the <hi>same Batteries</hi> against three Kingdoms that were rais'd in his Royal <hi>Father's Reign;</hi> and a <hi>Bill of Exclusion</hi> must truly carry the Design of all the old <hi>Remonstrances, Ordinances, Covenants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </hi> with the <hi>Soul</hi> of a <hi>Cook,</hi> a <hi>Bradshaw,</hi> and a <hi>Cromwel</hi> at the <hi>Bottom</hi> on't: and all the <hi>Senate-House <hi>Church-proppers</hi>
               </hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that <hi>Vizor,</hi> are only Establishing <hi>Religion</hi> with the same <hi>Brand</hi> in their <hi>Hearts</hi> that <hi>Cain</hi> built <hi>Citys.</hi> And I doubt not but the <hi>Wisdom</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> of <hi>Succeeding Times</hi> will regain <hi>Sense</hi> enough to <hi>countermine</hi> all such <hi>Villany,</hi> and redeem the yet unrecovered <hi>Honour</hi> of <hi>England</hi> by <hi>shaming</hi> such a <hi>Second Imposture</hi> from the <hi>World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now to draw to a Period, I have only this <hi>Warning</hi> to give to the great <hi>Sticklers</hi> against Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery and Arbitrary Power, to have a Care that they <hi>Themselves</hi> do not bring in what they so <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lously</hi> endeavour to keep <hi>Out.</hi> For if Popery and Arbitrary Power shall ever get Footing in <hi>England</hi> by a Popish Successour, it can only be <hi>then,</hi> when by <hi>Ʋnlawful Exclusions,</hi> and <hi>Rebellious Associations</hi> against him, they shall put him upon cutting his way to his <hi>Throne</hi> by his <hi>Sword,</hi> and consequently give him the Occasion, both by <hi>Forreign</hi> and <hi>Domestick Assistance,</hi> of gaining that <hi>Right</hi> by <hi>Conquest</hi> which is denyed him to assume in <hi>Peace;</hi> and thereby enable him by the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Right</hi> of a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour,</hi> to Abolish what <hi>Laws,</hi> and Establish what Government he pleases, without either strain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his <hi>Honour</hi> or <hi>Prerogative.</hi> And so shall the <hi>Irregular Designs</hi> of <hi>defending</hi> our Religion and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:42213:17"/> be the only means of destroying them. And that this will be the undoubted Success of such <hi>unlawful</hi> and <hi>trayterous</hi> Opposition of the <hi>Royal Heir,</hi> let all such Turbulent Spirits (for their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort) consider that the World is much <hi>mended</hi> of late, and whatever Prosperity attended their victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Father's <hi>Rebellious Arms,</hi> the old <hi>Cheat</hi> will not pass altogether so glibly a <hi>second</hi> time; and the deposing of Monarchs will be, in all reasonable prospect, a <hi>tougher piece</hi> of Work in <hi>this Age</hi> than the last. For Men's Eyes and Understandings begin to be more <hi>Enlightned,</hi> and the <hi>Odds</hi> (thanks be to Heaven) is on the <hi>Loyal</hi> Side.</p>
            <p>However as a Caution to those <hi>unwary</hi> People that may be seduced by the false <hi>Suggestions</hi> of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publican Conspirators</hi> under the plausible Pretence of <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> to ingage in so impious a <hi>Cause.</hi> Besides the Breach of their <hi>Christianity</hi> and Hazard of their <hi>Souls</hi> in so wicked an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking; they are link't into that very Rebellion in which they are certain of making themselves <hi>Miserable,</hi> not only if they are <hi>Subdued,</hi> but likewise if they <hi>Conquer</hi> too. For as I said before, there's not only a certain <hi>Slavery</hi> attends their <hi>Defeat,</hi> the Impudence of such <hi>flagitious Treason</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it self alone a sufficient <hi>Provocation</hi> of Tyranny, enough to exasperate even the <hi>serenest</hi> and <hi>best Temper'd</hi> Princes into a Spirit of <hi>Cruelty,</hi> and consequently, to make him impose that <hi>Yoke</hi> upon their Rebellious Necks which they have but too justly deserved; and so put him upon <hi>Acting</hi> what other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise had never entred so much as into his <hi>Soul</hi> to <hi>Think:</hi> So on the other side, supposing their <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Fortune</hi> would prove so great and successful as should answer their most <hi>Flattering Hopes,</hi> and that it would be possible for them to gain that <hi>Absolute Triumph</hi> o're the <hi>Royal Cause,</hi> as to reach, not only the <hi>Crown,</hi> but also the <hi>Head</hi> that wears it: yet all this while what have they done, but through all the <hi>gaping Wounds</hi> of their poor <hi>Bleeding</hi> Country, through all the <hi>Horrour</hi> and <hi>Miseries</hi> of a barbarous <hi>Civil War, <hi>deposed</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>butcher'd <hi>One</hi> Imaginary Tyrant</hi> to set up possibly <hi>five hundred <hi>Real Ones.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>For as all <hi>Victorious</hi> Rebellion ends in <hi>Anarchy</hi> and <hi>Confusion,</hi> and all the <hi>Conquests, Acquisitions,</hi> and <hi>Trophies</hi> devolve into the Possession of the greatest <hi>Ringleaders</hi> of the <hi>Conspiracy,</hi> whil'st the <hi>popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar hands,</hi> the <hi>working Tools</hi> that set them up, have <hi>little</hi> or <hi>no</hi> share in the Booty. What have the deluded Wretches gain'd by the <hi>Change,</hi> but only avoided a lesser <hi>Scylla,</hi> to run into a <hi>greater Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rybdis,</hi> enslaved themselves and their Posterity to a <hi>Herd</hi> of <hi>Tyrants,</hi> to escape a <hi>single <hi>one.</hi>
               </hi> A worse Subjection than that they fear'd and fought against. A <hi>Republican Tyranny</hi> being so much more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable than a <hi>Monarchical</hi> One <hi>can</hi> be, as this has but the <hi>Ambition</hi> of <hi>One</hi> man to satisfie, and the other of <hi>Hundreds,</hi> whil'st the particular <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Avarice</hi> of each respective <hi>Dignifyed</hi> Rebel in Power, has so many <hi>seperate</hi> sinister <hi>Interests</hi> and <hi>Appetites</hi> to gratifie, and thereby our <hi>Estates</hi> and <hi>Patrimonys</hi> continually to be squeez'd and drein'd not only for the Chargeable Support of <hi>Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Armies</hi>
               </hi> that must uphold this <hi>Anarchical Constitution,</hi> but likewise be exposed to the <hi>insatiate <hi>Gorge</hi>
               </hi> of every <hi>State-Cormorant</hi> amongst them. A Tyranny so much more unsupportable than that of a <hi>Crown'd Head,</hi> as there are so many of ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>conspire</hi> and <hi>abet</hi> all the the greatest of <hi>Insolences</hi> and <hi>Injustice,</hi> and so many to <hi>divide</hi> the <hi>shame</hi> of it. A Tyranny yet so much more execrable still as every <hi>Low-born <hi>Villain</hi>
               </hi> amongst them dare stoop to all those <hi>dishonourable, abject,</hi> and <hi>sordid</hi> Deeds, that IMPERIAL <hi>Blood</hi> and ROYAL <hi>Heirs</hi> would <hi>staggar</hi> at.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>